- Well hello, hope you
have your canvas set up
and ready to go, I think we'll
do another almighty picture.
And today, I wanna do
a ridge of mountains,
rather than the jagged, sharp mountains
that we've been doing,
I wanna do a nice, smooth
little ridge of mountains,
coming down into a beautiful little lake.
So we'll start off here
with a little bit of Prussian
blue on the big brush,
there we go, just work
it into the bristles,
and we'll start right at
the top of the canvas.
OK, we'll put us a quick
little sky in here,
and we'll just move this paint
around, let it work, play.
Don't want a dead sky.
(calming piano music)
OK.
Now I've already had the
magic white on the canvas
before I started so,
we have that ready, there we go,
just nice little sky with some life in it.
Now I put just a touch of
fatal green with my color,
and we'll put in some water.
There we go.
And sort of bring all that together.
We've left a little area open
right here in the center,
so that it'll look like a sheen of light
coming across the water.
OK.
(brush splashing in water)
(brush banging on metal)
There you go, just
redecorated your living room.
Now, let's take a little
bit of the titanium white,
and just a little touch
of permanent red in it,
always like to put a little
bit of pink into my clouds,
just so it looks like a little sunshine.
And we'll do some
almighty big clouds here,
just let em work off that brush,
keep the brush moving.
Keep it moving.
You don't wanna set and
grind one spot to death,
all you'll do is end up with
huge cotton balls in the sky.
And we want nice fluffy clouds.
Leave some of these areas dark,
that'll end up being the
shadows in your cloud.
OK.
There we go.
Maybe we'll just have a little cloud
floating around up in the sky up here.
There we are.
Now maybe another nice little cloud,
with just a little touch
more pink with that one.
There, now he stands out,
we just want these to
be soft little clouds.
OK.
Now we'll take the big brush,
and very gently hypnotize this,
just work it a little bit, leave it alone.
If you overwork it,
you've killed your cloud
and you've become a cloud killer,
ooh, nothing worse than a cloud killer.
There, fluff it up a little,
and don't worry if you pull little streaks
of paint out when you do that,
because when you hypnotize
it it'll go away.
There, we'll just hypnotize
the whole thing now.
OK let's clean the brush.
(brush splashing in water)
There we go.
And let's put one more
little cloud in there.
We'll just have him right
here, just let him work around.
If you're gonna separate these two clouds,
you need the dark area in between,
so don't kill all your darker area.
There, there.
Blend him in a little bit, fluff
him up, then hypnotize him.
OK.
Now let's start working on
this ridge of mountains here.
And we're gonna take a
little blue and brown,
I wanna make sort of a grey color here,
blue, brown and white.
And your blue is a hundred
times stronger than the brown,
so use it sparingly.
There we go.
Now, let's just take in, lay
us in a nice little ridge here,
and we're really pushing
this into the canvas,
work it hard, working hard.
Push, you're not gonna hurt that canvas.
Just a few little bumps
here and there on top.
We really push that color
into the canvas, there.
Now we take the big brush,
and we'll pull this downward.
There we go.
Get rid of all that excess paint.
And it's blending with the
magic white as you pull it down,
and automatically it gets lighter in value
toward the bottom.
OK.
OK, let's clean the old brush.
(brush banging on metal)
There we are.
Now, let's take a little bit of white,
and I'm gonna grey it a little bit,
just to make it a little bit duller.
And over here I'm gonna make
up a little shadow color,
and it's brown, white
and a little bit of blue,
so we can work back and forth
between highlights and shadows.
Little bitty, little
little bitty roll of paint
on your knife, almost no paint.
Want this to be very subdued.
There we go.
There, just let this come on down,
this should look almost like cliffs.
Just with a light striking here and there.
OK.
Little bit of the shadow
color played here and there.
I think you'll find that,
doing these kind of mountains,
are a little more difficult
than the other ones
we were doing, where we used more paint.
These here, almost non-existent
when it comes to paint.
OK.
Then we'll take the big
brush and diffuse this,
make it even softer, push
it even farther back.
Like so.
Really pushing back.
OK maybe we'll put a little ridge
coming right around here sorta.
There we go.
You could spend all day
just playing with mountains,
and it's a super, super way to learn,
so, if you have an old
canvas around take it,
and just do nothing but
mountains on it, the whole thing.
It really, really will
make friend of that knife
by the time you're finished.
And it'll help you to
understand mountains,
everybody's not as fortunate
as I who can live in Alaska
where you can look out your window
and view mountains that most
people only see in pictures.
Alrighty, let's bring this down,
maybe we'll just have
it come right into here.
There we go.
OK, and if you don't have
mountains outside of your window,
you can buy a lot of books
that have pictures in it,
and examples, and after a
very short period of time
you'll begin making these
up in your own mind,
you no longer have to worry about copying,
but copying is a way to start.
In here we're trying
to give you something,
just sorta as a guideline to go by,
and to make your own vision,
and to put it on canvas.
So don't worry about
trying to copy exactly
what I'm doing here, do what you wanna do,
put your feelings into it,
your heart, it's your world.
OK.
And maybe a few little
things here and there.
A few little shadows.
And maybe we'll just
change some of these angles
here a little, there we
go, I like that better.
See it's your mountain, you can change it.
You can change it anyway
you want him to be.
We'll put some little
shadows here and there,
just to make some little
projections coming out,
wherever you want em.
OK.
Now, let's diffuse this,
lay it in the mist here.
Very soft.
Now I must take a little magic
white, little magic white.
We need a thinner paint,
if we're gonna make
some happy little clouds
that just sort of float
down over the mountain here,
and maybe we'll just
take this one right here,
and just let him float right
on down over the mountain.
Now, it's essential that you
have a thick paint on first,
it is essential, absolutely necessary,
or all you do is make mud here.
OK maybe there's a little cloud
just floating right down through there.
OK.
We just lay these clouds where we want em.
Heck, maybe this one
comes down over here too.
Very thin paint, can't stress that enough.
OK.
Now, very, very gently,
a hair just about touches,
not quite, just about.
There we go.
And then we'll hypnotize
it, ever so lightly.
Super, super lightly, there.
See how easy it is to put clouds
just drifting right over the mountain?
(brush splashing in water)
OK.
Now then, let's take, let's
take a little sap green,
and a little brown mixed together.
OK let's see here, let's take,
oh got a big old hair, and it
ain't right here on the brush.
If you get a hair on the canvas,
just take the corner of your
brush, and lift it right off.
No big deal.
If you take your finger and start picking
you'll destroy your whole picture
trying to get that one little
son of a gun off there.
OK now, we'll just lay in some color here,
maybe I'll add just a little
touch of blue to that.
Yeah, I like that better.
There we go.
OK, now then, we can
take and grab the hold
of a little bit of that, pull it down,
instant reflections, instant reflections.
Pull that across.
OK, now we can highlight a little bit,
we'll take a little
bit of the magic white,
a little yellow and a
touch of thalo green.
Nice bright little green here.
And, they'll lay in
some nice little things
happening all over the place.
There we go.
OK let's reflect a
little bit of that color
right down into the water here.
OK.
Now, let's mix up some
blue, and some brown,
and some sap green, and
you want this very dark,
it looks black.
And, we'll use the
almighty fan brush today,
make some little trees in the background.
We've used just about every brush here,
so just show you how you can make
some beautiful little trees with this.
And you just sort of let
em fall of the brush,
back and forth, shape your
tree, and lay em in there.
Maybe we'll put one a little higher,
that way we'll put the cloud,
that little cloud that's floating
in front of the mountain,
we'll put him behind the tree.
There we go.
These are fun little trees
to make, just let em happen.
OK, maybe one over here.
His top got bent a little bit,
maybe airplane went too
close and clipped him.
In Alaska that's not unusual,
they have some crazy
old bush pilots up there
that run over everything.
Friend of mine brought back a
12-foot tree hanging on his,
back of his airplane.
OK maybe a little baby one over here.
OK.
Then we'll just pull that
down into the reflections,
very gently,
like so.
Alright.
Now we'll take some magic white,
and a little bit of Van Dyke brown,
a little touch of yellow,
just to make sort of a dirt
color, sandy little color,
and we'll lay in some
little waterlines back here.
And maybe we'll have a
little beach comes down.
There, and that just
run around the corner.
OK, there you goes.
We'll take a dry brush, and
we lift this just a touch,
this is a thinner paint
so it'll move on top
of the other without destroying.
OK, now just some straight magic white
and we'll sparkle this up a little bit.
OK.
We'll put a few little sticks
and stems here and there.
OK, time to move forward in this picture.
We'll mix us up a little more dark color.
OK.
Let's put some paint
on the one-inch brush,
and build us another tree here.
Maybe we got a nice evergreen
that's growing right up through here.
There you go son.
Just let him drip out of the brush.
And we'll give him a little friend.
There,
we go, alright.
Now, let's just put
some little bushy trees
right in here, like this,
some little reflections underneath.
Pull those down.
OK.
And we'll put some
little trunk indicators,
just here and there.
Alrighty, now we can highlight that.
And we'll throw a nice
little green bush right here.
There's a nice little tree.
OK,
there.
We'll reflect those right
down into the water.
And give them a little pull.
OK, little Van Dyke brown,
and we'll put some soil in here,
and we'll just sort of
let this come around.
Then a little brown and
white, a highlighty,
make him look like stones and stuff.
Few little bushes that
travel down, there we go.
There we go.
OK.
And we'll put a little
waterline under here,
and this is still water
so it has to be flat,
all these lines have to be straight.
Go anywhere you wanna go with them
but they have to basically be straight,
or your water's gonna
run out of your picture,
you're gonna have to get a
bucket and put it under one end.
Let's put a few little
sticks here and there.
Alright.
Now, let's take some brown, and do this,
shwip, just let this go.
OK.
Really pushing that into the canvas,
really pushing it.
OK.
And we take a little
white, a little brown,
a little touch of blue into it here.
And we'll just do this, shwoo.
Turn it into some nice dirt area.
OK.
Now then,
let us build a tree right here.
Nice tree, there we go.
This is just our dark color
that we've used before,
blue and brown and a little sap green.
Maybe we need a little bush
right in here somewhere,
just to break it up.
A little bush out here.
Maybe we'll put a little bush right there.
OK.
Add in some little trunks.
Like so.
And we'll put some little
highlights on here.
OK.
(brush splashing in water)
(brush banging on metal)
And, there we are.
Some little things happening on this bush.
OK.
And we'll have some
little bushes over here.
Maybe we have a little path that sort of,
just comes through here.
Just a little dark area.
That'll bring it down to it.
OK, let's see what we can do here.
Let's have a nice tree right here,
heading on right up through here maybe.
Put his other side on,
don't want a one-sided tree.
OK, they go down through here,
just let him fall down wherever.
Maybe a little one there.
Give them a little highlight.
OK.
And we'll take our dark color,
and we'll put some leaves
on that little rascal.
There.
And we'll just take,
a little more color, and
we'll highlight these.
(brush splashing in water)
(brush banging on metal)
Maybe we'll put a nice bright
little tree right here.
And a few little things down here.
This sort of gives it the indication
that the land works down that way.
OK.
Now I wanna put a few little
sticks all throughout here.
Like so.
We're just cutting through the paint here.
OK, now we'll take a dark color
and I've used a thin oil here,
and maybe we'll put a few
little things that are just,
sort of, playing around out like so.
Just here and there,
wherever you'd like em.
This is your creation.
OK, and we need to have a
old dead limb here and there.
OK maybe I'll just mix up
a dark, dark green here,
we'll just put a few little
highlights on these trees
to indicate little
lights playing on those.
There we go.
(brush splashing in water)
OK I think we'll sign that one,
and that one should be
just about finished.
There we are.
I really hope you have
enjoyed this painting,
I hope yours is complete also, if not,
hope you'll be with us next time.
And until we meet again, happy painting,
thank you very much.
(acoustic guitar music)