- Hey, welcome back.
I'm certainly glad you
could join us today.
I thought today we'd do a painting,
it's very simple, I think you'll enjoy it.
Let's start out and have
them run all the colors
across the screen that you'll
need to paint along with this.
While they're doing that, let me show you
what I've got up here today.
I have my plain old 18
by 24 inch double prime
pre-stretched canvas,
and I've just covered it
with a very thin coat of liquid white.
That's basically all.
We use 18 by 24 inch
canvas, but you use any size
that you like when you're doing yours.
I thought I'd start with
a little, just a little
two inch brush today.
I'm going to tap a little
bit of Indian yellow into it.
Don't need a lot of color,
something about like so.
Let's go up in here, and maybe
right here we'll do that.
That's all there is to it.
Okay, got that one
finished, it's that easy.
I'll go into a little bit of cad yellow.
Same way, just use a
little two inch brush.
We don't have to even do anything,
just go around the edges
without cleaning it,
touch a little bit of yellow ochre.
There, just working the yellows out here.
A little bit more of the yellow
ochre, come right on around.
Something about like that.
If you put two eyes and a
big smiley face in there,
it'd look like little orphan Annie.
There we are.
Okay.
Sort of blend those together.
That's all we're looking for today,
something about like that.
Still without cleaning
the brush, go and touch
a little bit of the alizarin crimson.
Don't need a whole bunch.
And just begin blending that together.
I want to make a sky that
looks like there's a,
maybe the sun's here,
and it's shining out,
and it's a beautiful day.
We'll do this painting
mostly in brown tones.
Sometimes it's gorgeous to do
paintings in just one tone.
There we are.
Mmm, all right.
Now, then, I want to mix up a color.
I like brown made from
sap green and alizarin crimson.
That's one of my favorite colors.
There we are, and I'm going to mix it
a little bit to the reddish side.
Just a small amount.
Normally we don't worry
about mixing color too well.
Today, I want to mix this pretty good,
because I don't want any
green streaks up in the sky.
Okay.
That ought to do it.
Wipe the old knife,
then we'll go right into
that brown that we made.
There, and we'll go up in here,
and let's begin using that.
See it?
It sort of matches all this, it sort of
works together.
It's really a gorgeous brown.
All right.
And some on the other side,
just right in there.
And then we'll finish the canvas up.
We'll just use a little vandyke brown.
Little bit on the other side.
And we're ready to wash the old brush.
As you know if you've
painted with me before,
that's really the fun part
of this whole procedure,
is just washing the brush.
This is the way, it's the way I get even
with everybody here in the
studio that picks on me.
All right.
(laughs) You can certainly
change the decor of a room
very rapidly if you're not careful.
I suggest when you do this at home,
you get a little device
called a brush beater rack.
It fits down in the bottom
of a waste paper basket,
it allows you to do all this without,
without ruining a happy marriage,
because you can certainly
do that in a heartbeat
if you cover the living room with paint.
I'm just blending all
these colors together,
like so.
All right, and then I'm going
to wash the brush again.
I'm really just looking for
excuses to wash the brush.
(laughs) There we are.
Now then, I want to
brighten that a little more,
so I'll go right into titanium white.
We just put a little
on the two inch brush.
Go right up in here.
Start in the lightest area,
and begin working outward.
We want this to be the
lightest, brightest part
of this whole painting, right here.
There.
And just begin blending that outward.
Now you can do this several times,
to achieve a desire lightness.
You can make it as light
or as bright as you want,
but once you get our here
in these dark colors,
I suggest that you clean the brush
before you bring it back into the center.
There we go.
Something about like so.
Once again, you can make it
as light as you want it
when you do your painting.
Or leave it as dark as you want.
It's really an individual thing.
Now, very lightly.
I just want to take out the brush strokes.
Now, then.
If you want to put the indication,
knock off the excess paint,
if you want to put the
indication of a little sun,
we can do a little finger
painting right there,
and just take your finger
and make a little round sun.
Those square suns sort of bother people.
Make it sort of round.
Of course, then, you have
to clean your finger,
and you beat it against
the easel the same way.
All right.
And just barely caress it,
and the indication of a little sun
will remain right there
in your sky, that easy.
See there?
It's all you need.
Okay, let's have some fun.
We're still using the same old brush,
a little white, a little
bit of that brown color
that we made out of the sap and
the alizarin mixed together.
Maybe in our world, way
back in the distance,
there's some little foothills
that live back there,
so let's do them.
All you have to do is decide
where they live in your world,
and begin tapping them in.
You know, when you paint,
tell little stories.
It makes painting easier,
it makes you understand
why things work in your painting.
Shoot, sometimes I get carried away and
maybe talk about the old
trapper that lived in the woods,
maybe fell in the river,
just crazy things like that.
But it gives you a reason
for that old, abandoned cabin
being there, or something like that.
But make up little stories.
I know, I know, you're going to say your
friends and relatives will sort of
laugh at you, standing around
talking to yourself painting,
but that's okay.
That's okay.
Now, then.
I'm going to lift gently upward,
just to make it look like
little trees are growing
on those hills, far away.
Short, little strokes,
tiny, little strokes.
There.
Just a little bit, don't need a lot.
Just a little bit.
There we are.
Maybe I'll even take a
little of the titanium white,
I'm going to put the least
little touch of Indian yelllow
in it, and just here and there,
touch it a little bit, so
it just stands out a little.
You can lighten it up a little.
There, lift upward.
But that's all I'm looking for,
just enough to make it
stand out, like the light's
zinging across there.
There.
That's all we want.
Okay.
Now, we'll use this little
number three fan brush,
take a little white, a
little more of that brown.
I want to be a little bit darker
than what we have up there,
but not a great deal yet.
All right, let's go up in here,
maybe there's a little stand of trees
that live right here.
Little group of trees.
Happy little family of trees, right there.
I don't know, you decide.
In your world, you put trees
wherever you want them,
as many as you want.
There, see?
And we can come back with
our old two-inch brush,
and we just tap a little bit.
That easy.
And create a whole other
plane in our world.
I'm going to lift up,
sort of bring it together,
make it work.
That's all there is to it.
And back to our white, with a little bit
of the Indian yellow in it,
and we can begin just
showing some little dooders
that climb up the hill like this.
This'll just show different
planes in your hill,
and that's all we're trying to do,
something about like that, lift it up.
There.
And maybe over in here, it
just sort of disappears.
We don't know where it goes.
Don't know that we even care.
Doesn't matter.
I'm just going to cover all this up
with that nice brown we made.
There.
As I say, I want this painting to have a
sort of a brown flavor to it.
I love this color,
and I like paintings that
are almost monochromatic,
just one basic color.
All right.
I'll tell you what, sometimes,
sometimes you have to get a little crazy.
Let's take a little bit of that white,
and get a little roll of paint,
right on the edge of the knife there.
Let's go up in here, and maybe
we'll just make the indication,
just by doing this,
that's all you have to do.
Just like this, just enough
so that it separates,
and we can begin putting
little things like that.
If you just rub that very hard,
and keep it pretty level,
when this is all done,
it'll look like,
well, watch, it'll look like there's a,
maybe a little river
back in here somewhere.
But it's far away.
We don't want a lot of detail in it.
Far, far away.
Just something like that.
And we'll come along, and we'll
put something in the foreground,
but maybe there's some
little rapids back here
that are slowly running over.
And it's just to give an indication.
Too far away to have
a lot of detail in it.
All right.
We don't know where it goes back here,
don't know that we even care.
Doesn't matter in our world.
Something about like that.
Okay, now.
I'm going to grab a clean,
clean two inch brush.
I'm going to take that
same brown that I made,
but this time I'm going
to add a little bit of
midnight black to it.
I want to start getting very dark.
We're getting into the foreground now,
and we need to get much darker.
But we load it the same
way, scooping here.
Okay, bravery test.
Maybe.
Let's put some nice, dark color in here.
Very dark.
You need dark in order to show light,
and that's all we're putting
this in here for right now.
The only reason we're putting it in here.
There, we'll just make a nice little hill.
See, and it pushes all
that back very, very far.
That easy.
And you can just decide
where you want this to live.
Now, you could really
put this in any old way.
I suggest you practice this tapping,
because we're going to
put grass on top of this,
and it gives you a chance
to practice those strokes,
and anytime you can practice,
it'll make your life so much easier,
and besides that, it's more fun than just
painting it on there with a paint roller.
All right.
That's coming along pretty good there.
Something about like that.
That's really all we're looking for,
it's just a dark area.
Then we'll come back,
begin putting all the beautiful
little lights in there.
All right.
This is interesting,
this is the 30th series
of "The Joy of Painting."
Shoot, there's nearly 400 shows now.
If you hadn't got a chance
to see them all in your area,
give the station you're
watching this on a call,
because they're available to them,
and if you'd like to
see them, let them know.
That's the only way they
know that you're interested.
There we go.
Something about like that.
Now, then.
Going back to my old two inch brush.
I'm going to take some sap green,
a little bit of the cad
yellow, yellow ochre,
all those beautiful
little colors, just tap.
Now, then.
Back in here, I want the indication
of a little bit of grass area,
that lives right along in here.
Something about like that, but just tap.
All you have to do is tap.
Just tap.
You decide.
About like that.
See how you can make
all those little things?
And the more you tap
it, the more it'll mix
with the color that's
already on the canvas,
and it'll get darker and
darker automatically.
Automatically.
You don't even have to worry about it.
If you want it to be
bright, don't tap much.
If you want it to be darker,
just get in there and
tap the devil out of it.
There.
All right.
Now, let's get crazy. (laughs)
You've painted with me before,
you know I really like trees.
Let's take some vandyke
brown, alizarin crimson,
and midnight black, and mix them together.
All right.
Let me wipe the old knife.
Let's grab, I'm using a number
six fan brush this time.
Number three would work
okay, doesn't matter.
Whichever one you happen to pick up.
Load it full of color.
Maybe up here on the
top of our little hill,
lives, yeah, you guessed
it, a happy little tree,
right there.
I like little trees.
They're some of the nicest
people in the country.
There, see?
There he lives.
I don't want him to be lonely.
Maybe there's a little family
up here that lives together.
What a magnificent view to set
up here and look at all day.
Mmm, I'm envious.
We'll even have a little one right there,
then we got a whole family.
Three little trees on the hill.
Now, then.
I just want to scratch in the indication
of a little tree trunk here and there,
something about like that.
That's all we need.
Take that same brown color,
maybe add a little bit
of the bright red to it.
Not much, just a little bright red.
There, maybe even a little
touch of titanium white,
just to get it to stand out a little bit.
I don't want a lot of highlights on these.
Yeah, that's plenty.
Just enough so that you get the feeling
there are some highlights.
But they don't distract.
There, this one next.
You have to decide which
tree lives in the foreground,
which tree lives back.
I think this one's right in the front.
So we do him last, so he's in front.
Hope that shows up.
Now, we can go back to our
brush that has that sap green,
a little Indian yellow, all those colors.
All the different greens, so we can begin
bringing this together.
A few little dooders back there.
But isn't that neat?
See, got a little family
of trees that sit here.
They look out over this beautiful view.
Mmm, it is gorgeous.
I'd like to live in a place,
well, I'll tell you what, why not?
If I was going to live
here, I'd need a house.
I'm not very good at sleeping on the dirt.
So, let's come right up in here,
and let's build us a little,
maybe it was a little house there.
We'll just scrape us out a basic shape,
something like so.
I want it right in front of these trees.
We'll take a little vandyke,
a little dark sienna
mixed together, and
let's just paint this in.
A quick little house.
This is just a happy little
house up here on a hill.
Like that.
There.
Gives us a nice roof.
Got to have a roof to keep the water out.
There we go, something like that.
Now, when you do yours, maybe
you want to have a house
that's different, maybe you
don't want to have a house.
Maybe you want to have a two story house.
You can do that.
Anything that you want to do.
Painting gives one almost total freedom,
at least on this piece of canvas.
A little brown and white,
no pressure.
I want this to be sort
of an old, raggedy house.
There.
As we mentioned earlier,
doing stories and stuff,
maybe there's a trapper that lived here,
and he went down to the river one day
to check his beaver trap,
and maybe he fell in.
Who knows?
Now we can do a cabin-ectomy.
In other words, just cut it off.
Get it the way we want it.
Better have a door in our cabin.
It's easier to get in and
out if you got a door.
It's hard climbing through
the window sometimes.
Here we go.
Take a little dark color,
put the indication of a few
boards and stuff on there
if you want them.
And you could have made
a log cabin just as easy.
Let's take a little red,a little white,
a little dark sienna in it.
Let's see, maybe,
yeah, why not?
Maybe this has got
little red roof on there.
It's not in too good a shape either.
Not in too good a shape, the
whole shingle's about fell off,
it's got some holes in it.
Yeah, a few little highlights,
right up here on top
where the sun's really
zinging across the top.
A few little dooders down the side here,
so it stands out.
There.
Got us a little cabin.
All right, now we can go back to our
brush with a grass color on it,
and we can begin putting
in all kinds of little
grassy areas like this,
right up here by the trees.
These trees remind me
of my little squirrel.
What'd be a good place for him to live?
I want to show you my little
squirrel one more time.
Shoot, I've showed him
to you a couple of times
in this series.
He's one of the cutest little
devils that you've ever seen.
He's Pea Pod Junior.
He likes to live in my pocket.
Of course, by the time
you get to see this,
he'll already be turned
lose, and he'll be free,
probably living in my backyard, and
he'll have a little condo
back there in a tree.
I love these little old rascals.
I raise a bunch of them
every year, turn them lose,
and they go back to nature,
where they're supposed to be.
Hope you enjoy seeing
those little rascals,
they're really special to me, and
I like to share them with my friends.
All right, maybe over in here,
okay, I see a thing happening here,
it's a place for a path, right there.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, I see it.
As you, (laughs), I'm
sorry to get excited,
as you paint, you begin
seeing things here.
They just sort of happen.
Watch here, watch here.
We take a little brown, a
little brown, and maybe,
you see the indication of a
little path coming out here,
maybe sort of disappears, comes out here,
around.
It just, these things happen.
Don't fight them when they happen.
Very quickly, you'll learn
to use anything that happens
in your painting, and it might make
some of the most interesting compositions.
A little bit of brown and white,
just a small amount, and
we can highlight a little,
just so it stands out here and there.
All right.
Tell you what we need here.
Let me find a liner brush.
Take a little paint thinner,
and we need a few little
sticks and twigs that live
right along in here.
Maybe, maybe even
something on out in here,
old stick that lives there.
Might've been a little tree there that
didn't have such a good time,
things got rough on him.
Okay, let's get crazy.
We've got a minute left here.
Take a little bit of the midnight black,
vandyke brown mixed together.
All right, bravery test.
Here it comes.
(whistling noise)
Got to make those little weird noises.
We got a happy little tree
that lives right there,
and he's got a friend, too.
See?
Now we got two little
trees that live there.
Now let's go back to our liner brush.
Need the paint thinner
though, to make the paint
very thin, so it'll literally flow
right over the top of the paint
that's already on the cavas.
Turn the bristles in there.
That brings it to a very sharp point.
There, you can see it?
See, just turn them, like that.
Now,
Now, if it's thin enough, it'll just flow
right over the top of that paint,
without mixing together.
About like that,
and you can put in all kinds
of little arms on your trees.
Just wherever you want them.
You have to decide though, like,
which one's in front?
Which one's behind?
These are decisions that
you make in your own world.
Gives you a lot of power, doesn't it?
There we are.
Okay.
You know, every day we get letters from
fantastic friends all over the country
who are picking up their
brush and trying this,
and they're saying, "You
told me I could do it,
and I never believed it until I tried.
Now I have my whole family painting."
That's so wonderful, when families
do things together,
because this is something
you can do with your spouse,
with your children,
with friends, neighbors,
or even people you want to be your friend.
It's a good way to meet new people,
because people who paint just seem to be
some of the nicest people.
There we are.
All kinds of little dooders.
And you decide, once again.
You must make these decisions.
We don't want to tell you how many limbs
to put on your tree, or even
what kind of tree to paint,
because painting is a
very individual thing.
There.
I'm going to take a little white,
a little bit of the midnight black,
paint thinner,
just mix them together a little bit,
black and white,
or white and black,
and I'm going to come right along here,
put a little highlight right
on the side of that tree.
There.
If the sun's up here, zing.
Just to make him a little
sparkler on the side there.
Something about like that.
All right, go back to our brush that's
got the sap green and
all the yellows on it.
Tap a little color.
And let's just clean up the
bottom of its foot here,
bring all that together.
Maybe, maybe there's a little
baby tree down here.
He's going to take over one day.
One day, he'll be the big tree,
but now he's just a little baby,
and I think with that,
shoot, we've about got
a finished painting.
Take a little paint thinner, a
little bit of the bright red,
and let's sign this little rascal.
Really hope you've enjoyed
this little painting.
It's a very simple little painting.
It'll work for you.
If you have time, take a
photograph and send to us.
All of us here at the
station would love to see
what you're doing.
So, until then, from all of us here,
I'd like to wish you happy painting,
and God bless, my friend.
(theme music)