hi I'm glad you could join me today you
ready to do a fantastic little painting
what come on let's do it let's start out
and have them graphically run all the
colors across the screen that you need
to do this painting with me and they'll
come across in the same order that I
have them on the palette starting with
the titanium white and working around I
thought today would do a beautiful
little winter scene I'm you know partial
to winter scene since I lived in Alaska
for so many years so let's go up here
and do it I've already covered the
canvas with a nice thin even coat of the
liquid white it's wet and select ready
to go Dan we'll start out with a little
touch of the bright red and let me say
that again a little touch it is very
strong just tap a little bit into the
two-inch brush there it's just a small
amount I guess go right up here and
maybe we'll come let's go right in here
just put in a happy little global don't
want to set this on fire all we want to
do is create a little glow right across
here be careful
once again this bright red can eat up
your whole world in just a heartbeat
there now that's mixing with a liquid
white and you get a beautiful warm glow
and maybe we'll just put a little bit
right down in here what the heck
anything we don't like we just cover up
and if we like it it's already there
without cleaning the brush same old
dirty brush I'm gonna go right into the
least little touch of Indian yellow it's
a very transparent now I'm allowing that
red that was already in the brush to mix
with the yellow there we go okay just go
back up here now right above the red
small amount of the Indian yellow and
use a little crisscross strokes little
X's and just blend all that together
it's like so very soft and very quiet we
can just take the clean off the brush
down here we don't care now then I have
some midnight black going right here I'm
going to take a little black and a
little bit of the phthalo blue and we
just mix it together right on the brush
just tap it I still have not cleaned the
brush I'm lazy if I can keep them clean
the brush boy I'm all for that can't
just go right up in here still use the
little crisscross strokes and drop in a
happy little sky yeah back and forth
gonna come right down into there like so
get a little touch more of the color I
just black the black in there just to
just a gray it a little bit alright okay
let me clean the old brush now as you
know that's my favorite part of the
paintings is cleaning this whole brush
shake off the excess just give it a nice
little wrap there okay now with just a
clean dry brush and be sure it's dry you
sure it's dry that may be one of the
biggest single problem areas we we hear
people talk about is that the brush is
not dry and they wash their painting
drip right off on the floor let me get
upset with me and I really I really want
this to work for you and I want you to
be happy with it there we go
okay very soft and gentle just so you
can blend this to any degree of softness
that you want just sort of look at it
make a decision and go for it this is
your painting your world so you can you
can create any kind of illusion that you
want on this piece of canvas let's have
some fun
take the old round brush I'm gonna go
into a little bit of the Van Dyck Brown
little dark sienna and just tap it tap
it very firmly let's go right up here
maybe right in here we back in the
distance lives a few happy little trees
just like so this would have been a good
scatter well we might do it yet we might
put a happy little cloud in there go
ahead and put these in yes like so there
we go these will be far far away okay
tell you what let's do put a little
cloud in there just want to show you how
to do that
we'll use a fan brush today go right
into the titanium white pull it through
a little lot of paint into the bristles
a lot of paint okay let's go up here
maybe right in here lives a happy little
cloud I use just the corner of the brush
turn it wiggle it normally you should do
this before you start putting your
background trees in I just changed my
mind decided I want to put a little
cloud in here but when you're doing this
at home I would I would really advise
you do it before you put your background
trees it'll save you a lot of trouble
there they have it let's take a nice
clean dry brush and I'm using just the
top corner of the two-inch brush to
blame the bottom of the clouds out
barely touching tiny little circles tiny
little circles see there
now after that bird this is a big circle
big grab it lift it upward you're still
just barely touching the canvas and then
very lightly blend the entire sky see
thanks and that here you can drop in a
happy little cloud clouds used to drive
me crazy when I was traditional painter
I'd worked for days trying to put in a
little clown I'm going back to my round
brush the dark Sienna the Van Dyck Brown
so you just really tap it in there get
tough with it
tap hard just go back up there I tell
you I'm having so much fun these little
trees yeah there's one he lives right
there we don't wanna get loneliness
giving a friend his friend lives there
whatever we're going down here we really
don't have to worry about down here yet
a little bit later we'll begin to worry
about such things but right now all
we're doing is applying some very very
basic little shapes I just want that
pinkish glow to be really shining
through the trees look at that nice tree
that lives there think about the shape
of a tree just think about it make up
little stories about trees it's a little
taller you can get carried away with
these I'd like to do trees you know
buddy travel all over the country doing
demonstrations for for PBS stations and
other fantastic groups all over the
country and it's unreal some of the
fantastic new modern equipment they've
come out with recently I was doing a
demonstration in a small town and there
was probably about 150 200 people had
showed up and they they gave me up and
tastic me microphone and it was wireless
and I didn't have any wires or anything
on and I forgot it was on so just before
the show I went to the bathroom
needless to say with a wireless mic when
I came back everybody knew her I'd
dinner
I don't even worse what I've been doing
to be careful some time all right
a basic tree lying in here if you want
to call it that we're doing is just
tapping now then let's take the script
liner brush and I'll dip it in a small
amount of paint thinner and I want this
paint to be just like water a liquid
turn that brush that pulls it to it a
nice sharp point see how sharp it is and
it has long bristles on it get scoop
here
now here and there I did a happy little
tree trunk just drop me wherever you
want maybe there's wine that lives right
there and let these old trunks just sort
of wiggle and jiggle and carry on we
don't want them all to be future
telephone poles keep it moving if you
have trouble making your paint stick add
a little more of the paint thinner
okay maybe up in this whole tree there's
a big one lives there turn that brushes
you're pulling us down turn it allow it
to pick up all the color that's
underneath there we go and we're gonna
cover up most deadly you're not really
looking for a lot of detail right here
just some basic shapes let's go over in
this one told him to be left out give
him a little trunk but maybe here's one
sticking out through there
I can't why night there maybe it goes
right I lost the canvas we don't know
where it goes all right yeah I won't
take it
another round brush and I want to begin
highlighting some of these things and
really making them stand out so start
off with a touch this is titanium white
and then I'm gonna pick up a little bit
of the phthalo blue and maybe I should
say that a little stronger a little bit
it's like the red it is very very strong
very powerful it'll eat up all the white
in the world in just a matter of a
second but to tap that brush you really
want to get a lot of paint in there a
lot of paint
okay let's go to the canvas now I want
this painting to have both some cool
colors in it and some nice warm colors
so let's cool right up here and I'm just
gonna use a top corner of the brush
to begin tapping on all kinds of little
things like it maybe I'll add a little
more white to my color so you can see it
a little better there you go there see
just all kinds of little little frosty
thanks hmm and if you have trouble
making your paint stick
I had a small amount of the liquid white
so you just sort of dip it right out
into a little liquid white and then go
back through it and because this is a
little thinner then it will stick very
easily takes a very little pressure on
the brush here maybe lives a happy
little push this is what keeps a little
rabbit warm in the winter
he's got to have a place to cut 11b be
cozy
don't worry not hearing this cold we're
gonna have snow down here then I'm going
back to my other round brush and with it
go into a little bit of yellow to the
bright red a yellow ocher CAD yellow and
then to the red okay let's go back up
here now right here with this nice glow
is I want to use some nice warm colors
just let them sort of bounce through
Jess let them bounce through add a
little more Becca there see you said all
those little things happen and work in
the layers maybe on this tree here the
lights playing through there
lucky there all those little colors
beautiful little things happen this is
all the yellows with a little bright red
now who sets our lights coming through
there over here to will Sparkle these up
with a little color still working in
layers Indian yellow a little bit of the
red just go right up here put a little
bit out in here they're so round brush
makes a fantastic little leaf effects
for distant trees I really like it for
distant trees don't want to get too much
don't like it now I'm going back to my
round brush that has the blue and the
white on it and let's begin playing some
of those colors right into it so it just
looks like a light striking over there
on the side every once a while I'm gonna
add a little bit more of the liquid
white so it sticks easy okay yeah we
just sort of let these come together all
the little warm colors and the cool
colors are all playing together there
okay let's go back over here maybe
there's a happy little tree yeah we
could just quickly drop on a few little
things here and there
think about some basic patterns just
don't throw things on at random there's
one right there wherever you are and you
can put as many or as few in your world
as you want if you want to look like
they're hanging down use more of the
brush and just tap downward it's also a
super way if you're painting weeping
willows they're beautiful trees and
they're probably one of the easiest
trees are to paint
Oh kinds of little hang you down okay
yeah well I got this old dirty brush
going here I'm just gonna pull a little
bit of this color just like so I begin
thinking about the lay of the land out
here and all we do here is just putting
in some base color we're not really
concerned about what it is at this point
it's picking up some of those Browns and
all the colors that we have in the trees
pulling all that out too but it gives
you a feeling of the lay of the land and
it gives you a starting point something
to work with okay let me find my fan
brush here I'm gonna get him and let's
begin putting in some details we'll go
right into a titanium white I touch just
a touch of the bright red okay now then
you have to make some big decisions
where is the snow let it begin playing
pulling it across see use very little
pressure and that color it's underneath
shows through and it automatically will
make beautiful shadows for you there's
always little bumps and stuff just
create all kinds of happy little things
there comes one I see one right there
then blend it out a little
yeah just like so come right now across
and you just keep going on them however
many you want there's another one just
layer after layer after layer let's have
some fun make some big decisions and
what else do we want in here maybe maybe
little cabin you know me I'm I'm crazy
about little cabins hmm
so let's try them back to you what will
we will paint the cabin let's use it
let's use a big brush today we'll take
the 2 inch brush pull it through the
paint now I'm using the dark sienna and
the Van Dyck Brown and just mix them on
the brush see when you pull it wiggle it
wiggle it both sides and then sharpen it
just like you would or a knife I just
pull it right through there and look at
the sharp edge look at that it comes to
a very sharp chisel edge okay let's go
right up here now you got to make a big
decision
where's your little cabin liver maybe
today we'll have a big old cabin yeah
I'm gonna do the back Eve first so we
just paid it off like so hello to little
more paint and then we pull it straight
down all we're doing here is applying a
base color okay we need a other side of
the house
see they just pull it down and a lot of
paint a lot of paint on them I want that
to be very strong then another side
right here straight down like that now
since our light source is coming from
here we want this side of the cabinet to
be lighter then over here so over here
be sure this side is a good and dark
real dark so it stands out nice okay now
same old dirty brush I'm gonna go right
into a little bit of the white a little
blue and just tap a little bit on the
brush see just a little on the brush
here do both sides and you can see it a
little better maybe see there can't go
back up here add it I want this to look
like old weathered wood so all I'm gonna
do is just start touching and letting it
bounce and come right down can you see
that it looks like it's old old old
looks like my house okay now I'm gonna
do the same thing I'm gonna make it
darker once again I had a little black
to it once again we want the side over
here to be darker so load a lot of paint
let's go back up there now then over
here we want the same basic thing see
just barely touching and let it work
down so it looks a hold you're sort of
touching and pushing at the same time a
little bit on this side I can't come
right
a little house is about to fall over now
then we can take the knife and work on
our perspective here a little bit we'll
see yeah you can just cut it off
whatever you want it just like so and we
need a roof on that cabin so it takes
them the titanium white we use at night
let's go right up here and lay in a
little snow-covered that simple just let
it work right down and you could take
clean this edge up make it nice and
smooth bet it overhang a little bit then
grab it and pull there you go how easy
it is to make a happy little cabin put a
little snow on this side I can have at
least least little touch of the phthalo
blue I want to make it look like here's
that edge on here
they'll blue over here just a little
blue with white tiniest tiniest little
mountain already I tell you what let's
do take the Van Dyck Brown pile without
very flat cut across and get just the
smallest little roll of paint right on
the edge of the knife I have it right
along here well just touch and make the
indication of all kind of little boards
whole weathered boards there we go
dude do the tooth dope - and you can put
as many boards and your cabin as you
want put something out here
then we could take our liner brush we're
just a little the liquid white on it
we'll put the indication of some happy
little icicles hanging off here there we
go there we go whew over on this side
every mini whatever that gives us a
little icicle this old guy he's probably
he's probably we ran out of storage
space
I'm a junk saver so maybe he had to
build him a little it lives right
there here's a side cut a roof on his
shed don't want him don't he sure to get
full of snow it'll touch you some
highlight out here very touching we need
some boards on that too okay lately
once again you can cut it off tell you
what let's do let's just let's put in a
window right here there's one Arizona
looks like two big guys don't take a
little bit of kid yellow I will just
make the indication that maybe
somebody's home the lights are on there
that easy you take a little touch of the
liquid black and just go right around
these that easy make them stand out
there we go there we know somebody's
home okay let's go back to her fan brush
and we can begin coming right in here
bringing all this together
if you pick up a little bit of that
brownish color don't worry about it
don't worry about it it makes beautiful
shadows beautiful little shadows here
all these happy little shadows just drop
on me just sort of work back and forth
between the warm and the cool colors
just all kinds of beautiful little
things happen here let me pick up a
little bit of the brown and maybe here
and there there lives a happy little
weave here in there there yes just drop
him in lift up a little bit
and you can take a look on the snow
color just reach out of there clean up
his foots and bring them all together
okay let's get crazy
why not well I can take some brown and
some black we'll throw in some crimson
shoot even the live it up a little bit
of phthalo blue we don't care long is
this good and dark let me clean my knife
and we'll take the two inch brush and
I'm gonna go right into all that dark
color just look at there pull it wiglet
bring it back to a nice sharp sharp
chisel ditch me that good chisel edge
there it is very sharp okay let's go
back up here tell you what let's do
maybe their lives right there
a great big evergreen tree he just goes
right off the top of the canvas just use
just the corner of the brush and tap as
you work down the tree add more pressure
tap harder and harder make those
bristles Bend downward may come just
bend look at that and that easy okay
they don't create our happy big tree
this is big tree and we can take another
brush and put some white on it why a
little touch of a blue there there okay
let's go back up there and let's just
put the indication of something a little
bit of snow hanging here and there don't
kill all the dark the dark is what makes
us stand out just here there
okay yeah there we can just begin
playing with some of the nice things
around here we're gonna just take a
little blue and white lift upward a
little bit and begin just bringing all
this together
see create another plane that easy that
worked right I've been there just like
so it sort of work it back and forth
they're all right now maybe maybe take
the liner brush touch of the liquid
black on it but it will stick or twig
here and there they're always sticking
up out of the snow however many you want
I'll tell you what maybe over here maybe
there's a couple over in here too like
so
drop in a few here I think that makes a
pretty nice little painting thank we'll
call that one finished in fact so from
all of us here I'd like to wish you
happy painting
god bless we'll see you next time