hi welcome back I'm glad you could join
me today today I have a special friend
with me here that I want to I want to
show him to you this is my little friend
hoot and hoots a little baby owl and he
is a character and as you can see
hooting I have the same hairdresser what
son of agains got a hair it looks just
like mine and he's just oh he's about
two weeks old now and this is his first
time in front of a camera so he's a
little nervous but I buried him from the
bird lady so I could show you that's
Diane Schaefer she lives here in Muncie
and she takes care of all these little
characters when they get hurt this one
was orphaned as I say he's about two
weeks old hey isn't he something though
beautiful little bird yeah
yeah you go to talk a little bit okay I
think we have to go to work now I'll
tell you what let's have him run all the
colors across the screen that you need
to paint along with me today I'll set
him down I'll be right back with you so
we'll just set him right over here there
we go
he still squawking grab the old pallet
as you can see today we have a canvas up
here that's I've taken black gesso and
I've sort of painted a basic shape in
here and on top of the black gesso now
we've allowed that to completely dry and
then we've taken and put transparent
color over here and that's the mixture
of we put some Van Dyke Brown a little
bit of phthalo blue and phthalo green
and I just covered it in this spot right
in here I've just put liquid white and
everything is wet and it's ready to go
so let's go tell you what let's start
out today with an old two-inch brush I'm
gonna go and pick up the least little
touch of the CAD yellow just least
little touch there we go okay now right
here at the horizon I want to put a nice
bright little area right there
that easy maybe a little touch over here
okay now then without cleaning the brush
I'm gonna go right back over and pick up
a small small amount of yellow ochre
just a little yellow ochre okay
now this right above that and lying it
to blend together we'll put that ochre
mm it's pretty already
okay once again without cleaning the
brush I'm going to go right into bright
red so we started with CAD yellow went
into yellow ochre and now we're into
bright red and just tap a little into
the bristles just tap it and then gets a
nice even distribution of color all the
way through the bristles okay now then
with the red we can go right in here
we're just using sort of little
crisscross strokes just apply a little
bit because you had the yellow when you
brush this is going to turn a beautiful
orange color there if we just blend it
right on down into the yellow ochre just
let it sort of disappear
that's pretty already I like these
colors now then once again without
cleaning the brush this is one of those
paintings I like because you don't clean
the brush a lot I'm lazy I want to write
it to phthalo blue just a small amount
of blue and once again tap the bristles
okay let's go back up here up in here
we'll put the blue there we go little
darker
I just let it blend right down to the
rib okay now we can wash your brush wash
your brush that's a fun part of all this
shake it off
cover everything in the studio now with
a nice clean dry brush you can go back
in here and just blend all this together
so you can't tell where one color stops
and the next color starts just like so
okay and that gives us a beautiful
little sky and it's very very simple now
then I'm put a little black on the brush
and then I'm going into yellow I put the
black on the brush only to make this
turn green when I touch it a little tiny
bit of the midnight black I'm going to
go and tap some color into it let's go
right back up here maybe there's a
little Hill we back here in the distance
so all we do is just tap just tap all
you're doing is touching the canvas with
a brush canvas will pull off what it
wants give you back what's left
just like the tax man he takes all what
he wants gives you what's left usually
there's not much left there all you're
doing is just tapping gently gently
tapping if you want to show maybe
another plane in here
you start with fresh color and leave a
little dark area between them and you
can create the illusion of another plane
they're that easy and you can make as
many or as few as you want in your world
hope you enjoy seeing the little
creatures I like I like to show you the
little birds and stuff we have some
birds that are grown and I I can't show
those goes head they're sort of hard to
control a little owl he's a character
it's one of the most beautiful little
birds
okay well we have little brush going
tell you what we just take maybe we'll
just tap the corner here into a little
bit of paint we'll get a little yellow
ocher little indian yellow just the
corner of it just that corner okay let's
go back up here maybe right along here
lives a happy little tree I'm just going
to take the corner that brush and just
begin creating the basic shape of little
tree there and just a little touch of
the bright red there make a rascal stand
out and sing say all you need is a big
old two inch brush little imagination
some practice you can paint fantastic
paintings beautiful little paintings
look at there this Bush lives right
there just sort of make up a scene in
your mind drop it on the canvas so
what's so nice about this style of
painting you can you can put an idea on
canvas before it escapes when I was
traditional painter I'd get an idea in
my mind and shooted by the time I got
around to painting it and spending a
week or two working on it the vision in
my mind had totally changed here you can
do it while it's fresh there all right
see now we've created a whole nother
plane right here just by doing that just
by doing that maybe tell you what to
tell you what
it helps to be a little crazy when you
do this and think up little think about
little stories and make up little things
here in my mind I think this is a
beautiful place back here to maybe have
a little cabin that lives way back over
in there so for that let's take some Van
Dyke Brown pull it out very flat we take
the old knife cut across so we have a
little roll of paint right on the edge
of the knife there you can see it good
now maybe our little cabin maybe it
lives maybe it lives right there we'll
paint the back Eve first just like so
paint the other side of the roof mmm
there where see how easy that is if you
don't make those little noises oh it
won't work for you kind of make those
little noises doop there one right down
here and that is a nice way of blocking
in your basic shape for your little
cabin and you're not committed yet you
could still change that little rascal
any way that you want to maybe it's got
a roof on it that's a use of brown and
white little bit of black in there
what makes sort of a dirty gray color
just leave your color marble like that
we don't want to over mix it once again
our little roll of paint it's most
important how you load this knife now
then just touch and get nervous here let
it go OOP OOP OOP OOP OOP OOP OOP OOP
OOP OOP see there and it makes beautiful
little shapes on your house then you
just let it just bounce right along
through there looks like little shingles
you can see far off in there maybe a
little bit out here on the other side
you'd see a little touch there now they
don't get the small knife that small
knife is fantastic for sneaking into
little places we'll take some dark
sienna a little white mix them together
but not over mix them maybe we'll put a
touch of Van Dyke Brown there too whoo I
like that that's nicely you get
beautiful colors happening right there
and when you pick up that little roll of
paint those same
colors are right they're not roll of
paint now then touch and just pull it
down barely barely grazing barely
grazing look at that see and that simple
you can paint the front of your little
house your little cabin now for the side
over here not as much light I'll hit
that so we'll add some more Van Dyck
Brown will make it darker cut off a roll
of paint same way and and and look right
there we'll put a little bit on the side
and see there you can do that it's easy
we make painting easy we show you how to
do it
the only thing you have to add is
imagination there we are
make it look like are some little boards
in there mmm kitty now we need a door
let's put a door we take straight Van
Dyck Brown you this little door right
there just come across with some brown
see you can make your doors big or as
small as you want it can take a little
touch of the white that'll just sort of
highlight the edges of it so you can see
it there right around like so shoot
maybe there's a little window in there
who knows would take a little blue
little touch of blue least little touch
it white it little we use a small edge
of the knife maybe
OOP there that's enough to give the
indication that there's a little window
in there sometimes maybe we just will
make this edge stand out a little song
add a little light color right along
this edge so it'll stand out there you
can see it better now then we want to
fix the bottom of this cabin so we can
do a cabin ectomy there you go cabin
ectomy just cut it off and you have a
nice little cabin right there
they have them let's take a little brown
little crimson then we'll go into our
yellow only put those colors on there so
when they touch the yellow you get all
these different shades don't want just
straight yellow and a lot of things
happening little SAP green too little
Indian yellow yellow ocher a tap give
the brush a little push see how that
brushing a little Ridge of paint right
out there that's what you're painting
with now then let's come back in here
and just begin barely touching and we
can add all these layers of little
grassy things that are happening there
over here on the other side the cabin
maybe this comes down like so okay tell
you why we need a way to get to this
little cabinet yeah let's take some Van
Dyck Brown go right in here just begin
pushing that like so and we want to make
this path get larger large it's hard to
see right now against the black and
it'll show up there yeah we'll have it
coming right on around maybe down in
here somewhere
hmm okay as I said this Brown it
probably won't show up a great deal
against the black background but when we
begin putting highlights in there it'll
come alive so let's begin working on
some little bushes and stuff at our back
here we just go back to the old two-inch
brushing just going to tap a little
color right into the corner of it here
again that's a nice easy way to make
some beautiful little tree in bush
shapes
maybe right back in here there lives a
nice little bush right there
see there he is you know he was there
you knew he was there look at that
and that sort of just pushes that cabin
right back into the distance there we go
now let's begin working on maybe some of
these trees here that are on the on the
sides so for that use the liner brush
and I'll go into will just use this
color right here that's a nice color
I was just brown and white we want that
paint to be very thin very thin let me
get a little more paint thinner here we
want to be sure it's a real thin like
ink turn the bristles in there all right
now maybe right up in here maybe there
lives a nice tree trunk right there turn
that brush let it wiggle and jiggle and
all kinds of things happen as it works
its way down there just keep turning it
it makes very interesting tree trunks
and you can come back in here and drop
in the indication of some little limbs
and branches and sticks and need a place
for a little owl to sit there why son of
a guns got some talons on him he'll get
you there you have to have to be very
careful with it be respectable because
he didn't realize how strong he is even
just a two week old baby out boy he's a
signer I got maybe over here see there
is another tree
maybe he's got a friend right here and
in your painting you put as many or as
few trunks as you want just sort of look
around and and each one will be
different look at your painting because
it's not going to be exactly the same as
mine the only thing we try to do here is
show you how to how to make effects how
to create certain illusions and then you
do with it whatever you want we each see
nature through different eyes so you
paint the way you see it and then it's
right and it's right the only rule that
I respect in art is if it makes you
happy then it's good you do what makes
you happy you paint scenes the way you
see them and that's when you really
really experience the joy of painting
there now we have all kinds of little
tree trunks and things happening in
there all I got that going maybe back in
these little bushes here you can make
out the indication of some little things
that are projecting up there's one and
once again you decide how many of these
live in your world and drop them in okay
tell you what let's do let's grab an old
one-inch brush here and we'll begin
putting some foliage in here going to go
up here grab a little touch of the black
and go into the green or the yellow the
little make green yellow ocher now tap
the bristles into the paint just tap
them that loads a small amount of paint
right out on the tip so you can see it
being pushed up right there right there
that's what you're after okay
now then begin thinking about shape and
form and all you have to do is just
barely touch the canvas and begin laying
in all kinds of beautiful little things
like maybe I'll make it a little bit
brighter so you can see it a little
better on TV there but now when you're
painting your picture at home you paint
it any way that you wanted if you have
trouble making your paint stick
at a small amount of the liquid white or
a little bit of paint thinner to your
brush there we go but once again the
most important thing here is worrying
about shape all the little individual
things that happen in here there we are
hmm this is one of the nicest easiest
ways of ever developed of making
beautiful beautiful little trees and
even if you've never painted before you
can do this you can do it it works we
give you everything you need here all
you need is just a little practice and a
little imagination and off you go
they're just layer after layer and don't
be in too big a hurry
just work in one section of your tree at
a time I have to be in a hurry here if I
don't get done in time Lee I have no
sense of humor why they'll get me put it
home just take your time think about one
clump of leaves one group one individual
one friend there and just layer after
layer all these beautiful things live
deep in the woods and in the trees see
somes in the back somes in the
foreground anywhere you want there we go
once again if you have trouble making
the paint stick and the least little
touch of paint thinner or liquid white
on either one the liquid white of course
will make your pain a little brighter so
if you don't want it to get any brighter
then add nothing but paint thinner there
right in there okay
little baby when lives there too now
let's go on the other side here this big
old tree that's hanging out over here
we'll give him some nice highlights
there see still working in clumps or
groups that's what makes that son of
guns stand out and save some of these
dark areas in between that's what gives
you tree depth the tree starts looking
flat chances are you've killed all those
beautiful dark areas and you can go back
and put them in because we don't make
mistakes
we just have happy accidents learn to
work with anything it happens anything
it happens okay maybe since we have that
area we'll just put some leaves right
out here some nice highlights look at
that
cherry think you could take a big old
one-inch brush and make just thousands
of beautiful little individual looking
leaves that easy you really can really
can there we go
okay shoot I brush is too slow
let's get serious here get the old 2
inch brush it does the same thing only
faster will tap a little color into it
same ol way now that let's begin
creating the lay of the land just begin
deciding where this goes as it goes away
back into the shadow area back in here
use less and less pressure let it just
sort of disappear darker darker darker
back in here this is where creature
hides back in here ask with a little
bunny rabbit lives it's quiet and dark
there we go okay just varying the colors
a little bumps and hills in your land
all kinds of happy little things in here
but start at the area this father's to
way and work continually forward forward
forward and that helps create that a
illusion of depth the illusion of
distance in your painting and to me
that's extremely important in a painting
that it has depth and distance and many
many different planes in it there we go
see but this the curvature that you
putting put in here once again that
creates the lay of the land the way the
land flows the direction of the lamb
whatever you want to call it all means
the same thing and the more you tap this
the softer it'll become it just gets
thick it'll look like velvet if you work
it enough just like velvet I'm going to
add the least little touch of liquid
white just wanna then that paint a
little tiny bit more a little bit of
liquid white there we go see that sticks
easier any time you have problems making
the stick just try adding a little bit
of liquid white or paint thinner
there we're just layer after layer after
layer this is a very simple little
painting if you've never if you've never
painted before this is a nice one to
start with because it's very easy and it
works well okay add another little
little hill right there let's go over
the other side and have some fun over
there too she we don't want this side to
have it all we'll use a little more of
the SAP green just tap that right in
there little little brush happen now
then I have to make a big decision maybe
maybe comes right down here you just
push that little cabin as far back as
you want you could come way up in here
if you wanted to and look like it's
behind the hill there we are maybe this
one comes from way over here somewhere
it just drops down
and maybe maybe maybe you want to create
maybe this is efficient a more severe
drop maybe it drops off faster than the
other side and you can do that just by
changing the angle make up little
stories in your mind once again and just
work from that there and you can turn
this so it comes toward you look like
all those little grassy and things and
little ferns that are hanging over just
layer after layer
I've probably painted 20,000 paintings
and I still get excited when I see this
work so fantastic every day I get
letters from people all over the country
who have never picked up a paintbrush in
their life and they tried this and it
works and they've experienced a whole
new world a whole new world and it makes
people happy and the people you share it
with it brings brings a lot of joy to
them it's the reason we call this a joy
of painting there I hit a little touch
of the bright red that time but see how
this is hanging over it's unbelievable
you can change these angles and create
all types of illusions kitting now and
let me find an old fan brush here we put
that Van Dyck Brown in here and we
didn't show up much now watch what
happens I'll just take a little bit of
titanium white on the fan brush just a
little now we go back up here and we
just barely touch barely touch see now
that Brown begins to show and we can
clean up the bottom of all these little
grassy areas bring it all back together
and you can make this as light and
bright as you want it just by adding
more white
you can add a little white with some
dark Sienna in it that's very pretty
ever just sort of experiment a little
the fun in painting is the experimenting
learning new things every day if you
paint for a million years the next
painting is going to be your masterpiece
you'll always see something in your
painting that you can approve and I get
letters from people all the time and
they said I did a painting and I'm not
satisfied with it
that's fantastic because that makes you
want to go do another painting you see
what would make it better I hope you're
plagued with dissatisfaction your entire
life that way you'll get better and
better and better now maybe maybe here
and there you can even see the
indication little brown and there's too
bright that way or a little stone lives
right up here climbed right up the side
like heaven you can just put anything in
here that you want okay
shoot I think we'd better have a finish
paint either I won't take a little bit
of the bright red with paint thinner and
when you go to Sandy's I get a lot of
questions about how do I sign it look
how thin this paint is I mean it's
literally it'll run you can see it
dripping right off the palate then like
ink turn the bristles in there and let's
go right up here and we'll sign this one
hope you've enjoyed is a fantastic
little painting it'll teach you a great
deal try it let me know how it works for
you that one's signed I think we're
going to call this painting finished and
on behalf of my little friend hoot that
I showed you the beginning of the show I
want to wish you happy painting
god bless I look forward to seeing you
again
you