hey welcome back certainly glad you
could spend a little time with us today
and do a fantastic little painting so I
tell you what let's get started haven't
run all the colors across the screen
that you need to paint along with me and
they'll come across in the same orders I
have them on the palette starting with
the white and working around today as
you can plainly see I have a black
canvas up here and I've just covered
this with black gesso allowed it to dry
completely and then on top of that I've
added a mixture of midnight black and a
little bit of Prussian blue
not much pression blue just enough to
give it a little bluish tint and I
thought they would do a little mountain
winter scene something let's just do it
and see what happens okay start off with
the old two-inch brush today go right
into a small amount of titanium white as
I've mentioned before these black
canvases are fantastic if you want to if
you want Atma's friends and relatives
and etc because they don't see you put
the color on top of the black it is
transparent and then when you come in
here and you add a little bit of white
just all kinds of beautiful little
things just happen and today I just want
to add a very small amount of the
titanium white just to get the
indication of a little color here and
there don't want a lot of color today
just a little I will put some clouds I
think in here so all I'm looking for is
just a little background color this one
this is behind the clouds you'll do that
first any will come in with drop in a
happy little cloud here and there
I like these black canvases because a
little bit of color shows up so strong
and so beautiful it just it sounded real
what you can do with them
you know I get letters from people every
day and they send me photographs of the
paintings that they're doing at home and
these black canvases maybe some of the
favorites and these are from people that
a lot of them have never had they've
never even suspected they had any art
talent they've never had any lessons
they just watch the shows picked up
ideas got enough confidence grab the old
brush and they're doing some beautiful
paintings and you can too you really can
let's wash the brush shake it up beat
the devil out of it
all right let's get us a 1 inch brush if
we're going to have a happy little cloud
we'll just continue to use the titanium
white just pull a little color into the
bristles now we have to make our first
major decision here where does our low
clouds live in our world
maybe yep you're right there he is I'm
just using that top corner of the brush
and just making tiny little circles just
tiny little circles tiny little circles
there you go this is saying along as you
as you're doing this think about tiny
little circles there you go okay and
blend it out look at that let's look how
color stands out on this black canvas
it's unreal it's unreal maybe there's
another little cloud he just floats
around right here whatever wherever
there we are
okay maybe a little more of the color
maybe yeah you're right
let's have another clad this this will
give us a little bit of practice doing
some happy little clouds they're a lot
of fun a lot of fun and they're very
easy to do very easy to do
maybe he comes right on we don't know
where it goes here a little fluffer
there clouds are so free so free they're
just one of the freest things in nature
maybe it comes out through here there
where's the job I want my next life only
come back get cloud and just float
around have a good time older maintain
out take a large brush and I'm very
gently just begin beginning to blend the
base of this very lightly Jesus blended
blended blending once again color shows
up so much stronger on the black
canvases much stronger than on a white
canvas there we go you can blend these
till they're dead so don't overdo it
just blend just enough to stir them up a
little bit mix about their a little bit
right in there now I beat the brush just
to remove excess paint off of it so I
don't have to clean it again then I'm
going to fluff them let them tease of
pull them this is not not a very firm
pressure on applying that just gentle
just gentle just enough to grab it move
it a little bit and very lightly very
lightly
look at that look at that I had some
fantastic little cloud look there they
stand out once again so strong from
these black canvases this black gesso is
one of the most fantastic things years
ago I used to just use black house paint
listen I've had some letters and people
they wrote and told me that didn't do
too well so the black gesso is designed
specifically for this hmm okay let's
build us a mountain let's build us a
mountain today I'm going to use just
black and vendek very own little
Prussian blue we'll throw some alizarin
crimson in there too what the heck
looking for a color that looks very dark
looks black okay cut off a little roll
of paint have it right on the edge of
the knife and then you have to make a
major decision where did your mountain
live in your world I think he's going to
live over here so let's go right up in
here and let's just drop us in a nice
big mountain nice big nut I like I like
to do mountains because it gives you
gives you a lot of experience with a
knife once you learn how to do mountains
with this knife oh it's your friend you
can do anything
maybe this comes over here and there's
another peak lives right there wherever
you want there if you can do mountains
with this knife you can do off just do
rocks stones and roads and buildings and
some of the past series we've done
entire paintings using nothing but the
knife absolutely nothing but tonight
we'll have to do some more of those type
shows it's interesting to see why can be
done just using a knife it's a little
difficult because of the time restraints
there we go now I'm just using a two
inch brush I just want to pull this down
this is an excellent way of laying out
highlights and shadows you can see those
brushstrokes in there every stroke you
make it stands out I hope you can see
those on you on your TV set but you can
lay out entire mountains just just using
the brush strokes and you're not
committed you can change it free feeted
lee literally hundreds of times but it
teaches you how to how to make your
mountain look the way you want it to
look there so we just can carry away
make all kinds of beautiful effects okay
let's put some snow on that mountain for
that I'm going to use titanium white and
put a little bit of black with it just
to dull it down just a dollar so it's
not pure white pull the paint out firmly
just really get in there and raise the
devil with it and then cut us off a
little roll of pain again you want that
to be right on the edge of the knife
okay
now that no pressure just let it touch
the canvas and Gray's all this touching
is that roller paint it just grazes the
canvas
graze it and caress it there make good
friends with it look at that that the
paint break and work for you we have a
very firm paint and it's designed
specifically for this technique and it
works so well but you need a very firm
dry paint most most important now you
have to make some big decisions where
does these Peaks live are they in the
background in the foreground we'll put
this one in the foreground like so here
we are just let them go or everyone
think about where the light would strike
Keawe takes a light use some pression
blue Prussian blue some black looking
for a gray blue color
sort of a grayish blue that's not bad
something like so once again our little
roll of paint now we can come back in
here and we can begin playing in all
cancelin shadows just follow the lay of
the mountain here say here comes one to
me looks like there's a valley right in
there so just pull it create that
illusion the illusion
there now they don't see that peak right
there I want to push it back watch here
right here you might have seen me do
this before
but it's always fun just come directly
distinctly through that and it pushes
that son-of-a-gun right on the back and
here I'm going to leave that dark so it
looks like our nice recessed area leave
some dark in there times there we go
here's a nice one and here and there
there's one you can put the indication
of shadows and it causes like little
ridges and all kinds of beautiful little
effects very simply there we go change
that let that go where we want to but
practice these mountains it will open
whole new worlds for you once you learn
to to make friends with this knife get a
little more of the titanium white with a
touch of black in it so without flat
once again our little rule of paint I
want to put a few highlights over here
on this little mountain
this reminds me of my home in Alaska
where God was having a good day when he
made Alaska so beautiful if you've never
been there your your to go see it while
it's still wild you can see more
creatures there in one day so beautiful
my favorite uncle sent me there
Uncle Sam you know he he asked me if I'd
like to go up there for a while and if
you don't go you're going to jail
you know how I'll say I'm ask you to go
but I went up there and I fell in love
with a crazy place it is so spectacular
I was born and raised in Florida I
didn't know that things like that even
existed I've never dreamed of there no
pressure
want that paint to break creats all of
those beautiful little effects just sort
of bring that together right in there
like like a little valley lives now
little mountain goat has to have a place
to go hide now then we'll take we'll
take two-inch brush and very lightly
will begin tapping always following the
angles in the mountain now I'm going to
have snow down here so it doesn't matter
if we get a little paint down here we're
going to cover it all up so don't be
worried about it don't be worried about
over here we want to follow these angles
look at the angles in your mountain and
follow them want to create that illusion
of mist beat the brush to remove excess
paint now maybe right in here
sometimes you can very gently just blend
things together here see just blend them
together it'll make it look like it's a
little misty or you're laying right
between those there bring it right on
down now very lightly two hairs and some
air grab that and lift upward gently
lift upward upward upward there over
here
follow these ankles lift it upward now
you're just lifting right in here you
don't want to lift and destroy all these
just diffuse the bottom of the mountain
so it looks like it's sitting right
there right in mist okay we wash your
sole brush give him a good scrub shake
him up cover cup of cameraman and
wearing business business
all right let's use the same old dark
color here we had some black some
Prussian blue some Van Dyck Brown
Blizzard crimson doesn't matter there's
some dark sienna we can throw that in
there whatever you have well there when
we clean the knife let's grab us a fan
brush here there
and I'm going to load it full of this
dark color that we just made full of
color a lot of paint and back in here
back in here we're going to have some
little evergreen trees that are far away
now they'll stand out against that
lighter mountain color maybe they come
down there we go
and what this just to be straight so I'm
gonna have it go uphill here a little
bit so we have some we have some
variation in our in our land make him
look a little more a little more
interesting if it goes every which way
there maybe comes right I don't up here
I don't know wherever you want it
wherever you want
I help push all those mountains back but
you need that little misty area in
between a little mystery is your
separator it keeps it keeps the
mountains and the trees apart I'm gonna
put a little bit of that shadow color
head left here and just lift up worthy
to create the the illusion a little
distant tree trunks I want this very
subdued very quiet see just shows up
good that's all now if you get one
that's too bright you don't like it all
you have to do is continue to rub it and
it'll go away it'll go away
now maybe back here true let's have some
fun
a lot of paint a lot of paint what a
messy brush I got there look at that son
of again I got paint all the way up to
the furrow that's okay
maybe back in here there lives a few
trees are closer to us and they're big
and they're strong there they are
see now if you have problems making your
paint stick over this mountain because
it's there's a lot of paint back here
add some paint thinner to your dark I'm
doing all right right here today but
sometimes you have a little problem if
that occurs just add a little thinner
because a thin paint will stick on top
of a thicker paint there and I do
realize that happens sometime people
write and tell me that they're having
some problems usually if you just add a
little paint thinner that'll cure there
you don't mention before we travel all
over the country we give painting
demonstrations and work with PBS
stations and other charity groups around
the country to help we'll make a happy
buck or two and if we get to your area
come see us shoot I'd love to have the
opportunity to meet you and talk with
you I've met with literally thousands of
people it's it's fantastic they bring
photographs of their paintings in sound
real what people are doing and if you'd
like to know what I'm going to be in
your area drop me a line just put your
name and address on my card and send it
to the address at the end of the station
they'll send it to me we maintain a
little mailing list amell I'll try to
drop your card and let you know who
we're going to be in your area well we
got a whole mess of trees going there
and then it's going to take a knife
just hearing here I know those are hard
to see but there's little lines in there
we need to brighten this picture up I'll
put some snow in it that'll that'll zing
it you find a big brush okay let's get
serious we write into titanium white now
we have color on the canvas already we
have a blue and black mixture so hungry
when we put color on get a little less
shadow color too and we put color on
there it's going to get a little darker
than what we have on the brush and we're
depending on that okay got to make a big
decision towards you snow live let's say
soon goes right let's go uphill down
likes dancing or I know you saying Bobby
made a mess this time you may be right
too I've certainly been known to do this
there we go
but we don't we don't make mistakes you
don't we have happy accidents very soon
very soon if you start painting in this
method you'll learn that there's nothing
that goes wrong and correct anything it
happens one of the things when I was
teaching classes continually that's so
good and if you were teaching this will
help you with students is if you sure
that they're there are no mistakes you
can fix everything it happens and that
really helps get you over some of that
fear well we have a lot of fear we first
touch a big old blank canvas once you
once you get over that that's when
you're really really beginning
experience enjoy a pain
there see there that's quickly well we
get a whole snow bank in there just like
so okay weirdin brush go there it is
let's have an evergreen on the other
side same old color same ol color I'm
really loading that brush full of color
a lot of paint both sides alright maybe
it is a tree that lives in our world yep
right there all right there here he
comes
there kind of just work back and forth
making the bristles Bend downward as you
work down a tree get stronger and
stronger and more and more pressure
I commend more it makes those little
things that hang under the limbs little
I call them hang you downs for lack of a
better word but they're always an
evergreen trees those little hanging
down thanks there see how this one's
closer to us and by putting trees in
different places that once again helps
create that illusion of distance though
having a little friend right there
okay now that we can reach up under here
grab some of that dark and pull it down
that creates our shadow under our tree
fixes the bottom of the tree calls one
stroke and then I'm going to take some
white and a little bit of phthalo blue I
like a phthalo blue it's a brighter blue
nice bright blue okay maybe there's a
happy little a little path need a little
more blue doesn't show up enough you see
it well there see just a little path and
lives right in there
there yes that blue makes it cold but
table blue so quite warm it's a nice
blue and here and there you can bring
some little things down the fan brush
you can really get in there and smooth
things out put little individual things
and blend them just make all kinds of
happy little things going on I'll tell
you what this is a nice place for a
little building
let's have maybe right back here against
these trees come right up here so we can
I'm gonna scrape out a basic shape just
take the knife scrape out a basic idea
of what it is that you want here just
scrape it out there we go see still not
committed at that point are you doing
just scrape it out okay take some white
let's put a roof on there need a roof
now here's a little trick so you can
come down that edge get all your lines
nice and straight and when you pull this
down then you'll have a beautiful
straight edge sneaky huh there we go now
we need a little bit of snow on the
other side of the roof over here just
like it get into some Van Dyke Brown
there we are
see there we putting in all we're doing
is blocking in some color they're just
blocking it in
now we'll take some dark sienna that's
some white very gently very gently just
pull straight down make us a nice boards
there
add a little Van Dyke Brown to that
darken it down a little more there yeah
we can just whack off the bottom get it
the way we want it you know what time
maybe I'll tell you what let's go right
up in here excuse Marvin just a second
you can see that I will put some little
things like it then we go right up here
on the top a little little bit of
winning maybe we'll just take and turn
this into a little Church this lives out
here but a little steeple right up there
just all covered with snow boy it's
really cold out here
there the snow laying all up around
there yeah maybe tell you what let's do
this maybe getting ready for a service
they've turned they turned lights on
here they've got the lights burning in
the windows so let's just creep out the
indication of some happy little windows
won't take a little bit of CAD yellow
just put in in the case of a little
light coming through those windows there
people gonna be arriving pretty soon
cold a cold day okay back to my fan
brush here that in this put some snow
right up around the foot here I can't
okay maybe tell you what maybe right
here in the foreground let's just put a
little treat and is right there hair is
give him a little friend or two
just want to put a little something here
it'll push everything back and that
helps create that illusion of distance
in your painting a little bit up a
little bit of shadow underneath should I
think with that have a a finished
painting hope this gives you some ideas
shows you what can be done black canvas
hope you enjoy our little Church in the
in the snow from all of us here happy
painting and God bless
you
Oh