Oh
hello I'm Bob Ross and I'd like to
welcome you to the joy of painting this
is a wet on wet painting technique in
each week I'll take you step-by-step
through a beautiful oil painting if
you've been with us before I'm glad to
see you again if this is your first time
with us drag up your paints in your big
brush come along and paint with us and
let's go ahead and get started and talk
a little bit about what we're going to
do up here I've already covered the
canvas with a thin even coat of liquid
white and this makes the canvas wet
makes it slick it allows us to blend
color right here on the canvas and now
I'm going to have them graphically run
all the colors across the screen that
you need to paint this project with me
it'll come across in the same order that
I have them on the palette starting with
a titanium white and working around
while they're doing that let's go on up
here and get started then we'll start
with a two inch brush today and go right
into a small amount of alizarin crimson
and just really tap the brush into the
color just tap it this assures a nice
even distribution of paint all the way
through the bristles okay let's go up
here let's go right in here and just
make little little criss-cross strokes
little X's and put in a little tiny bit
of pink just like so using very little
pressure just apply it right on the
canvas don't want that to get too bright
we don't want to set this guy on fire we
just want a little pinkish glow in this
guy okay now then I'll take the same old
dirty brush add a little more the
crimson and a tiny tiny bit of phthalo
blue proportionately we want much much
more crimson than blue I'm just mixing
this right on the brush to make a nice
lavender color that's purplish color
okay let's go up here and sort of test
it now sort of test it up here if it's
not the color you want
stop and change it you can fix it this
is your world and you can create any
type of illusion that you want here
you're the boss on this canvas you can
do anything anything okay a little more
paint
I just sort of let that play around when
a little more blue to that tiny bit more
blue there today I thought we're doing
nice painting it's very soft and very
quiet you know it'll make you happy it's
a very easy little painting there we go
that's down here I'll just clean the
brush off just like so okay then let's
clean our brush we clean our brushes
with odorless thinner and be sure it's
odorless earth
you'll be working by yourself shake off
the excess right down here I have a box
I shake the brush into then this is
where you take out all your frustrations
maybe the absolute most fun of this
whole technique okay now let's take the
clean brush and go right back up here
and just blend the sky together still
using little crisscross strokes still
using them back and forth back and forth
there we go
okay and you can blend this to any
degree of softness that you want you can
blend it till you lose all the little
variations that you have personally I
like to leave some of those in there but
when you're doing your painting you look
at it
and you do it the way that you want it
okay there we go and that quickly we
have a very effective little sky and
we'll just use long strokes here to take
out any brush marks okay and that gives
us a happy little sky now then let's
take a little bit of the phthalo blue
and the alizarin crimson we'll just mix
it together still we have a little bit
more of the crimson when we do blue
we're still working with a nice lavender
color pull it out very flat and then cut
across it so it's a small roll of paint
right on the edge of the knife there you
go okay let's go right up here maybe
there's a happy little mountain that
lives right along here you're really
pushing this paint right into the fabric
really get firm with it you're not gonna
hurt this canvas shoot they make tents
out of this tough really push it in use
a lot of pressure a lot pressure
holy the only thing you worried about is
this nice outside shape here you could
care less what's happening down here and
it gives us a basic little little
mountain shape now then let's go back to
our large brush and grab that and pull
it just pull it now that's mixing with a
liquid white and automatically it gets
lighter toward the base and if you can
see the entire mountain it should be
lighter at the bottom than it is at the
top and as we've said on previous shows
because at the bottom you have mist and
now we have pollution and these things
have a tendency to break up and diffuse
light so it looks softer at the bottom
now by just taking the knife here we can
create the illusion of highlights and
shadows just push very firmly you can
take the least little touch of titanium
white we want these mountains to be far
far away so they don't have much detail
just very barely touch smallest amount
of the titanium white and I'm rubbing it
Jane let's put a little tiny bit right
there then we can just rub that right
him
simi creates the illusion of all kind of
things happening without you actually
doing a whole bunch it keeps that
mountain looking like it's far far away
far away far away there we go maybe a
little touch right in there wherever you
just make a decision in your mountain
and put it wherever you want it and then
we can tap that you blend it a little
bit and that mountain should look just
like it's just laying there and just
floating in the sky
very soft very quiet okay let's have
some fun now maybe there's a little
footy Hill that lives right down here so
we'll just keep using this old two inch
brush I'm going to take a little blue a
little bit of crimson and I'll just mix
them right on the brush we'll add a tiny
little bit of white in there too so
we've got Lisbon crimson little bit of
phthalo blue touch it white okay and I'm
just tapping the brush just happen it
lets go right back up here maybe there's
a little foothill that lives right here
and all you needs just the corner of the
brush and just begin laying in some
basic shapes
yeah I sort of let your brush touch and
pull downward touch pull down straight
down straight down and maybe they come
right on down here wherever you want a
little more pain there we go there they
are just right on down and then I want
to create the illusion of mist right
under the bottom of this foothill so
I'll take a clean two inch brush and
we'll come right here and tap firmly if
you can hear that tapping very firmly
and that'll create the illusion of mist
at the base of these foothills just like
so and then very lightly lift upward
just lift straight up straight up and
flick it out okay maybe tell you what
maybe there's another layer of foothills
in there so let's go right into the same
color lizard crimson phthalo blue but I
wanted a little bit darker this thing is
get closer to you to landscape they
should get a little darker and value
okay let's go right back here let's
start right here and maybe we'll just
bring this one down and let it drop
there it is there it is just right on
down right on down see it's a little bit
darker so it stands out might even had
the smallest smallest touch of SAP green
to that the smallest touch I just want
to begin giving the indication of a
little green far far back here okay then
we'll take our clean dry brush and once
again I want to create that illusion to
mist down here at the bottom so we tap
it very firmly very firmly and you're
using just this area you can see see
just the top corner of the brush strike
the canvas
like so that's like it that easy you
have missed the bottom left foot hill
and then lift up right there and got
something okay
we'll wash the old brush here I like to
wash the brush that's the most fun part
course everybody's studio is covered
okay now then let's begin putting some
little things that are happening we we
back in the distance I'm going back into
this lavender color I made and add a
tiny tiny bit of SAP green just the
smallest amount and all I'm doing is
tapping the still tapping okay let's go
right up here that may be back in here
we back in here it's just a little soft
he'll lives we back here very gentle
there and we're going to put layer after
layer after layer of little Hills back
here now if you live in the Carolinas or
someplace that have the beautiful
beautiful Hills this is a super way to
make them you can make all those
beautiful mountains that you have in
that area the same way just leave this
big one out there we go a little bit
more color on the brush maybe I take
what maybe there's one it comes from
this direction
want to add a little touch more blue in
there there later that's better now we
wanted to get a little darker as they
get closer so all we're doing is just
tapping very gently okay okay little
more the green into that color and you
have to make all mighty decisions here
maybe this one comes right down there it
is look at that see now each time you do
this you're creating planes in here and
each plane that you add into your
painting makes your painting look deeper
it shows much more depth in it and of
course we're not interested in that
almighty dollar but if you should be
that's what sells the painting there we
go there we go see just layer after
layer after layer I tell you what let's
have some fun let's have some fun let me
grab a fan brush here and we'll mix up
same old color a little blue Ezreal
crimson and then went ahead a little bit
of white to that little bit of white
there we go
a little bit more than crimson good okay
a white with a knife off now we're gonna
load this fan brush full of paint just
really load it full wig lead in there
okay let's go right up here maybe back
here lives a happy little tree a little
evergreen tree now just sort of touch it
to give you a Center and then give it a
little upward push sometimes we make
evergreens by pushing down sometime by
pushing up or today I thought we'd do it
upward look at all the little things
happen there
look at that look at that cute little
tree and we don't want him to get lonely
so let's give him a happy little friend
his little friend lives right there
trees need friends too
they all all need a friend there yes
okay and you know what happens if
there's two trees sooner or later
I have little saddle the guns are gonna
get together here's a little tree he
lives right here beside him just like so
okay and you're painting you put as many
trees as you want I'm gonna put three
right there
maybe I tell you what let's have a
little tree a little tiny tree there's
right there and we make him the same way
only smaller just make him in the
smaller and go out and study trees make
friends with trees you know I talked
about going out in the woods and mm-hmm
and sitting around the dog eating trees
there's nothing wrong with that that's
the way you learned what makes a tree
look like a tree spend some time with
nature let it become your good friend
I'll put some more trees or a doubt in
there see there you'll just put trees
wherever you want them tell you what
let's do let's take this brush and see
right here at the base I'm gonna take
his brush and just begin picking up some
of that color and tapping all I'm doing
is tapping I'm going to begin adding a
little color to that little yellow ocher
little CAD yellow just very lightly and
being again creating little highlights
on all these little Hills so that I'm
all blend together just a nice soft
little meadow back here add a little
Indian yellow here in there a little
touch of bright red tiniest little
amount of the red toe
there we go just just a highlight a
little don't get carried away all right
okay and I'm just sort of mixing all of
these yellows and Red's together on the
brush there we are there see how that
begins to soften and increase the
illusion of depth that's what we're
looking for all right I'll tell you what
let's go back into this same old color
the blue and the crimson and the white
get the old brush all loaded up here a
lot of paint tiles go back up here maybe
in here some more little trees just give
it a little push upward and once again
in your painting you put as many or as
few trees as you want but the more you
make the more practice you get and if
there's a secret to painting it's
practice it's practice the more you
paint the easier it becomes it's like
anything else when you first first
started tying your shoe probably
probably didn't work first time you had
to practice it a few times and now you
can do it without even looking it was
the same way with painting pretty soon
you can do it and it's almost oh it just
happens you don't have to worry about
how to load this brush you can spend
your thinking time worrying about
composition and and begin looking at
things in the painting that's when it's
fine that's when you truly experience
the joy of painting maybe tell you what
maybe right here this old tree he didn't
make it in nature you have trees that oh
maybe maybe somebody stepped on him when
he's little and they got a little uh
little herd in them and they died but
you had dead trees in nature too so put
some of those in your painting it makes
them look real okay we'll just drop it
not a little tree of two okay then once
again we just grab the bottom of that
and let it go tap it then we can take
our liner brush you know use a little
bit of the liquid black on it just put a
little indication here and there have a
fuel fuel looms that are still hanging
off these dead trees back here and that
easy
we got her okay
yeah then takes more blue and some more
crimson there we go all right
let's let's come right down here and
here comes another hill and all we're
doing is initially laying in the base
color a dark color just like so don't
cover it completely leave some of these
areas that are light in here these will
create all kinds of beautiful effects
when you're finished and as you know if
you've painted with us before we don't
make mistakes we have happy accidents so
learn to work with these things anything
that happens learn to use it learn to
use it let it be your friend sometimes
you have a tendency to fight painting
and just just work with whatever happens
whatever happens here we go seeing you
begin again creating the curvature of
the land here or the lay of the land
just sort of let your mind wander and
enjoy painting should make you happy
should really make you happy there you
know the one thing if painting teaches
you nothing else it teaches you to look
at nature I get letters every day for
fantastic people that say Baba I've
looked at the tree in my front yard ever
since it was a little baby and I've
never really seen until I started
painting and that's true that's so true
painting it teaches you to see to
appreciate pretty soon here you're
heading down the street and you say oh
my gosh look at that tree a trees made
of sap green with a little blue in it or
that cloud can be done with a fan brush
of course you had to be careful you're
wrecked a car when you're doing things
like yeah but okay I'm going to add the
least little touch of white and a little
bit of red right on the brush just
tapping it in just tapping okay maybe
there's a little light that plays right
through here what is to be a little
bright area right in there so I'm gonna
do is just sort of tap that on it maybe
like right there right there
all right there I'm just taking go right
into a little bit of yellow and a little
green to that and I'm using all the
yellows here little touch of the red
touch of the reasons very strong okay
let's go back up here now then we can
begin just tapping on some highlights
here see
and begin once again begin thinking
about the lay of the land
just sort of let it flow because on this
piece of canvas you can create anything
anything there we go see now if you want
to create little Hills it should be
brighter on top than it is down here and
that gives you illusion of a little Hill
like a light striking apparently to get
darker darker darker darker as it works
down there you go hmm
you know I've painted thousands and
thousands of paintings and I still get
excited when I see at work
it's so fantastic and I don't look at
all the little hills and little ridges
and you can do it you can do it see a
little bright areas just it just shows
up little Sun striking right through
there pretty when it's done in touch
right there okay less really has some
fun yeah I'm gonna go right into the the
midnight black and I'm gonna add a
little bit of Van Dyke Brown just mix it
right on the brush a lot of paint a lot
of paint okay let's go up here maybe
there's some some big trees that live in
here and I think one lives right there
and all I'm gonna do is just tap just
tap to come right down like so
just tap it in and I have several fan
brushes going here so I don't have to
wash them take a little bit of the white
right on this brush and watch here we're
gonna come right down this edge right
down the edge and we'll put some
highlight right on that tree and that
easy that easy you have a nice strong
tree trunk oh that was fun let's do
another let's do another insane color
little brown black
now you had to make a decision where is
the trees live in your painting I know
right there dairy cows
and all these trees aren't perfectly
straight like telephone poles let them
let them have a little character trees
are like people each one has has its own
individual personality Oh field or to be
one right there right across the
mountain every tree is different
once again spend some time with nature
go out and go out and talk to a tree
don't matter people thank you crazy us
painters you know they think we're a
little weird anyway that's all right
that's all right tell you what maybe
okay right here we'll have a smaller
tree that lives right here on this
little hill we'll push him back I can't
can't go over the other side here we
don't want this side to have all the
trees so we'll put there's one right
there
OOP just drop it off this is just black
with brown huh big one right there big
ole tree a little more of the brown
bagel tree he comes right down my cabin
hey there
okay easy they were to make and we'll
take our other fan breast it has the
white on it and very quickly you can
just go right along here and dis drop on
a little bit of highlight remember which
side the lights coming from and if
you're right-handed
it's normally easier to have the light
coming from the right
left-handed it'll vary from person to
person okay let's go right along here
mmm let's drop on some little things
like so 10 specs though hmm can't let's
take a liner brush and I'm gonna put a
little bit of the liquid black out here
on my palate take our liner brush and
I'm add a little tiny bit of thinner to
it so it's a very thin turn that brush
bring it to a nice point let's go right
here now then here and there just drop
on a few happy little limbs little arms
on the trees yeah trees got some arms
see just wherever you think they should
live you know pine trees always have old
broken ones all over look at that look
at that this is just liquid black with a
little bit of thinner here and you can
put as many or as few as you want if you
back in here we don't want this old tree
to be left out there here we go okay
let's go over here
put a little bit ah right there right
there but this is a very nice painting
if it's your first painting project it's
works very well if you've painted with
me before it's a paint you'll give you a
lot of fun but there gives us a few
indications of some limbs yeah then
let's take let's take the old fan brush
I'm gonna use some of the black still
and we'll drop a few little leaves on
these trees okay let's go right up here
now we touch and give it a little upward
push make little smiley faces yeah sort
of
make a decision where you think they
live off of me drop em in
maybe look here a few on this old tree
plus like that let's put a few in this
little tree leave some of the old trunk
showing some on this one hmm all kinds
of things happening and just let them go
yes let them go
I'll give this trees out there si all
kinds of leaves here and that's some of
the sky show through and I'm over right
into a little bit of the SAP green with
a touch of yellow on it and come back
and very gently I like some of these and
that easy you have a beautiful tree and
I think with that we just about have a
finished painting so I think we'll call
that one done and from all of us here
I'd like to wish you happy painting
god bless and we'll see you next time
Oh
you