- Hi, welcome back.
Certainly glad you could join us today,
because today we're going to
have just a fantastic time.
Let's start out and have
'em run all the colors
across the screen, that you
need to paint along with us.
While they're doing that,
let me show you what's happening up here.
I thought today I'd show ya
how to use a black, white and grey gesso
to make a fantastic effect.
Now I've taken these
three colors of gesso,
and using an old liner brush,
one that I didn't care anything about,
I've just made some little tree shapes.
That's all there is to it.
You just pull it down with a liner brush,
make a little limb here and there,
and then take the liner brush sidewards,
and put in these little fluffy areas.
It sorta looks like leaves.
But that's really all there is to it.
After it's totally dry, completely dry,
I've covered the entire canvas with
a very thin coat of Liquid Clear.
Now clear is transparent,
and you have a tendency
to put too much of it on.
If you have any doubt in your mind,
and you think you may have too much,
take a paper towel and
wipe your canvas down.
What's left will be just right.
Tell you what, let's do it.
This is a fun painting
that anybody can do.
This is a good one.
If it's your first or second painting,
this is wonderful.
If you've painted before,
this is one that'll, it
will certainly excite you.
I'll start with a little Phthalo Blue.
It's a beautiful,
beautiful blue, I love it.
Think it's one of the
nicest colors that we have.
Just put a little in the two inch brush,
and let's go up in here.
There's not a lot of paint on the brush.
And I'm just gonna start
and just make my little
criss-cross strokes, as usual,
and paint right over this.
And fantastic things will happen.
Look at that.
Already, it looks like, it looks like
the sky is showing
right through the trees.
This is one of the neatest effects.
And it's not limited to this,
you can do anything with this gesso.
There.
And where the canvas is dark,
I've used lighter gesso, and vice versa.
Look at there,
see already we have a basic background in,
and done.
Let's see, while I got
that blue on my brush,
I'm gonna add a little
more of the Prussian Blue,
cause it's stronger, it'll
go right over the top.
In the corners, I'm gonna darken a little,
with Prussian Blue.
Prussian Blue is much stronger.
Much deeper.
See there, there we go.
Just the corners though.
And that, in turn, will
make this look brighter.
If you make this darker,
this gets lighter.
Now,
we've got Prussian Blue on the brush.
I'll just sort of rub a little of that
right here on the canvas.
I know you can't see anything,
but when we put a little color on there,
beautiful things will happen.
There.
Alright, ready to wash the old brush?
That's the fun part.
Let's wash it.
As you know, we wash our brushes
with odorless paint thinner
Just scrub 'em off, give it a good shake.
(brush thuds)
(laughs) And cover the entire studio.
That's really the fun part of it.
Now sometimes,
when you're walking in the woods,
which I do quite frequently,
and you look out and you see
the light coming through,
it's so bright, it just, it
burns right through the trees.
Watch, watch, it's easier to show you.
Take the brush,
I'm just gonna take one corner.
Just one corner.
That's a beautiful close-up there.
One corner,
and get a little Titanium White on it.
Now come up here.
Decide where the sun's at back there,
shining through all these trees.
And very lightly just begin,
that light area, and begin working around.
Notice that we're keeping that corner
in the light spot.
And we work around and
around and around we go,
there we are, see there?
And begin blending outward.
Now this paint is very opaque.
We've used transparent color up until now,
and now we're getting into opaque color.
But that sun's burning through there.
Light's just zinging right through.
But by blending it out,
it'll become transparent enough
that you can still see the
tree shapes through there.
That's what we're trying to achieve.
To me, that's what it
looks like when I see
the sun shining through.
There.
You can still make out the
images of the trees in there,
but they're washed out.
The same as if you're looking at 'em
in the woods, and the
sun shinings through.
Just like that, and we
can blend a little light
right on down through here.
Up to you, up to you,
you decide where it lives.
You decide.
There.
Now you could do this several times
to achieve a desired lightness,
or a desired brightness.
This is about all that I want.
I just want that nice spot
shining through there strong.
I like that when that happens.
Okay.
(brush thuds)
Actually, I just wanted
to clean the brush again.
Already, we're in business.
Now we have to make some big decision.
What's happening here in our world?
Let's take some black,
and some Prussian Blue.
I'll be right back, I'm
gonna get a little crimson
and put in there too.
Tell you what, maybe even a
little Sap Green, a little brown
a little Van Dyke,
just all the dark colors,
it doesn't matter.
Okay, let's go up here.
Now in my mind,
I see back in here,
maybe a little grassy area that lives
right underneath these trees,
so I'll just tap them a little dark.
Don't need much because the black gesso
has created most of it.
We don't have to worry about it.
About like that, that's
all we're looking for.
There.
Just let it disappear back in there.
Hmm, okay.
Same brush, I'm gonna go
right into some Cad Yellow,
some Yellow Ochre.
Let's just load some
color on the brush here.
Tap it, push it, give
it a little (grunts).
See that little ridge
of paint right there?
It's what we're looking for.
Let's go back up here.
Now we can come back with
this beautiful green color,
and just begin tapping in the indication
of some little grassy
areas that live far away.
Far away, very soft.
Very soft.
There, sneak 'em around
some of those trees.
There.
Reload the brush as you need it.
Alright, but very gently.
All you do is barely touching the canvas.
Color shows up, it seems
like 100 times better,
stronger on a black canvas than it does
on a white canvas.
It's amazing what happens to color.
There.
See, wherever you want 'em to be.
Wherever.
Maybe, maybe a little,
a little projection
sticks out right there.
Maybe, maybe, maybe.
We can make a little bump,
just by doing that,
whatever you want, you decide.
Alright.
Now, I'm gonna grab
another two inch brush,
I have several of 'em.
(brush thuds)
Make sure it's good and dry.
Small amount of Titanium White on it.
Now we put color on here.
Even though it doesn't look like it,
there's a little bit of
that blue that we put on.
Very gently pull down.
Don't put a lot of color on here.
It shows up, once again, so bright.
You need very, very
little white to do this.
Very little.
And it's important that
you pull it straight down.
Straight down, okay.
Then we go across.
Just enough to make it look like
a little watery area under here.
Now you could just as easy have painted
those trees with the gesso in the water,
and reflected 'em.
I think in the last
series, or series before,
I sorta lose track of them,
I think we done that, and it's gorgeous.
You can do it.
Now, shoot, that worked pretty good.
I'm gonna go back and get some dark.
That was black, blue and
oh, crimson, whatever.
I want another one over here.
I like that one so well.
Look at here, we'll just
put us another little
little projection that comes
right out through here.
Little dark color in there.
There.
Okay, back into our yellows,
Indian, Yellow Ochre.
Cadmium Yellow.
Also I hit a Bright
Red, believe it or not,
red will dull the color,
cause red and green make brown.
So every once in a while,
I hit a little bit of the Bright Red,
sometimes more to dull
than to make things bright.
There.
Just begin forming this.
Just begin working with it.
Think about the lay of the land.
Just drop those little devils in there.
They're everywhere.
There.
But isn't that gesso,
it's one of the most fantastic ideas
we've ever come up with.
Colored gessos are really wonderful.
There.
Don't know why we didn't
do this a long time ago,
it makes like so much
easier when you're painting.
And you can put things in like,
like if you wanted to paint
a little house or a building,
you could do it all with the gesso,
and then basically, all you need to do is
just take, put some clear over it,
come back with a little color.
And it's there, that quick.
(snaps fingers)
Take a little bit of the,
little bit of the Titanium White,
and I'm gonna put a little
touch of reflection under here.
Just a touch, just a touch.
Don't want a lot.
Want to keep this pretty dark,
so that light area back
here really shines.
There we go.
About like that, then once again,
just go across, just go across,
that's all there is to it.
Isn't that easy?
I knew you'd like this one.
I think it's one of my favorite paintings
in the whole series.
It's so easy, it's great for people who
are just beginning to paint,
and just beginning to
experience The Joy of Painting.
Hey, there's a commercial!
Alright, let's put some stones in there.
We'll put some little stones.
I'm gonna take some,
I'm gonna take some black
and a little Van Dyke Brown,
put it in there, just mix it up real good.
Little Dark Sienna too, what the heck,
little more of the Sienna.
Okay, Now I'm gonna go over here,
and get some paint thinner.
I'm gonna thin this paint
down, til it's very thin.
Remember our golden rule,
a thin paint will stick to a thick paint.
We'll thin that down.
There, that's good.
That's good, let me clean the knife.
We'll take some white,
oh, we'll use a little Dark Sienna,
a little Van Dyke Brown,
I'm gonna make a highlight
color for the rocks.
Oh, I like that, that's good.
It's not too bright.
Okay, do the same thing again.
I'm gonna thin this
paint with paint thinner,
til it's pretty thin, pretty thin.
It's about the consistency
of soft face cream.
Or butter that you've left out.
You know, sometime you
leave the butter out,
it gets real soft and gooey,
that's what we're looking for.
Okay, let me clean off my knife.
Now probably the easiest
way I've ever found
of making very effective little stones,
is using a little Filbert brush.
Okay, and let's go through
the dark color first.
Both sides, okay, stay right there
and I'll bring the light up.
We have both sides full of dark.
I'm gonna take only one
side, and go through light.
So we have light, dark, light, dark.
Now we can go back in here,
and you have to make big decisions.
Where does all these
little rocks and stones
live in your world?
You can put a million of 'em in.
Or one or two, it's up to you.
I like little stones.
This is the easiest way,
there he is, that I know of
to put them in there.
Maybe over here, they're
getting a little bigger.
Big old rock.
But in one stroke, you can put
the top and the bottom of the rock in,
that easy.
Let's put some on the other side.
We don't want him left out.
There.
Look at all those little rocks.
I used to agonize over rocks,
trying to get them in there,
worked myself to death.
And, you see how easy it is.
If you want great big rocks,
then use our little oval brush.
The one that just jumps right in there.
I'm gonna take a little liner brush,
a little bit of white,
a little blue in it,
a little Phthalo Blue in it.
Mostly white.
Instead of using the knife today,
I'm just gonna take the liner brush,
and just here and there,
sort of work a little water
line right around the stones,
like that, look at there,
just let it wander around.
Wherever you want it.
It just cleans up the edge,
and the bottom of these little rocks.
There.
See there, then they can
come on out through here,
they can be a few little things.
You could do this with a
knife if you wanted to.
I thought today, we'll just do
it with a little liner brush.
But you need a thin paint.
So it'll just zip right over there.
There we go.
Something like that, when you do yours,
take your time and really,
really do 'em nice.
We're a little pressed for time here,
so I have to do it a little quicker.
But when you do it,
just enjoy it, enjoy it.
Alright.
We gotta put something
in our foreground here.
We'll just go back to our brush that's
got all that dark on it.
We had blue and black and some brown.
See, Sap Green, Alizarin Crimson,
bravery test, (blows air).
Maybe in our world it comes
right across like that.
There, just tap that in.
Just tap it in.
Fill it up.
Fill it up, a lot of
good dark color in there.
There.
Now then.
Okay.
Let's go into our yellow,
same thing as we did before.
I'm just gonna do the same basic thing.
Get some green here.
By taking that color we had on the brush
and going into yellow,
automatically, we get green.
And then we can begin
just putting all kinds
of little grassy areas back in here.
There they come, there they come.
If you just take your time,
and you keep tapping this,
it'll get so smooth, you
almost can't believe it.
There.
Just little soft grassy areas.
There they go, right on out.
There, a little more paint on the brush.
Alright.
Just keep working it
back and forth though.
Something like that.
Okay.
Just sort of let your imagination go.
Painting is so great,
because your imagination
on that piece of canvas
can become reality.
Can become reality, and sometimes,
we all need to escape from reality.
This is the place to do it.
Here, everything's peaceful and quiet.
There's no bad things here,
these are happy places here.
Now, watch here, watch here, watch.
Sometimes, come right up in here.
Sometimes it's fun to take this brush,
put it up here, and give it
a little upward push, watch.
Bloop, see that little grassy area?
Bloop, bloop, bloop, bloop.
That's all there is to it.
Gotta make those noises
though, or it doesn't work.
There, just like that.
Maybe the grass over
here is a little taller.
You work in layers.
There.
And we can go back to just tapping.
Like that.
There.
And then maybe, bloop, yep you're right,
there's another, bloop, bloop.
A little glassy area right there.
Wherever you want 'em.
And over here, it's much softer.
Much, much softer.
Over here's where you'd wanna,
you wanna take your shoes off,
and run through there with naked foots.
That'd be fun, I like the feel of grass
on the bottom of my feet with no shoes on.
I think that's a neat feeling.
There.
When we were kids, my brother Jim and I,
we used to run all through
the woods in Florida.
Shoot, we were tough, we didn't
even wear shoes back then.
Probably because we didn't have any.
Bloop.
More little grassy areas, there.
Just as many as you want.
You know what we need?
You know, don't ya?
We need a tree.
Let's take some Van Dyke,
a little Dark Sienna,
mix them together with an old fan brush.
And let's have a bravery test, right now.
(laughs) Here we go.
I want a tree that lives right there.
Oh, right through the pretty rocks.
It's okay, we know they're back there.
Just pull it through, (blows air).
Like that.
Big strong tree.
See, it just keeps growing.
Can always make them bigger.
Sometimes, it's a son of a gun to try
to make them smaller,
but you can always make them bigger.
Put a big old foot on him out here,
so he has something to stand on.
There.
Tell you what, let's just
use a little Filbert.
We'll take a little white, a little brown.
And just, just let that
work right down the edge.
That's too bright, I don't
like that, too bright.
Let me darken it up a little.
Too bright, oh that's much better.
That's much better.
See, if you don't like
something, change it.
In your world, you have
that kind of power.
You can do anything.
Anything.
There, see it gives the impression
of an old rough mean tree
lives out here. (growls)
There he is, we need
some arms on our tree.
Let me wipe that color off.
Liner brush, there he is.
Little paint thinner,
little Van Dyke Brown.
There we go.
And in our world, there's
an arm lives on this tree.
Right there, there he is.
Put a few arms, let's put
some leaves on this tree,
so we don't have to put many arms.
Maybe there's one that
hangs off here that, mmm,
there.
Now let's put a few leaves on there.
We get a fan brush,
take some dark color, black, blue.
Maybe a little Sap Green,
and crimson in it too.
And our world, there it is.
Push in a little dark first.
There, don't wanna
cover up all that trunk,
but some of it.
There we go.
Gives us an idea of where
some nice limbs are.
I'm gonna go right into
the yellow with that color,
since it had blue in it,
we'll have instant green.
There, and push upward again.
Sometime we push down,
sometime upward.
Let me get a little more color on here.
It's up to you.
Up to you, there it comes.
See, don't want to get
too much of this in here.
Just enough to make
this old tree stand out
and sing in the sunshine.
Right there.
There it is.
There.
Okay.
Now we can take our old
number two inch brush right
here, and put a little grass
around his foots.
I'm still feeling crazy,
and I got a minute left.
I like to do this because it,
it upsets my director when
we're getting low on time,
and I do something like (whistles).
Maybe there's an old
tree, fell down. (laughs)
This old tree just fell
down, it was tired.
He's a tired old tree,
and I can relate to that.
Put a little highlight
along his edge here.
Just use a little brown and white.
That was just Van Dyke
Brown we made him with,
just like the one standing up.
This one, this one he's
laying down on the job.
Laying down on the job.
That's okay, he had a long life.
Now he wants to rest.
We'll put a few old limbs
that are still on here.
Some coming out from
the side, and going out.
There, if you had trouble
making this slide,
all you gotta do is just add a little more
paint thinner to it.
There, see whole limbs are just,
just handing around out here.
There we are.
Go into a little bit of
white, brown, like a lighter color.
And we can highlight those a
little, just so they stand out.
Something like that.
There.
There, old tree's just
laying out there asleep.
Now then.
Let's go back and get our brush
that's got the dark color on it.
I want a little, I want a
little bush living right here,
so I'll put one in.
In your world, you put them
in anywhere you want 'em.
Put some dark in.
Go into a little bit of light,
I'm gonna use a little
into the Yellow Ochre side,
a little touch.
Nah, want more Yellow Ochre than that.
If you're not happy with it, change it.
Oh, that's better, now I'm happier.
There we go.
There we go, all kinds of little things.
Like that.
See, you can put these in
anywhere that you want 'em.
Just any old place.
Just to make it look
like theres a little bush
right here on the edge.
It goes right off the canvas.
Happy little bush.
Okay.
Back to our little liner brush.
Little light brown color on it.
And here and there and there,
we can put in a stick or a twig.
Whatever you think,
just a couple.
And, we had rocks on the other side,
let me go back to my Filbert
that had the rock color on it.
Any maybe over here, there's a rock or two
that lives on this side.
I know that side's better,
but all the rocks didn't move over there.
There's still a couple here.
Still a couple, where do they live?
Here's one right up against a tree.
Yeah, wherever you want 'em, you decide.
There.
Maybe right down here at
the base of that big tree,
lives a little stone.
You make the decision, but
he may live right there,
that's okay.
Shoot, I think we're about ready
for a signature on this one.
Take a little paint thinner, a
little bit of the Bright Red,
and we'll sign it.
I have people write and they say
"Do you have to sign with red?"
Absolutely not, you sign
with any color that you want.
I just sorta got in the
habit of signing with red,
and I always do it.
It's sorta became a trademark,
but you sign in any color that you want.
There we are.
I think we're gonna
call that one finished.
Hope you've enjoyed it.
I'd like to hear from you,
if you try this black
and white and grey gesso,
because it does fantastic things.
From all of us here, I'd like to wish you
happy painting, and God bless, my friend.
("Interlude" by Larry Owens)