- Well welcome back, glad
to see you again today.
I thought today we'd do
something a little different
and I've taken the liberty of going ahead
and covering the canvas
with a complete layer
of Sap Green.
And to that I'm gonna add
a little Prussian Blue
right on the bottom here.
And we just start at
the bottom and work up
so that it gets lighter
and lighter as we go up.
There we go.
I thought today we'd make
a happy little stream,
it's just sort of running
through the woods here.
There.
Okay, we just work this
blue back and forth
so it graduates in value as it goes up.
(gentle music)
Okay.
Now,
let's take, let's use this brush.
We'll take a little bit of Cadmium Yellow
and let's make a light source in here.
And we'll just do this by
making little X patterns.
There we go.
Just work it around and round and round
so it gets it darker and darker
as it goes out from the center.
Maybe a touch more.
Always starting in the light
area and working outward.
There we go.
Just back and forth, little Xs.
Okay.
Now we'll take the big brush,
and very gently we'll hypnotize this.
There.
Just let it blend outward.
So that we sort of have a light source,
that's all we're looking for here.
Now still using the big brush,
we'll go right back into the Sap Green.
And we'll do some basic tree shapes here.
We push the paint into the
canvas, just really push it.
There we go.
And you need an almighty
easel when you're doing this
because you're really, really pressing
the paint into the canvas.
(gentle music)
Okay.
Maybe we'll have another
big tree right in here.
Okay, there it is.
Isn't that fantastic, that
you can just push a tree
right out of your brush like that?
We'll have another tree here.
No use stopping,
we're having so much fun
here with these trees.
Okay.
And already we have a
basic shape to work with.
We really don't plan these paintings,
we let them happen,
we just sort of decide
where we want basic shapes
and work from there.
Okay, let's take the almighty knife,
a little Van Dyke Brown
and white mixed together.
And we'll put some trunks
on these almighty trees.
And all we're gonna do is touch
and sort of pull a little bit.
It'll get wider as you go down.
There we are.
(upbeat guitar music)
And maybe we'll have another trunk
hiding back in here somewhere.
Just make all kind of little
tree things happen here.
This is sort of different
than the paintings
we've done previously,
because this painting
has no Magic White on it.
All we do is start with the Sap Green,
completely cover the canvas,
work the Prussian blue
from the bottom upward
to make it darker in the foreground.
These are the kind of things
that we continually look for,
new ideas, new ways of using
this fantastic technique.
And these ideas we put out continually
to all the people that
enjoy this type of painting,
we have a little quarterly
newsletter that we use
to put these ideas out to people
so they are current in what's happening.
Okay, let's just have
another almighty trunk
right down through here.
Maybe we'll highlight
these just a little bit,
with a little plain white.
Just think where the light would strike
and run through here and have fun.
(jazzy guitar music)
There we go.
And over on this side now,
the light's gonna come from
the opposing direction,
the opposite direction.
Just a little here and there.
Okay.
Now we'll take a one inch brush
and a little bit of Magic White.
And we'll start with some yellow
and a touch of Phthalo Green.
Remember that a thin paint
will stick to a thick paint
so we thinned it just a little bit
with a little Magic White,
and then we just push out
all these thousands of little leaves.
There they come.
There they are.
Isn't that fantastic?
If you're painting along with us,
by now you should begin
to have little leaves
all over these trees, just
beautiful little leaves.
Leave a lot of the dark areas in here,
we don't want to kill all the dark areas.
We need the dark in
order to show the light.
There.
Okay, maybe we'll come right down here
and drop in another happy little bush.
There they come.
And over in here.
You want this to be the
brightest area in the painting,
back here where the light source is.
As we work forward, we're gonna get darker
and darker and darker.
Mmm-kay.
Maybe a little light coming
through right in here.
Now put your trunk in before
you put the leaves though,
so you have leaves in front of the trunk,
you don't want the trunk sitting
on the outside of the tree.
Okay.
There's a nice little bush, there he is.
And maybe over here, just
happy little thing growing.
Nature's so fantastic, enjoy it.
Let it, let it make you happy.
Okay, there's another one.
Now I'm gonna go into a little Sap Green,
begin using a little Sap
Green with this yellow
so it begins to get a little
darker as we work back here.
And we'll put some highlights
on this little tree.
(gentle guitar music)
There we go.
By now you should begin having the feeling
that you're walking through the deep woods
of all the beautiful
tree shapes are there,
the little squirrels
are hiding in the trees,
the bunny rabbits are behind.
There we go.
Once again, don't kill all this dark area,
you need it to produce
distance in the painting.
Okay.
That should give us enough
to get started with.
Now we'll take the almighty fan brush
and we'll take a little
bit of Magic White,
and a little bit of Firm White.
And we'll make a, let's
have a little waterfall
that's happening back here,
and maybe a bubbling little stream
is just working its way through.
So often we avoid running water,
running water is a lot
of fun, so here we go.
Pull it over, and let it drop,
if you're making a little waterfall.
Then we take the fan brush and push,
makes the little foamy things happen.
Then we begin building our running water,
and we're pushing the fan
brush so that it bends upward
and the foam's on the top
instead of on the bottom.
There we are.
Let all these little things just happen.
Mmm, there we go.
Maybe under the water here,
there's a little stones,
causing the water to
sort of just bubble over.
You might not see this
stone, but it's under there.
As it comes towards you, let it get wider,
bigger, stronger.
More of these little things,
little actions that are happening here.
(gentle guitar music)
All kinds of little churning motions.
And avoid having your waterfall here
and stream coming straight
through your painting,
let it sort of wander around.
All these little water actions.
And they all hide here in your fan brush,
all you have to do is
sort of push them out.
Okay, good.
Alrighty, maybe
maybe back here in the distance there's,
we have a little stone back here.
We just use some Van Dyke brown
and we'll build us a little stone.
And maybe there's a
little stone out here too.
This is your world, so you
put stones wherever you want.
This painting comes right of your heart,
so just let it sort of flow.
Let it happen.
Maybe we'll take a little
bit of brown and white and
the least little touch of blue.
Just to make sort of a grey color here.
And we can highlight these
little stones, just like that.
Maybe there's a little ridge
coming down through here.
Little sunlight playing across the stones.
A little dark edge underneath here,
so that it has some distance
between the water and the stone.
And we take the little fan brush,
and splash some water up
on the stones there, there.
There we go.
Okay, maybe we'll let this
just drift right on down through here.
Maybe right along here, there's another
happy little waterfall
that's happening right here.
So you take your fan
brush, and go straight,
and let it just fall over.
Just like so.
Isn't that something?
You can make a waterfall that quick.
Just a small one, you don't want
to have a violent waterfall here,
just a little bitty waterfall.
And then we push to make
our little foamy areas
where the waterfall's gonna hit and crash.
There we go.
Okay, now let's take the big brush again
and use some Sap Green and Prussian Blue.
It's getting darker as it comes down.
And we'll throw in some more
happy little bushes back here.
You need the dark in
order to show the light.
(gentle guitar music)
Okay, maybe over here
there's a nice bush too.
Let some of these bushes
protrude out over the water.
Okay.
Now we can take a little
more of the highlight color,
some Cad Yellow with a little bit
of Phthalo and Sap Green mixed together.
I'm gonna start back
here and push this rock
back into the painting.
We just put a little bush in front of it.
There we go.
And maybe right here there's
some nice little things
that just sort of hang over the water.
Okay, let's do this nice one right here.
There we go, there we go.
You can do it, you can do it.
Just push that waterfall
right back into the painting.
Okay, let's
let's take a little more brown here
and just put a little stone,
a little gravel out here
for all these nice bushes
and stuff to sit on.
There we go.
Little highlight on the stones.
(gentle guitar music)
And a few little grassy things that grow
right on down the bank here.
Maybe we'll even get daring
and put a little stone
out here in the water.
There.
Just lay it in with Van Dyke Brown,
then we highlight it with
sort of the grey color.
There, just let this bright play
just run across this little stone.
Okay.
Little more of the Magic
White, a little Firm White.
Now we're gonna start playing
the water around this stone.
Maybe it just comes around like so,
sort of falls over,
splashes a little here,
around the side, down.
All kinds of little
actions happening in this.
Okay, a little bit of water
splashing up against the rocks here.
Okay, now we're getting a
nice little stream here.
You can see how it's
beginning to pick up the blue
that's underneath here,
and make this water darker
as it comes closer to you.
There we go.
Okay, let's go back to
good old big brush here.
Little more blue and Sap Green.
And we'll project some bushes
right up through here now.
Need a lot of paint in the
brush, more green than blue.
And we just let these run
right on down like so.
(jazzy guitar music)
And we can highlight these with
a little yellow, Sap Green.
We're getting much darker in color now.
There.
Just sort of vary your color tones
back and forth a little so they stand out.
Leave the dark areas, that's
the only thing you have
to separate all these beautiful bushes.
Mm, there's a nice one.
Okay.
Add a little bush right in here.
Looks like some of the beautiful streams
that we have in Alaska.
Walk through the woods, and
you listen to, and you look at.
And they make you happy.
They have a beautiful sound to them.
You can almost hear the
bubbling and carrying on
as it travels down the creek bed here.
Just with the Van Dyke Brown
here, we're just adding
a few little sticks here and there,
you always have in the woods.
Okay.
Now we can take a clean knife
and just scrape through the dark areas
and let the canvas show through to give
the indication of all kind
of little sticks and twigs
that are going through here.
There they are.
Just using the point of the knife here.
And these little sticks create
tremendous distance in the painting.
So many of the fast painting techniques
that I have seen around the country
as I teach this almighty method,
are very flat, have very
little depth to them.
Okay, maybe now, we might
as well have some fun here.
Let's take some Van Dyke Brown,
and let's put an almighty dead
tree right up through here.
You always have dead trees in the woods
when you're walking around.
There.
Be brave, go right across
the waterfall here.
And we'll just lay this in with a knife.
We're using very thick paint here.
Right across the top.
And we'll just give him a little friend
right beside him here.
This whole tree's just
about, just about had it.
He's gonna sort of fall over in the stream
and be washed away here pretty soon.
But until them, he's still
part of the beauty that's
ever-evident in nature.
We'll just make him a little taller,
that way he'll make a bigger
splash when he hits the water.
Okay.
Now I'm gonna use the liner brush
with a little bit of thin oil on it,
a little yellow and a little
Permanent Red mixed together,
we'll brighten this one up a little touch.
And I'm gonna just go
down the side of it here,
just highlighting a little.
We need something bright here,
so I'm gonna just use this tree.
There.
And let this sort of streak
so it looks like bark.
Okay, we'll wash him off.
And we'll use some more of the thin oil
and a little Van Dyke Brown,
and we'll put a few old branches
that are hanging on this tree.
Okay, and with the thin oil,
it makes the paint thinner.
So once again, you're working
with thin and thick paints,
the thin paint will stick
to the thicker paint.
And I recommend you use an oil,
if you use paint thinner
it has a tendency to bleed
if you're not very careful.
And the oil makes it much slicker.
There we go.
Mm, there we are.
Just a few old limbs here and there,
let's get a little more oil here.
And when you're working
this paint in the oil,
turn your brush, that
brings it to a nice point.
And you can make all these
delicate little limbs and stuff.
So put some over here on this one.
At home you have unlimited time,
here we're limited by our time factor,
but you can put tremendous
detail in these paintings.
So we're just trying to
give you an idea here,
we're just trying to give
you a guide to follow,
to teach you how to use
this fantastic technique.
And at home, let your
imagination be your guide,
let your heart take you
wherever you want to be.
(gentle guitar music)
There, look at all those little limbs.
And just in a matter of minutes.
Okay, maybe we'll have one
come in right through here.
There we go.
Just let them flow off your brush.
And this tree tends to push
everything back in the painting,
give it more distance.
And maybe there's just an
old hanging sort of here and
there.
There we go.
Okay, we'll take a little touch
more of the highlight color,
that's yellow with a
touch of Permanent Red.
And a little oil in it.
And we'll just highlight some
of these major limbs here.
Just let the brush flow
right down the limb.
If you have a problem,
maybe your hand's not
steady enough to do this,
use your palette or something
to sort of balance your hand.
I was very fortunate, I was
blessed with a very steady hand.
And
it comes in very handy when you're doing
these little delicate things.
(gentle music)
Okay, your little highlights over here.
There we go.
Just sort of work all this together.
Little bit right up here.
Okay, we'll clean out the brush here.
And let's see.
What do we need here?
I'm gonna pull this
down just a little bit,
to make it look a little, there we go.
A little more of a cliff right here.
Stone, very dark.
Maybe right over here we'll build
a nice little stone right here too.
We have one in the water,
maybe we need one over here.
This is straight Van Dyke Brown again.
And we'll take a little touch
of the blue and the brown and white.
Okay.
Just lay this on very gently,
just let the paint break.
It's a very, very gentle touch.
Super gentle touch.
You almost let the knife touch.
Now we'll take a little
more of the Magic White,
a little green and yellow
and mix it together,
we'll make some little bushes here
to come up and protrude over the stone.
You need a thin paint to go over the top
of this very thick paint
that you've put on.
So there we go.
And we put some little grassy
areas around the trees' foots.
Okay.
Alrighty.
(gentle guitar music)
And we wanna splash that
back up on the stone here.
Like so.
Okay.
Good, I think we just about
have our little stream finished today.
And if you're painting along
with us, you should have
just about completed this painting.
I might put a few little
touches here and there.
As I say, at home you have time to put in
tremendous detail, you
can work and carry on
and build all kind of happy
little things in here.
Here, we're limited by
the amount of time we have
so we're just trying to show
you the basic technique,
the basic idea.
Need a little highlight
on this little dead one
that's laying right out through here.
Okay.
Just a little sticks here and there.
Little brighter color so they show up.
There's one right in front of the stone.
Okay, I think we'll just
take a little thin oil,
Permanent Red here, and
we'll sign this painting.
Little more oil.
(upbeat guitar music)
And I hope you've enjoyed this.
This is sort of a new idea.
As I say, we've used no
Magic White on this canvas,
just pure Sap Green.
This will work in a multitude of colors,
you can paint the canvas with blue,
with combinations of
colors, and make some of
the most fantastic little
paintings you've ever seen.
One of the prettiest
ones is to paint it with
Van Dyke Brown, and make
beautiful autumn scenes out of it.
And the brown is picked up by the yellows
and oranges and reds and
just, it just stands out.
Fantastic painting.
Okay.
We'll just sign this one.
There we go.
(upbeat guitar music)
Yeah.
And we'll call that painting finished.
Once again, I hope you've
painted along with us,
and you've enjoyed this picture.
It is a lot of fun.
And we hope to see you again next time,
and we'll do another
happy little painting.
Until then, from all of
us here, happy painting.
(upbeat guitar music)