- Hello again. Glad to see you.
Thought today we'd one of
these almighty black canvases.
It's time we got into doing
something on a black canvas.
I'd like to show you how
you can do a beautiful,
beautiful landscape
on a black canvas.
I've already went ahead,
because we are short of time on this show,
I've already went ahead and
covered the whole canvas
with Alizarin crimson.
Now I'm gonna take a little Van Dyke brown
and work into the edges,
just around the edges,
so it's, we already have it
covered with Alizarin crimson,
and now we're putting
a little brown on it.
The whole canvas was covered with crimson.
There we go.
Just around the corners.
Thought today we'd do a
beautiful little sunset.
And maybe we'll have a little sunset
like the sun's going down
behind the hill back there.
And we just have a
beautiful glow in the sky,
and then we'll go from there.
Now I'm gonna take and
pull this back and forth
to a get a nice even
distribution of paint,
working it up and down, back and forth.
There we go.
All right.
Mm 'kay, now we'll start
with a one-inch brush,
we'll use a little bit of cad yellow.
Figure out where the
sun is, just went down,
and we're gonna start like right here.
And begin working this paint around.
You start in the center and work
around and around and around,
and already it's picking
up the Alizarin crimson
and it's turning into
a beautiful little yellow-ish
orange-ish glow here.
There we go.
And we'll start right
here, let it work outward.
You want it to get darker and
darker and darker and darker
as it goes out toward the edges.
So we always start with a
color in here and work outward.
There we go.
Okay.
A little bit of color here, work it out,
and I'm doing this in
little-bitty X patterns.
Back and forth, back
and forth, there we go.
Mm 'kay.
Now let's take the big brush,
and gently gently hypnotize this.
We're still making the little X's.
There.
Just work that in.
And then just enough to
take out the brushstrokes.
Okay.
(water sloshing)
(paintbrush rattling)
Okay, let's take a little bit
of Alizarin, a little brown,
put it together here on the
brush, mix on the brush.
And maybe back here in the distance
we'll have a little foothill back here.
Just let this brush bounce along and play.
There we go.
Don't let the size of
this big brush scare you.
It does fantastic things.
Okay.
Now, maybe we'll have some highlights.
Take the little yellow and green and,
little touch of red here,
and we just push some little
highlights coming down here.
We'll make these little foothills
way back in the distance.
Okay.
Let's put some back over here.
There we go.
Then we'll take a clean brush,
and just gently lift up,
very very lightly,
just enough to give it an upward swirl.
There.
Very light, barely barely
touching the canvas.
You let two or three
hairs just about touch.
Just enough to move
the paint a little bit.
Okay.
Now we'll take a little yellow
and a little permanent
red mixed together here,
and we'll start putting
in some reflections.
Maybe we'll have a little,
have a little lake right
back here, a little pond.
Just lay a little color on.
And pull this down.
There we go.
Then just enough to give
a little watery effect.
Just
ripple it a little.
We don't want to destroy.
(water sloshing)
Mm 'kay.
(brush rattling)
Clean the old brushes here,
and we'll move right along.
Okay now I'm gonna go back
into this brown and Alizarin.
Once again we're mixing it on the brush.
A lot of paint on the brush.
Maybe we'll put a little
tree standing back here.
We'll make this one with the fan brush.
There we go.
And trees get lonely too,
so we'll give him a friend.
There.
And maybe there's a
little one right there.
Got two big ones, so,
invariably sooner or later
there's gonna be a little one.
There he is.
Let's fill him in, make
him just a touch darker.
Maybe we'll put a third one right there.
Work that in a little bit,
create a shadow behind the tree.
Okay.
(water sloshing)
Now, we'll just, with a knife here
we'll just make a little waterline
running back through here.
These black canvases, we
cover with a black acrylic.
A flat black acrylic paint,
and allow it to dry before we start.
And the Alizarin crimson that we use here,
is a transparent color, so
the black shows through.
It looks black, but when
you apply color to it,
man it really comes alive.
Okay, let's start with some
almighty trees and stuff.
We'll use the big brush today.
And let's have a big old tree right here.
I know this may be quite
difficult for you to see
but we are putting the general
shape of the tree right here.
These black canvases make
some of the prettiest pictures
that you could imagine.
And if you're interested
in selling paintings
and making a happy buck
to put in your pocket,
these are the ones that really sell.
Let's have another tree right over here.
Let these limbs just fly out, firemen.
Maybe a big tree up here.
And as you can see, we're
really hitting this canvas,
we're really pushing the paint into it.
You need an almighty easel.
Little Tiny Tim easels will let you down.
This easel is made out of
a platform step-ladder.
And they work very very well.
They're very strong, very simple to build.
Okay.
We've got that filled in.
Let's put some tree trunks here and there.
Okay.
And we'll put some dark
paint right along here.
There we go.
Just, in your mind,
wherever you visualize there
might be a little trunk,
just drop one in.
Now mix just a little brown and white,
so we can put a little
touch of highlight on this
and make it stand out a little,
like a light's playing
through here and touching it.
There.
And we'll put a trunk right
over in this one, too.
Little dabble.
Okay.
Now, if the sun's here, light's
coming from this direction,
this would be highlighted
on the other side.
Now probably in reality,
if the sky was this dark,
you would have nothing but silhouettes.
But that would be a boring picture.
This is a lot more fun.
Okay, you take a little
bit of magic white,
little yellow,
maybe a touch of Phthalo green.
And we can put some nice little leaves
on all these little bushes.
Look how that color stands out
against this black background.
It just jumps out at you.
Okay, now, let's,
let's put some on this little bush.
And there's some little
things growing down in here.
Use your imagination, let it go.
Let it go.
Remember, this is your world.
In your world you can create
anything that you desire.
Okay, let's do this old big tree here.
What's so very nice about
these black canvases,
if there's a light
shining directly on them
they look totally different
than if they're without a light.
So in essence it's almost like
having two paintings in one.
Especially if you hang these,
after they're finished,
over a light, so at night
if you turn the light on
it shines up on this,
it's remarkable what happens.
There we go.
All the little bushy areas.
Maybe some little touches out here.
Okay.
Now let's take some more Van Dyke brown
and let's put an almighty tree right here.
We'll just let him bend and play and
work right on up to here.
And, there we go.
There.
Have another little limb
coming down through here.
And maybe there's some little things
happening up here in the leaves.
And we'll have a little
light playing across here.
Just pull that knife sort of, swirled,
so it gives the appearance
of it being round.
There we go.
Now we're ready to put some highlights
on these little leaves out here.
Okay.
And just let the light
play through this tree.
Leaving a lot of dark areas.
We need these dark areas to
make the tree look round.
Don't kill 'em all.
Such a, such a temptation,
to do a little bit more.
I used to work with one art teacher,
that, he had a set of handcuffs
that hung in the studio,
and he'd walk by and he'd bump you
and he'd point at those handcuffs.
And that was his way of saying,
"You're beginning to fiddle it to death."
We don't have any handcuffs here today,
but stand back and look
every once in a while.
Don't overwork your picture,
you'll fiddle it to death.
Okay.
This looks like a
super place, maybe, to have a little path
that runs up through there.
So now take a little Prussian
blue and Van Dyke brown
and just very easy here,
we'll just make a little path
that runs right through this.
Got to have a way to get around the lake
to catch that big trout
that lives out there.
Know he's there.
Okay.
Then we'll put just a little
bit of highlight on there.
Just let that run down
through there and break.
You want that paint to break.
So it leaves some of those
beautiful dark areas in there.
There we go.
Now.
Little bit more magic white here.
Just want to thin that paint
so it'll stick on top
of all the other paint.
Now we can start in here.
We'll start putting some
nice little bushes that
are hanging over the path.
So the path just disappears
back here behind the big tree.
Okay.
And these bushes
protruding up over the top,
push it down into the picture.
You need 'em.
They pay you great dividends.
And we'll put some on this side
of the road over there.
Mm 'kay.
Let's make another big tree.
Maybe right up through here.
We'll just have a big ol' tree.
There he goes. Van Dyke brown.
Van Dyke brown's a very nice color,
it's almost like a
chocolate brown, very warm.
There.
Okay, now a little limb right there.
Now one thing I'd like
to mention while we're
putting the highlights on here,
if you have questions or comments or
anything you'd lie to know
about what we're doing here,
please feel free to drop us a line,
care WMVT, and we'll give you the address
at the end of the show.
And do use it, so you know,
we're here to help you,
if you have problems or
if you have questions,
anything concerning
this method of painting,
we'll be glad to work with
you and try to help you.
Okay.
We'll put some highlights
up here on this one.
Little bit more of the
magic, thin it down.
Just a touch.
Okay.
Thousands and thousands and
thousands of little leaves.
Okay, now, let's go down here,
put some little things around the tree.
And maybe you can, right here, say,
let's put a little stone.
Maybe a little stone just
lays right along here.
Of course he's a happy little stone.
We don't have any other kind.
And we'll make up a
little highlight color.
Just lay right over there.
Like so.
Okay,
now let's put some, mm, nice one there.
Nice one there.
Okay, let's have some little
bushes right along in here.
Now when you're doing this,
load this brush by pulling
it in one direction
so that it looks like
an old shoe on the end,
sort of hangs over.
You put that round part to the top,
and tilt the brush sort of downward
and just push,
just enough to bend the
bristles a little bit.
Don't fight it, let the brush do the work.
You have the fun, let the brush work.
Maybe we'll put a nice
little sparkler right there.
Just sort of to break that up a little it.
Okay.
Now let's lay in a few
stems here and there.
And all we're doing here
is literally just cutting
right through the paint,
using the point of the knife.
We literally just cut the paint.
There we go.
This is one of the paintings
that we do in class quite frequently.
It's a very effective painting,
it teaches you how to use black canvases.
It's a lot of fun.
And it's extremely, extremely effective.
We'll have a few little
sticks coming over like so.
There we go.
And once again, these little
twigs and these little sticks
show different planes in the picture.
It produces the illusion of distance.
Use 'em to your advantage.
'Cause the woods are always full of them.
Let's see, maybe back here we could just
put a little indication
of a trunk here and there,
some little sticks.
There we go.
Okay.
All righty, I think this
one's just about ready.
Then we can sign it.
So I'll use a very thin oil here.
And we'll just take
and use the liner brush,
and you mix this paint
until it's like water.
And if you mix it very very thin,
curl that brush as you pull it out,
twist it, so it brings it to a point.
It's just like you were writing.
You don't have to wait
until the painting is dry.
Okay.
There.
(water sloshing)
This same technique is also very good
if you want to put some nice
little sticks and limbs in
that you wanted to draw in,
use the oil to get the paint thin.
And then maybe we could
come right across and,
'cause a thin paint will
stick to a thick paint.
There.
Just let these little things
happen here and there.
Okay.
One of the things that we're trying to do
as we travel around and
teach this almighty method,
is we're trying to gather
up an army of teachers.
And soon we'll have teachers that
travel this entire beautiful country,
teaching this fantastic
method of painting.
If you would like to
have some information,
drop us a line.
Once again,
we'll show you the address
at the end of the show.
And soon we'll have
information on teachers
that are all the way across this country.
Teachers that we can guarantee
that can teach this fantastic method.
Okay.
I think now, we'll just
put a couple little things
here and there.
Put another little stick or two.
I hope you've painted along with us
and you've enjoyed this
half as much as we have.
We really enjoy doing
these black canvases,
they are extremely, extremely effective,
and you'll find
that they bring a nice
warm glow to your heart.
These can be done in
a multitude of colors.
You can cover 'em with any
color that's transparent.
We can use the Prussian blue, sap green,
any of these colors, or
combinations of colors.
Later on in this series
we'll do a winter
picture on a black canvas
and I'll show you how you
can put the moon in the sky
and let the light play across the snow
when you have the almighty
mountains and stuff.
And I'll think you'll find
these black canvases
can do fantastic things.
We also wanna do some
pictures in the series
where we paint the canvas with one color.
Instead of putting the
magic white on the canvas,
we'll paint it, for
example, the sap green.
And we'll paint beautiful pictures
by doing that.
There's a multitude of things
that can be done with this.
Use it, experiment with it, go with it.
Just let your heart be your guide.
Let your imagination take you
anywhere that you want to go.
Let it go.
Okay.
All righty, I think we're gonna
call that picture finished.
And, once again,
we want to thank you very
much for watching us.
And from all of us here
at WMVT, happy painting.
Thank you very much.
(guitar music)