- Hello, welcome back.
I thought today, we'd
do an almighty picture
that had some huge mountains in it
and maybe today, we'll
also work a little bit on
putting some clouds floating
in front of the mountains.
This is always something
that's very difficult to do,
so I'll try to show ya how to do that
and I hope you have a canvas
set up on your almighty easel
and cool drink in hand and let's go here.
I'm gonna start with a little
bit of alizarin crimson
and a touch of prussian blue
and maybe we'll just make
a sky that's sort of a
lavender type and sorta taste it, test it.
There we go.
I already have magic white on the canvas.
So, we're just literally mixing paint
right here on the canvas.
(calm jazzy music)
And we'll just bring this
down to about like so.
There we go.
Now, go into just a little prussian blue
and we'll lay this right
in like so, there we go.
Okay.
And while we have the
old brush dirty here,
I'll take a little phthalo
green in prussian blue
and we'll lay in some water here.
And already, we have a masterpiece for
a museum of modern art somewhere.
Okay, now we'll clean the old brush.
Be sure it's good and dry.
Then, this is just a clean, dry brush
and we're just gonna bring
these two colors together here.
Okay.
Just do you have a nice blending.
You don't wanna be able
to tell where one stops
and the other one starts.
And we'll hypnotize it
and sort of blend it out.
Okay, now let's take the fan brush,
a little bit of titanium white
mixed with a touch of permanent red
just to give it a little pinkish hue.
We don't wanna set these clouds on fire.
All we wanna do is give
it just a little hue here,
just a little pinkish hue
and we'll push us in some
nice little clouds here.
We're pushing very hard
just to push the value
right into the canvas.
And maybe we'll put little
cloud floating around
right here.
Okay.
We'll take and gently, gently, gently
blend that together.
Very light, delicate touch.
Don't overwork these clouds.
They're very, very easy to overwork 'em.
Then we'll hypnotize 'em.
Okay, let's build us an almighty mountain.
We'll take a little bit of blue
and some brown, touch of alizarin.
And a little bit of white.
There we go.
And mix your color marbley.
Don't mix it dead.
Let's start way up here.
Put us an almighty mountain.
Maybe there's a nice
little peak over here.
Let this drop down.
We're really pushing this
paint into the canvas.
Maybe we'll have another
little peak over in here.
And we'll take off all the excess paint.
Then we'll take the big
brush and pull it down
just to make sure we've
got all the paint off of it
that can come off.
All we wanna leave is
the value in the canvas,
the color.
Now, we'll start with a
little bit of titanium white
and I'm gonna mix a little
bit of brown and blue with it
just to gray it down.
Just a little bit.
We can start putting
some highlights on this
almighty mountain.
Maybe we'll have a little peak rolling
right down through there.
Maybe a little light's
hitting right up here.
And for shadow color,
we'll take a little bit of
blue and brown and white
mixed with a little darker value.
And we'll just lay us some
shadows right in here.
And each little highlight
needs it's own private shadow.
Maybe we'll add another little peak here.
This is your mountain, so you can add
what you want to on it.
Now let's diffuse the bottom of it
and here, we're just gently tapping.
Don't wanna destroy, just diffuse.
And then we'll pull just to take out
the little tap marks.
Now, we'll lay some clouds
on top of the mountain.
And I've added a little bit of magic white
with my paint just to make
it a little bit thinner.
You remember our golden rule here.
Thin paint'll stick to a thick paint.
So, maybe we'll have a little cloud here
that just floats right
across the mountain.
Okay.
Maybe right up here, there's one too.
Seems like I remember one up here.
Now, very carefully, we'll blend this in.
Super light touch here.
Okay, let's take
and let's work on this peak now.
Let's let him travel down and
just come right down
in the foreground here.
Give him a few little shadows
so he stands out as an individual.
And maybe a few little shadows in here.
Okay and once again, we'll diffuse this
just to lay some mist in here.
And then, maybe another
little layer of clouds
and we'll add a little more magic white
to keep the paint thin.
And maybe this one just drops
right out of the sky here.
And plays around the bottom.
There we go.
Just nice, soft little clouds.
Okay, this is a very, very delicate touch.
There.
And maybe we'll just take and
maybe there's another
little stone right in here.
Travels around.
Just to show ya how to continually
bring things forward here
and we need this to be a little darker
than the background back here.
And we'll lay some
highlights right on here.
Let that paint break.
Let it break so you have all
these little holes in it.
Let some of the dark show through.
There we go.
And maybe just a few little clouds,
little misty areas
floating around in here.
This creates a tremendous
illusion of distance,
makes things far, far away.
Now, we'll just hypnotize
this a little touch.
And it's vitally important,
when you're doing this at home,
that you use a paint
that's very, very firm.
Otherwise, you have nothing that's thinner
to go over the top of it, so be sure
to use a very firm paint.
Okay, let's mix us up a little color.
We'll add a little
sap green, little more blue in here.
Maybe just a touch more alizarin.
There we go, nice color.
And don't mix it dead,
remember not to mix it dead.
And we'll take this old big brush
and let's put us some little
foothills right in here.
Don't let the size of this
big brush scare you away.
Use it, it does fantastic things.
Now I'm gonna give it
just a little upward sweep
to make it look like little trees
way, way back in the distance.
There we go.
Then we'll tap a little bit here
just to lay some mist in between these.
We'll have two of 'em, I think.
Now we'll add a little more of the brown
and a little more of the blue just to
darken it up a little bit here.
All the same colors.
Blue, brown, a little alizarin, sap,
just to make it a little bit darker
so it'll look like it's in front.
There we go.
We'll lay another little ridge of
foothills right down through there.
We'll give those a little upward swirl.
Just barely, barely
touching the canvas here.
Okay.
Now we can start coming forward.
And we'll take a little bit of sap green
mixed with a little bit of alizarin
and then I'll mix that into some yellow.
Makes sort of a dirty green color
and we'll start putting some little trees
that are way back here.
Load a lot of paint in your brush
and just push upward.
There, all these little things happening
way back in the distance.
And maybe just a little
touch of yellow right here.
Just let this blend right
with the color that you had.
Let it go.
Now I'm gonna take and
pull just the edges down.
Don't overwork this
because you're working with
yellow into the blue water and it'll just
turn it bright green on ya.
Just pull it down,
hypnotize it a little bit,
and leave it alone.
Now we can put a few little
sticks here and there.
Just cutting through the
paint is all we're doing.
Make it look like little trunks
way back in the distance.
We'll take just a little
touch of phthalo green
mixed with a cad yellow
and a little bit of permanent red.
And we'll put some
highlights on these trees.
Just where the sun's running through there
and sparkling on top of 'em.
There we go.
Now, some straight vandyke brown
and we just lay us a
little, little bit of dirt
and gravel and stuff in here.
This isn't straight magic
white and we're just gonna
lay it right underneath here
just to give us a little water line.
And when you're doing this at home,
you'll have a lot more
time than we do here.
You can take your time
and put in all the little
fantastic details that
you want to back here.
Okay.
Let's begin moving this
in a little bit closer.
Using the same colors.
We'll just start coming forward.
Maybe we need a nice tall
little tree right here.
Let's put us a little bush over here also.
Can't leave this side out.
There we go.
Just lay that in.
Ya know, we'd love to hear from ya
and love to hear how
you're doing with all this
and if it's helping you.
We'd like to know what you
wanna see on these shows.
If you wanna see different things painted,
different techniques.
We'd also maybe like to, in the future,
bring some of the better instructors
that we have met across the United States
and maybe we'll have them demonstrate some
unbelievable techniques that can be done.
But we need to know what
you want, so let us know.
Now, let's take a little bit of the brown
and we'll just lay some
little trunks here and there.
Maybe we'll give this
little bush one here.
And we'll put some highlights on that.
Still fascinates me how this works
and how beautifully it works.
Okay, let's see, maybe we need a little,
there, that's it.
And down in here, we
need some little bushes
that are hiding underneath
this bigger one.
And we'll put some little
reflections in the water.
There we go.
Little red fireball there.
Okay.
Little touch more of the magic white
just to thin it down a touch.
Let's go over here
and we'll put some nice little
highlights on this tree.
There we go.
Leave a lot of these dark areas in here.
They create the shadows that
you need so desperately.
And we'll put a little color right here
for reflections.
Then we can lay a little
color right on top
to give us nice, beautiful reflections.
Right there.
Okay.
Now, let's take a little
more of the straight brown
and a little bit right along here
and we'll just draw in
some little bit of shore,
little bank here.
Lay a little highlight on top of that.
Touch here.
Okay, let's see what we got going here.
Looks like we have a
lot of space up in here
that we really need to do something with.
So, let's do this.
This is alizarin, crimson,
little bit of sap green.
Now we've gotta do something up here
'cause we've thrown
all this color in here.
There we go.
Maybe we'll put a little
bit right out here too.
Looks so good, we might as well not stop.
We'll take a little bit of vandyke brown
and let's do us an almighty tree coming
right up through here.
There he is.
And you're just sort of
pulling this sideways
to lay the paint right on the canvas,
let it pull off the knife.
And maybe we can give him
some little arms out here.
There we go.
And there's another one.
And maybe this is a
separate little entity,
little tree by itself growing down here.
Just a little sprout off the big one.
Now we can put some
highlights on these leaves.
And just let it touch.
Bend the bristles just
the least little bit.
There we go.
Few over here.
Isn't that fantastic that you can create
an almighty tree that fast?
We'll put a little highlight
here in this one too.
Don't want him to feel left out.
Let's put a little something over here
to give this a feel of bark.
Just here and there.
There we go.
Let's see.
Maybe over here.
Let's be brave.
Let's put an old, dead
tree right up through here.
And this old tree is tired.
He's just about to fall down.
Not too much left for him.
We'll give him a little tired arm.
There we go.
And here and there.
Just let these happen.
Good.
Maybe another little stick right there.
Alrighty.
Now, maybe we'll do
something a little touch
different here.
I'm gonna take a little
bit of the permanent red
and sorta highlight this old tree,
just run it down through there.
There we go.
And if we wanted to make
a few more little branches
on this tree, we can take
a little bit of the thin oil
and thin this down and we can lay
just a few more little
branches here and there.
Just a few that's hangin' on.
Most of 'em have already fallen off.
Okay, now we'll put something here
to cover up his foot, so it pushes him
back down in there.
Let's do the same thing over here.
Need to push him back into the picture.
And maybe we can take a little more of the
sap green and alizarin combination
and let's do this.
Maybe we'll just project this right on out
toward us here.
Give him some highlights.
Okay, there we go.
By now, if you're
painting at home with us,
you should begin having
a picture that's getting
close to being completed.
Should have listed your
spirits up very high
and ready to go to another one.
We just put a little
magic white under here
to give us a little water line
like so.
And let's put a few little
sticks here and there.
Okay, there.
Now, this is a most interesting picture
because of the mountains
and once again, the biggest thing
we'd like for you to learn from this one
is the laying of clouds
in front of mountains
and how to make these mountains be pushed
far, far away.
Okay, these little sticks
show all different planes.
They create the illusion of distance.
Okay, I think this one's just about ready
for a signature.
So, we'll take a little of the thin oil,
mix it up real good, make
it almost like water here.
And we'll just lay a little
signature right there.
And I'm very fortunate 'cause
I have a short name so,
only takes me a second to do so.
And I think we'll call that one finished.
If we mess with it any
more, we're gonna start
fiddling it to death.
Do your picture, get
your dream out on canvas
and leave it alone.
Don't fiddle with it all day.
In the time you spend fiddling,
you could do another picture.
So, thank you very, very
much for watching us.
We hope to see you again and until then,
happy painting.
(calm piano)