- Hello, glad to see you again.
Today I thought we'd do
an almighty winter picture
and I want to put a great
of emphasis on the sky
and how we make big bellowy,
fluffy clouds that just
roll and lay up in the sky here.
So I've covered the
canvas with magic white
and I'm gonna start with
sort of a grey color here
made by mixing a little Prussian blue,
a little brown and a little white
and we're just gonna
start gently working this
and let it go.
There we go, we just sort of
work it around and around here.
This is a winter sky.
Bad weather's coming in.
Okay, here we go.
Now we just sorta bring all this together.
But we want this swirling
turning action here.
And then very lightly back in here.
Okay.
Now we'll take our fan brush
with a little bit of white
and we'll put just a touch of
permanent red with it here.
Okay, a little bit of magic white.
Now we're gonna start
way back in the back,
the cloud farthest away first.
And we'll start working this.
There we go.
(light piano music)
And you keep this brush
moving all the time.
Just let it dance and play
and have fun up through there.
Very gently we'll blend that.
Okay, now we're ready to start working it.
Always doing the thing,
it's farthest away first
and working forward.
There.
Then we'll hypnotize a
little bit, very gently,
we don't want to destroy
what we've worked so hard
to put in here, we just
wanna blend it together.
There.
Today I'm using two fan brushes,
one so I can work with the darks
and the other one with the lights.
We'll throw some ol' grey clouds in here
that are sneaking around
and having fun too.
There he comes.
And maybe there's an old
grey one just sorta laying
out here like this.
And we'll work this one
just a little touch.
And we'll go back into another
little white cloud here.
And by the time I've got down
this low I'm getting away
from the pink that I had, I
just want the pink in the top
to give indication that
sunlight's playing through there.
Then all these beautiful
clouds just happen
right up here in the sky.
Clouds used to be something
that drove me crazy
when I was a traditional painter.
You'd work for days and days
to make big, fluffy clouds.
And here you just sorta let it
happen, don't worry about it.
Don't try to plan 'em.
Ah, there's another nice one.
'Cause clouds are free.
They have no boundaries.
They come and go as they please.
Okay, let's see.
Really pushing that paint into the canvas,
you wanna grind the value
right into the materials.
While we're talking about canvas,
one of the things to look for
when you're buying a canvas
to paint this technique
is look for a canvas
that's acrylic primed.
That'll hold the magic
white on there longer.
Keep it wet longer.
And we depend on this being
wet throughout the painting.
Okay, maybe there's another
little fluffy right in here.
Just wherever.
Just let it happen, don't worry about it.
There we go.
And here we're just putting
some brush strokes in.
Indicate light coming through there.
Okay, maybe laying up here in the clouds
we have some little mountains
that are just laying in here.
Okay, we want these to
blend right into nothing.
We're gonna lay these right in the clouds.
Okay, we'll have a little light
playing down through here.
Just bouncing around, having fun.
There.
Right up to this peak.
Want these to be far, far away
just about disappearing
right into the sky.
Then we're gonna diffuse them
by just tap, tap, tapping right along,
always following the angles here.
Just tapping.
And then we'll gently hypnotize them
so they just disappear right
on back into the picture.
Okay.
Now we can just lay clouds all around 'em.
Just set 'em down in there.
We'll work those a little bit.
Maybe a little touch of grey in here.
Okay.
Now when you're at home doing
this and have unlimited time,
you can put a great deal
more detail in here.
This is just to give you
an idea of how it's done.
Okay.
Let's have an almighty mountain.
Let's come all the way
down, what the heck.
He just comes right up through here.
Very little paint.
We're really pushing this
paint into the canvas.
Okay, then we'll take, pull that down.
Just makes the next layer
of paint stick better.
I'm gonna add just a little
touch of Prussian blue here.
Just so we have some
shadows under the snow.
Okay.
Now we can put some almighty snow
coming all the way down
through this mountain here.
And we're just gonna let it run and play.
Just let it go.
There.
See how easy that is?
Just let it flow in there.
And we'll run some right
along this mountain peak.
And maybe here since our
light's coming from here,
this one's gonna be highlighted
from the other side.
We'll create a little valley
maybe right down through there.
We can lay in some shadows
here using just some
Prussian blue and white.
There we go.
Any place you want a ridge to stand up,
all you have to do is lay
a shadow underneath it
and automatically it's right there.
Some shadows running down behind this one.
Okay.
Now, with a clean dry brush
I'm gonna diffuse this,
lay it in this mist, I want
this to be misty in the back.
Like it's very, very, very cold.
Where I live, in Fairbanks,
it's not unusual for it
to get 60 or 70 degrees below zero.
And it's always very, very misty.
We have ice fog that forms
and lays in between the trees.
It's cold but it's beautiful.
Mmkay.
Now, let's take here,
a little bit of the grey color
and I'm gonna lighten
it up just a little bit
with a little titanium white.
There, nice color.
Load this brush full of paint
and we'll put a little tree
way back in the distance here.
And I thought today we'd
make these little trees
with the fan brush.
We can make them with a
fan brush, one inch brush,
two and a half inch brush.
Today I thought we'd do it with this.
And you want these to be very quiet.
Very subdued.
To give the illusion of distance.
Okay, maybe there's
another one right there.
And we can start laying in a
little bit of snow up here.
And see how that color comes through
and we use that to make the shadow effect.
Mmkay.
And as I say, I want to lay this in mist
so I'm just gonna gently tap this.
I want it to be far away and misty.
Now we'll come forward just a little bit,
drop in some more little trees here.
There we go.
Just go and forth with your fan brush
and you're sorta bending
these bristles downward.
And however many trees you want.
This is your world so
you can put as many
trees in it as you want.
But you notice, these
trees are a little darker
than the first ones we put in.
Mmkay.
Now, let's mist these
up just a little bit.
All I'm doing is just tapping.
Then I'll lift it a little.
And maybe we got a few
little bushes growing
right around here that
just covered with snow.
Okay.
So, we'll put some magic
white and some titanium white,
mix 'em together.
Thin paint will stick to a thick paint.
Then we'll just put these
little sparklers here,
just little snow covered bushes.
There we go.
And we'll put a few little sticks in here.
Mmkay, let's move over to this side
and see what we can put in here.
Trees are closer to you,
they're gonna be getting a little bigger.
There.
And you need to,
when you're making these
evergreen trees here,
you need to leave spots
open in between the limbs.
Birds have got to have a place to sit
and wind's gotta get through.
Don't kill all those.
Get away from the little
Christmas tree things
we used to make when
we were kids in school.
Trees don't grow even,
they don't grow straight.
However makes them happy
according to the weather, the conditions,
the amount of heat or cold.
All these things effect
the way a tree looks.
Okay.
Maybe we want one right in the front.
I just made this a little
darker so he stands out.
A little baby tree right there.
See, because he's a
little darker now he shows
otherwise he wouldn't show.
He'd just lay in there and be quiet
and you'd never know he was there.
Now we know he's there.
Gonna tap this just gently.
Okay.
And let's have this come down like this.
We'll just make another little thing
coming right down through here.
Change the angle.
Mmkay.
Pull that right through.
This is a very cold picture,
I may have to go get my
coat here in a second,
it's about to freeze me to death.
There we go.
And as you can see,
where the paint breaks,
shadows automatically happen in the snow.
It's very rare that snow is pure white.
You always have the shadows
and you have some dirt
that shows through and
all those little things.
Okay, we'll have some of those nice little
snow covered bushes on this side too.
Don't want this side to get jealous.
Okay, a little magic white,
a little plain white.
There we go.
Nice little snow covered bushes.
Maybe, if we had such a beautiful scene,
maybe we'd need a little cabin about here.
We have to have a little
hunter's cabin or something
right out through here.
So first I'll take and
scrape off the basic shape.
This gets rid of all this
loose paint, the thinner paint
so we'll have something to work on here.
And we'll take that off.
It's also a very good
way to lay in your cabin,
to work on a perspective and lay it out
exactly the way you want it.
And just a general shape.
The big thing is to get
the loose paint off.
Okay, now we'll take a
little Van Dyke brown
and we'll back this back eave back here.
Just like so, nice and dark.
There we go.
Then we'll lay a roof on here.
There.
Just a little bitty cabin
out here in the woods.
Little snow on the other side.
Maybe the snow's pretty thick
so we'll lay it on there
nice and thick so it looks strong.
Then we'll put the front on.
Mmkay.
Son of a gun, there he comes.
Mmkay, let's make this an old cabin.
So we'll just make it
weather beaten, old boards.
Lay some shadows on top of that.
This is Van Dyke brown again,
I'm just sort of
alternating back and forth
between brown and white to
make it look very, very old.
This old hunter he...
He went out after moose, it was too big
and he ran off with him.
So the old cabin's just
standing here abandoned.
Better put a door on it though.
Maybe a passing hunter would
like to stay here overnight.
There we go.
And we'll make this an old slab cabin.
We'll just put some boards right in there.
Mmkay.
And you can, if you wanna
push this back a little bit,
we can put a darker color on here first.
We'll just push this cabin right back into
the bushes a little bit and
we'll have some little bushes
growing right down like that.
Little big of magic.
Okay.
Maybe when this old fella lived here,
maybe he had a little fence that ran back.
He might've had an animal
or two he kept in here
so let's just put a little fence.
And this little fence is
running over the hill.
We'll just let it go right
on back over the hill.
Just see the top of that one.
And a little bit of highlight.
Then a little bit of
snow on top of the posts.
There we go.
Okay, then we can run
some wire right down this
and let it disappear right over the hill.
Like so.
Okay, maybe a couple little
bushes out here in the front.
And I think we need some icicles.
So we'll use just straight magic white
and we'll pull down some
little icicles here.
Using the liner brush, this
is a number two script liner.
Whew, it's getting colder already.
Mmkay.
Let's move out the snow a little.
And let's put a few more
little sticks here and there.
Mmkay.
This is truly an almighty mountain.
There we go, few little
sticks here and there.
Maybe here and there
are little indications.
Mmkay.
Just here and there,
we don't wanna overdo.
We want this to look
very soft, very misty,
far, far away.
Mmkay.
Take a little thin oil here.
And we'll just sign this
happy little picture.
And I hope in the last 30
minutes we have shown you
something that you can do very quickly.
A way to make some almighty
clouds, almighty mountains.
Some fantastic things using
very, very limited pallet.
We've used mostly blue, brown
and white in this picture;
almost nothing else at all.
But it's a very effective picture
and it has a tremendous sky.
You can work on this sky.
Once again, you have
unlimited time at home.
You can take this sky to points
that are almost unbelievable.
You can work it, you can
alternate between darks and lights
in the sky.
You can make skies that almost
look like religious skies,
that things are gonna come through.
Practice it, work with
it, don't give up on it.
All you need is a dream in here
that you wanna put on there.
And we thank you very, very
much for being with us today.
Once again, if you have
questions, if you have comments,
feel free to drop us a line.
We'll be glad to answer
any question that we can.
From all of us here, happy painting.
Thank you very, very much for watching.
(relaxing guitar music)