hey I'm really really glad you could
join me today today is a very special
day to me and I'd like to share that
special day with you today marks a sort
of an anniversary for us where this
painting we will have one hundred joy of
painting shows isn't it fantastic it's
it's almost unbelievable to me then we
have a hundred shows now and I owe it to
you because you've allowed me into your
home each week you've called your PBS
station you've wrote letters you've made
it possible and I'd like to tell you
thank you and I hope you enjoy this
painting so let's go on up and let's get
started
let's say today we'll have them run all
the colors across the screen that you
need to do the painting starting with
the white and working around and that'll
tell you everything that you need to
paint this beautiful painting let's talk
a little bit as I have done on one of
the earlier shows I've taken and covered
the canvas with contact paper this is
just ordinary contact paper you can buy
at your local hardware store or
supermarket whatever and I've just cut a
design out here now in all honesty this
design came from a placemat off my table
so anything you can find to make a
nice-looking design you can use it and
then I've covered the outside of the
canvas with a contact paper and we're
ready to go and on that we'll do a
pretty little painting so let's get
started I'm going to take off with a
small amount a cadmium yellow just the
least little touch least little touch
will do a bright shiny pictures go right
in here and I'll just go across just
like it yes like so without cleaning the
brush I'm going right into a little bit
of yellow ochre same old dirty brush and
just lay a little touch so it blends
right into that like
here once again without cleaning the
brush I'm going into a little bit of the
bright-red
little bit it's very very strong and not
just put a little layer red right across
there okay it's sort of just very gently
very gently blend all those together you
don't want to look like stripes just
flame it together all righty now then
then I'm going to take a fan brush and
go right into a little touch of the
midnight black just a little bit just go
up here and up in here I'm going to
bounce in some happy little happy little
cloud shapes just let that brush plating
just work right down into the red keep
the brush moving little circles little
tiny circles just let it go every which
way here and there okay
you know wash that little brush just a
little bit of paint thinner and very
gently just gonna blend that black right
here on the bottom sort of blend it all
together now then under the black I'm
gonna go into the dark Sienna same old
fan brush okay let's go back up here and
just put in a little bit of this
beautiful beautiful brown color and let
it play around
I can't
just sort of warms up the sky and I have
several fan brushes going so I don't
have to spend a lot of time washing
brushes so I'll take some red and
titanium white just to make a nice pink
color with that let's go right up here
and we just bounce in some happy little
cloud shapes just little tiny tiny
circles ke from going keep them going
and I did pick up some of that under
color so it all mixes together there
some of the Browns and a little bit of a
black now with a clean dry brush very
gently very gently just blend all this
together you don't want to kill all the
little clouds now these dark colors
underneath here well absolutely
eat up your light colors so be very
careful don't want to eat them all up
you can make a fantastic little sky that
easy
very gentle hero3 hairs and some air and
you can beat the brush in that that
removes the excess paint you don't have
to go through all the cleaning
procedures look at there now just gently
blend it and you have an all-night esky
all righty
we got us a little sky let me wash this
brush as you know we wash the brushes
with odorless tanner shake them off and
just beat the devil out of them
alright let's get the old round brush
I'm go right into some Van Dyck Brown
some of the dark Sienna maybe a touch of
the SAP green in there too just a little
bit let's drop in some some happy little
tree shapes and we're gonna put in some
little background trees just tapping
just happy you know as I said at the
beginning of the show this is a very
very special show to me because it marks
100 joy at painting shows me as far as
we know as of the filming of this show
that's gosh I said most painting shows
any series has ever had that's unreal
and there's been a lot of fantastic
people that have helped to make all of
this possible a lot of fantastic people
and I would like to I'd like to dedicate
this painting to a couple of people that
have really made the joy of painting
possible there's been several but I'd
really like to to mention by name first
of all uh my wife Jane she's stood
behind listen and kept his thing going
and takes a special lady to live with a
crazy man and two other people that have
really really been super my business
partners and closest friends Walt Pinet
Kowalski without them there would have
been no joy of painting and would like
to publicly say thank you very much
let's take a little brown here this is
the dark sienna Van Dyke and let's begin
putting in some happy little things
right along here this is where we begin
creating little lay of the land back in
there see how easy that is
hey hey be right over here all this dark
is is just just to give us a base color
so the light will show we put it on top
there we go
all right all right I'm gonna take the
liner brush a little bit of paint
thinner on it make that paint a stain is
water turn that brush pull it ends and
let's put some let's put a few
indications of some little tree trunks
we back we back in the distance there's
one before he just came right up above
the trees see there kitty and you can
put as many or as few as you want in
your painting there we go
start all over yeah let's start putting
some highlights on there I'll just go
back into this little round brush same
old dirty brush I haven't cleaned it
will tap in some yellows I'll grab a
little green SAP green and we just tap
it in I got some yellow ochre CAD yellow
little Indian yellow okay let's go up
here just using the very top corner of
the brush just put in some happy little
shapes don't kill all your dark areas
don't kill them all look at that see if
you put too much detail then it's gonna
look too close and we want this to look
like it's far far away and very quiet
soft there I had a little bit of the
bright red to that Keller oh look at
there there's a nice one nice one
okay
right there Oh cans of things and work
in layers layer after layer after layer
that's what agreed to depth in your
painting okay now we can come down here
put in a little more of the dark and we
can start putting into highlights as I
say this is where you really begin
figuring out the lay of the lamp so
let's begin dropping it like so okay
once we have this dark here either
then we're ready so same whole dirty
brush I'm gonna go right into some of
the yellows and tap it see just tap it
okay let's go right up here now then
just begin touching
very gentle like so and you can make
layer after layer after layer what
you're doing this if you had trouble
getting your paint a stick add a little
bit of the liquid white or a small
amount of paint thinner just to make
your pain a little dinner I added a
touch of the bright red there just get
it to stand out a little see you can
just make layer after layer nice and
right there we go anywhere you want to
he'll just put a little bright area and
it creates the illusion of a a happy
little hillock there well just I don't
know go in there and let it work right
on up and just let your imagination go
when you're doing these at home the open
here we'll just pull that across we'll
come back and play with that later watch
you now we'll take a fan brush and very
gently with a fan brush let's make the
indication of just just a happy little
path that lives right up here all you're
doing is grabbing a little bit that
color I'm just pulling it if you want to
you here and there you can add a little
bit of brown just to make it look more
like dirt but allow it to grab these
colors just glitter I don't know
you got a little path that easy my head
with a touch of titanium point there
just to make it look like there's a
little Sun playing through there just a
little sunshine okay we can take the
knife and just scratch into indication
of a few little trunks back in these
distant trees the background trees just
hearing there now then let's me find my
fan brush we'll go into some brown and
some of the midnight black let's build a
little tree let's have some fun a lot of
paint on the brush let's go right up
here maybe their lives right here right
here just a happy little evergreen tree
all I'm doing is just just barely
touching the canvas and I take the
corner of the brush and give it a little
upward push see give it a little huh
we'll put some little blooms out here on
him just like so make his trunk nice and
strong give him a little foots he's got
to have something to stand on something
to stand on okay maybe he's got a friend
that lives yep right there right there
his friends a little bigger a little
stronger maybe he's got two friends just
like yeah
now then on these they're a little
closer so you'd see a little more detail
I'm gonna take a little white on another
fan brush and just very gently very
gently come along this edge and put a
little bit of highlight just to make
them stand out a little better and you
can take your script liner brush a
little bit of the liquid black and put a
little film here and there see there
just a couple happy little limbs in fact
earth two inch brush and just sort of
blend his little foots right into the
right into the little grassy areas that
easy factor black brown mixture let's go
up here maybe yeah there we are it's a
happy little leaf little limbs little
leaves on these trees just live right
about there
I can't and then same will brush I'll go
right into a little bit of yellow
cuz there's black on there when you hit
that yellow it's gonna turn a beautiful
green color loaded full let's go back up
here now you can come back and just put
some highlights to want to cover all the
dark maybe I'll make it a little bit
brighter so you can see it a little more
that yep there it shows up a little
better for you see they're nice leaves
there and maybe there's even a few
shining on this one back here he's
father well you're not gonna see as much
detail on that one alright I think we're
I think we're coming right along here
Brad now then let's have some fun let's
bring the camera right up close here
this is where the fun starts they grab
this contact paper
take this off look at that look at that
isn't that fantastic see it already you
have all you nice borders and around
here and what's really fun when you're
doing this at home you might want to
paint this oh like a nice tan color or a
very light like chalk powder blue you
can do all kinds of things so it looks
like borders looks like it's matted
around there when you get all finished I
get I get excited about these there are
a lot of fun okay go right into some
alizarin crimson a little bit of the
phthalo blue proportionately much more
crimson and the blue much more crimson
just tap that big brush in round brush
now here we go this is what's fun to me
I like to come out of these borders that
we created and let the painting actually
extend right out of the borders and all
we're doing here is just tapping in some
very basic little shapes where you want
some happy little things to be just like
so see and we're totally killing this
border okay now then I'll just use the
same will brush we'll go right into some
Van Dyck Brown dark sienna and we'll put
another little tree there's right here
just all kinds of little trees see how
those little things happen maybe there's
a heavy bush it goes right here
these are really fun paintings I hope
you try some of them they're so so
effective that comes right on down
wherever you want it to go wherever over
here not much color that it like a
vignette just let it get softer and
softer and softer over here toward the
edges there we go all right now then
we'll take a liner brush let's put some
paint thinner on it and go right into
our Brown turn that brush bring it to a
nice sure point okay now then let's go
right up in here and here some nice tree
limbs let's set them true right out onto
the pure white canvas see there look at
him just here and there just here
wherever there is something we over
there look at there you can just make
all kinds of happy little eels this is
just brown with paint thinner so it
flows there we go
but you have to make big decisions here
how many limbs live in your painting
just however many you want that's all
okay I may be down here just to change
things a little bit maybe maybe this
tree has a white trunk so I'll just use
a little bit of the liquid white and
we'll put a little white trunk in there
is that easy I like to turn that brush
it picks up all those under colors and
makes beautiful little effects say there
see how that stands out though if you
put dark against dark you wouldn't have
a whole bunch but when you put this
light against the dark
oh they stand out and shine for you
there maybe there's a little one right
here however many you want that's up to
you now we can have some fun let's take
the old two-inch brush and we'll go
right into some color here this is
yellow and green and I'm just tapping it
like so okay let's go up here now then
right along in here just barely touching
the canvas just put in a happy little
leaf here there and let some of them
extend out over your dark under color
that helps create the illusion of a of a
vignette see there
no these paintings really excite me this
is this is reason I chose to do this
type of painting on such a special day
I'm really glad you joined me for this
status as I say Dee you just can't
believe how special this is for me and
you've made it possible there there we
go
now let's put some let's put some things
in here I'll go back to the round brush
it's a lot of fun I'm just tapping into
a little yellow ochre and little green
reach over here get a touch of the
bright red just a touch
it's very strong very strong just go up
here now then just using the top corner
just the very top God just tap in all
kinds a little leafy effects after paint
won't stick I've set it over and over
add a little bit of liquid white or a
little bit of thinner let him just come
right on because a thin paint will stick
to a thick paint then the thick it's
probably our golden rule signal illest
project right on out past the dark
there's another happy little Bush that's
right there see I knew he was there you
did too didn't he you knew he was there
there we go there's another little Bush
he lives right there okay coming right
on forward oh there's one he's looks
like he's got little flowers on him
happy blush it's only kind of bushes we
make they're always happy and we'll just
sort of let some little things just just
graduate out into here just let the
color just sort of disappear gentle
gentle light little touch see there
these are very soft little paintings
these make excellent gifts for all your
friends people really love these and
when you frame them oh you can't believe
how pretty they are can't believe and
your friends will say you didn't paint
that but you know you did and you can
you can do it take just that Klein point
of knife and scrape down a few little
sticks and trunk indications here and
there
just like so oh right you know me I'm
not happy when we paint unless we have a
big tree in there so let's put a big
tree I don't go right into the midnight
black and the Van Dyck Brown
lololololololololol just be happy mix up
all these colors look at all the paint
nut brush let's go up here I said I
wanted a big tree so let's do a penguin
I think my big tree lives don't yell at
me don't yell at me he lives right there
there he comes oh goodness
big ol tree he goes right off the canvas
strong tree big tree look at that
be brave hey right maybe he's got a big
foot it comes right down here I can't
make old foot all right now I've got
another fan brush and I used dirt it's
got white on it so we'll just take it it
will come right down the side here come
right down the outside edge first see
and tap this tap this makes a tree bark
looks sort of fuzzy and that to me is
the way the way old evergreen trees look
they got a sort of textured bark ruff
maybe right in here see how you can
divide that tree up and create a little
hollow in there shoot ESCO that's where
some little creature lives right in
there
he needs a little house
yeah then liner brush right into some of
the liquid black and let's take and put
the limb right there right there
sinking put as many limbs as you want in
yours we just put a few in just to show
you how this is just straight liquid
black same there we go
and have some in there that are broken
off evergreens especially why they they
have a lot of oil to get broke off yeah
this is where all the little squirrels
come and set the plane they have to have
a good time too now while we had this
liquid black going here let's just work
on look at there we'll just have it big
oh root just come right on down just
sort of hangs right on off the canvas
look at that and there's one right there
and maybe maybe there's one it comes
over the other way just use your
imagination here
let's sudden these little things just
sort of happen okay we can go right into
a touch of the liquid white got a little
highlight right out here just like you
just might care isn't that something
that's something I like these little
paintings and I really hope you do and
I'm glad that you've been with me today
to share this special day thank you very
much for being with me today I like for
all my friends to to enjoy special days
with me and I have so many beautiful
friends all over the country that the
painting shows have allowed me to meet
alright let's go back to her brush it
has the black in it this is just
midnight black let's go right up in here
and let's put in there they are
she's beautiful little leaves on this
big evergreen tree wherever you think
they should live scene I like this here
because it breaks the border there but
leaves it there so you can see it that's
one of them happy accidents we're always
talking about learn to use them learn to
make friends with that it'll be enough
to show home I want to show hey there
right there okay now then take another
fan brush
we'll use yellow and SAP green yellow
SAP green little lot of color on the
brush okay let's go right back up here
now then come right along in here and
highlight these just put some happy
little highlights right in there that
easy and it'll make your painting
complete so if you paint along with me
all you need right now is to sign your
masterpiece and it'll be finished and
we're gonna call this one finished once
again thanks for being with me today
happy painting and god bless
you