- Hi, welcome back.
I'm certainly glad you
could join me today.
I thought today we'd just do a
fantastic little seascape.
I'll show you how easy
you can do one of those.
Let's start out and have them run
all the colors across the screen
that you need to paint along with me.
While they're doing that,
let me show you what I've got done.
Have my regular old canvas up here,
except today I've covered
the bottom part of it here
and up the side, with Black Gesso.
And I've allowed that to dry completely.
And after it's dry, be sure it's dry,
it takes about 30 - 40
minutes for it to dry.
And it's totally different
now than Liquid Black.
This is Black Gesso, which is an acrylic.
Then we've taken transparent color.
I've put a little Alizarin Crimson
and Dark Sienna mixture in here.
And a little Sap Green
and brown down in here.
Down here is just a little brown.
The white part we've covered,
as usual, with Liquid White.
So it's completely wet and ready to go.
So let's just have some fun today.
I'm gonna start out with
the old two-inch brush.
We'll go into the least little
touch of the Indian Yellow.
Just a small amount.
And we'll go right up here.
And let's just dance in
a happy little sky today.
Let's do a seascape that's very
bright and shiny and pretty.
There we go, little Cad Yellow.
Vary the yellows here.
Started with Indian Yellow,
now we're into Cad Yellow.
Shoot, now I'm gonna go into
a little bit of Yellow Ochre.
And Yellow Ochre's sort of a
gold color, it's very pretty.
Very pretty color, I like it.
We just let it come right on around,
maybe something like that.
Wherever, just make some decisions.
Then we'll take a little of the Bright Red
and we have not cleaned the brush yet.
I like these kind of paintings
where I don't have to
clean the brush much, I'm
sort of a lazy painter.
There.
But by allowing these
colors to blend on the brush
and on the canvas, you get a multitude of
different values and colors,
rather than just one old flat color.
Shoot, put some excitement in your world.
There we go.
I tell you what, let's just paint it
all the way down here to the water line.
This is just a little
piece of masking tape
I have across here.
Just to keep the water line straight.
There.
Sometimes my hand's a little shaky,
so I need all the help I can get.
So we just use a little
piece of masking tape.
You don't have to have that
there, if you don't want it.
Just makes it a little easier.
Gently, gently blend all these together.
Maybe I'll put a little
of that color on the brush
up here too, just to fill in the sky.
Just blend it all together.
So you can't tell where one color stops
and the next color starts.
There we go.
And you can make this
brighter or duller, whatever.
(brush rubbing across the canvas)
Okay.
Now then, let me grab another brush.
I have several brushes going,
so I don't have to spend
all my time washing them.
I'm gonna go right into
a little Titanium White.
Pure Titanium White.
Right up here, I'm gonna
put a little of this white.
I wanna make a bright spot in this sky.
It won't look all that
bright at this point,
but it will when we get
a little further along.
There.
(brush sweeping across canvas)
Just really give a nice sparkle up here.
Okay.
Maybe, maybe ... I didn't
realize how much I said that,
till a little boy one
day, about ten years old,
began mocking me.
He was walking around saying,
"Maybe, maybe, maybe."
(Bob snickers)
All right, I'm gonna make up
a little lavender color here,
using Alizarin Crimson and Phthalo Blue.
Much, much more crimson than blue.
Something like so.
Let me clean off the old knife.
And here's a dirty brush,
we'll just use that.
Has a little of that sky color on it.
I'm just gonna tap the bristles into that.
(brush tapping on palette)
Just tap a little bit, like so.
Let's go up in here and let's
make some nice little clouds
that just float around
and have fun all day.
Just sorta wind 'em up
and put 'em in there, see.
There.
Okay.
Wherever you think they should be.
(brush swishing on canvas)
I'm gonna just have 'em
come right over here.
This is gonna be a big cliff, I think.
A big rocky thing lives right there.
Just drop it in.
All right, there we go.
And by using these little twisting
or circular patterns here, it creates
a multitude of little
things happening up here.
It's not just a flat ol' dead sky.
Lot of nice things going on.
There.
Okay.
Maybe we'll come right over in here.
And I'm just gonna put clouds
all over the sky like this.
Okay, there we are.
Maybe it comes right down.
Just load a little more color.
There.
Maybe there's a little
protrusion right out here.
Wherever you want 'em.
There.
I tell you what, while I'm doing this,
because this is going
to take just a second.
I wanna show you one
of my little characters
that's living with me now.
I have three little baby
squirrels that I'm raising
and they are they cutest little devils.
We took a little video of 'em,
and I wanna share that with
you while I'm doing this.
And I won't do anything
I don't tell you about
while that's coming on there.
Now these are tiny little baby ones.
They're just beginning
to get a little fur.
I've had them now since just
after their eyes opened.
These little rascals
are hungry continually.
So, I thought I'd show
you how we feed 'em.
To do that, we take ... I
just use a little syringe,
with a little nipple on the end of it.
It's just like goin' to the
doctor and gettin' your shot
when it's feeding time here.
We fill'er up and normally though,
when you see a syringe comin' at you,
sorta scares you a little
bit, but in this case,
when my little friends here
see a syringe coming at 'em,
they get excited.
This just makes their whole day.
It's hard to get 'em
to eat, as you can see.
(Bob laughing)
I think they'll eat
about every 15 minutes,
if you'd feed 'em.
I have three of those little rascals now
and they live with me,
and my mother and I,
and Nancy, we all take care
of these little devils.
They're gonna soon be big enough
to turn loose and let 'em go.
There.
I'm just putting in a few
little clouds down here,
while you was watching
the little squirrels.
Still just using the corner of the brush
and just making little circular patterns.
Just round and around and around we go.
Just sorta stir it up.
Just stir it up, is all we're
trying to do at this point.
But we don't want a lot
of paint on the canvas.
All we're looking for is a little stain.
There.
Sometimes you can just decide where
it should be a little
darker, a little lighter.
Shoot, maybe there's
even a little projection
that comes right out through there.
See, that easy.
Just by tapping.
You can make all those little things.
Okay.
Grabbing another clean brush.
This is clean, has nothing on it.
It's very dry.
And with that, you can just
begin blending this now.
To any degree of softness
or harshness that you want.
Just blend it.
Aren't those little squirrels cute?
I really like those little devils.
They're so much fun.
You spend a little time with
one of these, and it certainly
makes you appreciate nature
and all of God's wisdom
when He created these little characters.
You get addicted to 'em.
Especially my young friends.
I have a lot of children that
live around where I live,
and I let 'em come over and help me
feed the little squirrels and
look at 'em, and hold 'em.
I think everybody should
have the opportunity
to make friends with a
little guy like that.
If you do, you'll certainly
have a greater appreciation
of nature and all the little things
that are runnin' around that we don't
pay a lot of attention to.
There we go.
Now then.
(brush banging)
Just knockin' off the excess paint.
Very gently, very gently,
we can just blend that.
But isn't that a fantastic
way of making a sky that's ...
(soft delighted exclamation)
Sun gonna jump out and get you.
And you can do that.
(brush banging)
All right, time to wash your brush.
And as you now, we wash our brushes
just with odorless thinner.
(banging brush)
(Bob laughing)
Just beat the devil out of 'em.
Maybe I'll wash two, I dirtied up
several while we were doing that.
(brush slapping and banging)
That's double your pleasure.
Okay, now the little piece
of masking tape right here.
Let's take it off.
(masking tape peeling)
See, now that leaves you with
a very straight, smooth horizon.
But there was no color
under that, so I'll take
a little bit of the crimson
and little Dark Sienna.
I'm just gonna, probably
this won't even show up,
but I'm just scrubbing a little
transparent color on there.
Just bringin' that all together.
This is just the crimson
and a little Dark Sienna.
There, right up to the water line.
Okay, just sorta blend it together.
(brush sweeping across the canvas)
All right.
Now then, we have to make
some big major decisions here.
You know me, I like to have
these big crashing waves.
I don't like just doing
these little subdued waves,
but if you like those, you
can do those the same way
as we do the little waves
in the back, very simply.
Maybe, in our world, our
wave's gonna live right here.
You can take a fan brush or filbert brush
and just make sort of
a little outline of ...
(swooshing sound)
There.
That's gonna be our wave, right there.
Now then, with a little
touch of the Titanium White,
and I'm using a number three fan brush.
I'm gonna go right up here to
the horizon and just begin.
Come up close right here.
I'm just making strokes
where I'm going like this.
I'm really exaggerating, but like that.
I'm exaggerating, but it looks like
little watery things back here.
There.
Okay, now that's one of the nicest,
easiest, simplest little
ways that I've ever found
just to make the indication
of water back in there.
I'm gonna add the least
little touch of Cad Yellow
to my color right in here.
Oh, that's nice.
That's beginning to sparkle.
Little bit more.
See it looks like light, just
shining right across there.
There we go.
This is just some background material.
Now then, let me wash the old brush.
(paint thinner splashing)
(brush tapping and wiping dry)
Now the fun part, right in here.
That's the eye of the wave.
We'll just take some Titanium White
and just, as my son Steve says,
"Just mush it in there."
Really push it in there hard.
You can do this several times.
If it gets like there's a
lot of color underneath,
remove that excess paint
and that remains there.
That color remains there.
We can take a little more of our white,
add a little of the Cad Yellow to that.
Go right back in here, see there.
Each time you do that
it'll get lighter in value.
Or you can take a rag or
something and just wipe that out.
Whichever way you'd like to do it.
Maybe it comes right on back, like so.
Just scrub it in.
Now then.
(brush banging)
Clean, dry, two-inch brush.
I'm only gonna use the top corner
and you put it there and you just
sort of wind it up, just wiggle it.
There.
You can make this as smooth as silk.
So smooth.
But there's not a lot of movement.
You're sorta just going around
in little tight circles.
There we go.
Then begin thinking about how
you want your water to flow.
(brush sweeping across canvas)
There.
(brush banging)
Knock off that excess paint.
That's an easy way of just
about getting your brush clean,
without going through
that whole procedure.
(brush scrubbing canvas)
There.
Okay.
Let me find a fan brush here,
got several of them going.
Maybe, in our world, we want to have
this water crashing over something.
Grab it and pull, think
about the angle though.
Angles are very important.
Very important.
Think about that water.
(makes wave sound, laughs)
Make those little noises.
That really helps.
There.
Just think about it crashing over.
That's all that we need at this point.
Now, if you want to bring some of that
dark back with a clean brush,
you can just grab it and lift it upward.
That'll very gently blend it all together.
See there.
You can work back and
forth, until you get it
exactly the way that you want it.
Okay, let me go back and get my
little number three fan brush.
I like this little fan brush.
It's good for makin' little foamy things,
and stuff like that.
Take a little white and
then I'm going into that
nice lavender color we used in the sky.
Make sort of a medium value lavender.
Okay, let's go back up in here.
Now then, let's start thinking about
having some nice foam out here.
Just using the corner of the
fan brush, and once again,
you can do this with a
filbert, just as well.
The little number six filbert
brush would work just as well.
I just happened to have
this, so we'll use it.
All we're doing here is
putting in some shadows.
Some nice dark areas for the foam.
Think about the water
churning and bubbling
and splashing and carrying on.
(makes wave noise)
Crashing.
Maybe it comes right
over here, I don't know.
Wherever you want it.
Okay, I'm gonna wash that old brush.
(paint thinner splashing)
I like to do seascapes.
They're a lot of fun and they'll force you
to study water and how it
moves and churns, and etc.
Go to the ocean.
Or get a video, or photographs
of water, just study.
If you don't live near the
ocean, then look in books
and videos and stuff like that,
and you can see all of this.
Now, I've got just Titanium
White and I'm going
right up here on top of this darker color.
Just gonna take the fan brush here
and scrub in a little highlight.
Wipe the brush off when you load it,
so you have nice, clean color.
There.
Just wipe it on a paper towel in between.
Think about that water, hittin'
and splashin' and churning.
Make up little stories
and sounds in your mind
and just let it happen.
Let it happen.
There.
(brush scrubbing)
Now then, back to our large brush.
(brush banging)
I use the large brush,
only because it seems
to have a little more hair
in it, and it blends better.
You could do this with a one-inch
brush, if you would like.
I'm sort of hung up on this ol'
big brush, but try 'em both.
See which one works the best for you.
That's the one you are to use.
Maybe over here, a little
bit right in here too.
Just that nice churning.
Maybe there's even a little,
splashin' down like that.
Whatever.
There.
That ol' water is comin'
down through here.
I'm gonna add the least
little touch of Phthalo Blue
into that color.
I want a little bluish
... oh, that's nice.
That is nice, I like that.
Begin thinking about how
your water is coming up.
Right up in this transparency, or the eye.
Just Phthalo Blue and white, once again.
There.
Maybe it comes down here and ...
(wave noise)
Think about shape though.
Maybe there's a nice ...
Shoot, maybe there's something right here.
Let that water come up and fall over.
We're creating a trough
or a valley in here.
Okay, here it comes.
There.
Just wherever.
(brush scrubbing canvas)
Little bit more of the
Phthalo Blue and white.
There.
Just let that splash and curl.
(makes splashing sound)
Big things comin' down through here.
This is what gives shape
and form to your wave.
I tell you, maybe, even in here,
let's just use the corner of the brush.
Maybe the water's splashing,
crashing right along in here.
There may be another
little splasher in there.
Who knows?
This is your world, so you can do
anything that you want to do.
Anything that you want to do.
Let me take a large brush.
and just sort of blend that together.
We're beginning to get
into little bit of that
Sap Green and Van Dyke Brown
stuff that's down here.
All right, let me get the liner brush out.
I like that little liner brush.
We'll take that.
I wanna go into a little bit
of that same lavender color
that had a little white in it,
same color we have up here.
Let's just sorta highlight this edge here,
with a little color.
Make it nice and firm.
Then begin putting in some little shapes.
Just some little doers in there that
create all the little shapes
and stuff that you want in here.
Paint thinner with a little
color, is all I have here.
Use a little of that
blue and white in here.
This is where you can begin
putting in all kinds of little details.
At home you have unlimited time.
You can really set and make beautiful
little things in there, put
all those little details.
While I've got that
going, maybe back in here
you can see all these little doers.
Little Titanium White
with paint thinner on it.
Highlight some of the brighter ones,
where you think light would hit.
There.
As I say, these little details is what
really will make your
seascape spectacular.
Now then.
Okay.
Reach down here, get a little
touch more of that paint thinner.
Just let some of these little things
wiggle and jiggle and your hand shake.
I've had people write and tell me
they had a little nervous
twitch in their hand,
they had a hard time painting.
Sometimes, that's a very valuable asset.
Use it to your advantage.
There.
Tell you what.
Let's have some fun.
Now, this big ledge up here,
I've already covered that
with a little bit of brown,
as I mentioned earlier.
Let's take a little Dark Sienna,
grab a little white, Alizarin Crimson.
Just sorta mix those loosely.
I'm just gonna mix 'em on a brush.
Maybe even a little touch
of the Yellow Ochre.
Not much, just a little.
Okay, just on the fan brush.
Let's go up here.
Let's begin thinking about shapes here.
All you have to do is just tap.
Take the fan brush and tap.
That's really all it amounts to.
And you can begin forming your rocks.
Just by tapping, just tap.
In here and there you can
add a little light color.
Wherever you think light would
strike and bounce and play.
There.
Leave some dark areas in here.
Dark areas will end up being
big holes in the rocks.
Little place for the seagulls to go.
They gotta have a place to build a nest.
In Alaska, we have little puffins.
They're one of the cutest
little birds God's ever made.
Looks like their beak's
too big for their head.
Beautiful little birds.
There.
But just form these, just like so.
And you could do this with a knife.
I just want to show you several
different ways of doing it.
But the knife will work very well
for making very nice rock effects.
There, try to stand out of
the way so you can see there.
Maybe this comes right on down
into here somewhere, like so.
I got several fan brushes going,
let me get another one here.
I want a rock on the other side too.
Right there.
(whooshing sound)
I bet you knew I was going to
put a rock there, didn't you?
I always like big rocks,
big trees in my paintings.
Just sorta decide how you think that
old rock should live in
there, and drop it in.
We can take some of that color,
come right along in here, and once again,
this is a nice way of outlining
and forming your stones and rocks.
There.
(brush tapping canvas)
I want this one to remain quite dark.
Quite dark, so it doesn't
distract too much.
There we go.
Now you can take a clean,
dry, two-inch brush
and very gently, just caress it.
Just caress it.
It'll blend all that together.
Make it nice and smooth,
and it looks like beautiful stones then.
But very, very gently.
One hair and some air.
There.
Little bit of our Phthalo Blue and white.
We'll have a little splash,
comin' round down through here.
(makes soft splashing sound)
Shoot, maybe there's even a
little water drippin' down.
You could do this with a
liner brush or the fan brush.
Just whatever.
Maybe there's even a ...
(makes wave sound)
Right there.
Look at there, let that
come right on back, like so.
See, just bring it all together.
Then a little bit in the foreground.
These seascapes are not
near as hard as they look.
You really can do these.
Maybe, let's get crazy.
We have a second cleft here, so we'll put
a little stone right here too.
I just like to have stones
all out in the water.
I like it, it just enhances my paintings.
Little bit of the nice highlight color.
Let's see here, we could
take the liner brush,
little of that Phthalo Blue and white,
and paint thinner.
Thin it down and you can
literally have water dripping,
right off these rocks, just like so.
Let some of this just ...
(makes wave sound)
Put all these little things in.
It's a super way though, of making
very effective little seascapes like this.
There.
Okay, little bit right in there.
Just make decisions,
where you think the water
would be churnin' and splashin',
maybe all around this rock.
Just using the corner
of the fan brush though.
That's all we're using.
All back in here there would be.
We'll have some churning
back against that big rock.
Little misty areas, like so.
And you can just keep on and on and on.
But there comes a time
when we have to stop.
I tell you what, we'll just take a touch,
a little touch of dark color.
We'll put one little lonely bird up here.
Little "m" bird.
And I think with that,
we'll call this ol' painting finished.
Hope this gives you an idea
of how to do a fantastic seascape at home.
If you give it a try, you will love it.
And I'd love to see some
photographs of what you're doing.
If you have time, drop us a line.
Let us know if you like the show.
Send us some pictures
of what you're doing.
From all of us here, I'd like to wish you
happy painting and God bless, my friend.