hey welcome back certainly glad you
could join me again today
got your palace set up let's get going
here
let's start off from having graphically
run all the colors across the screen
that you need to do this painting with
me and they'll come across as usual in
the same order that I have them on the
palette starting with the white and
working around while they're doing that
let's go on up here I've already covered
the canvas with a thin even coat of
liquid white it's nice and wet and slick
and all ready to go
I thought maybe today let's do a little
fall scene where maybe the weather is
not too great you know in the fall we
have a lot of rainy weather now you know
the snows gonna come pretty soon so
let's do something like yet and just
just have some fun I'm gonna start out
using a small a small amount of yellow
ochre just the tiniest little bit a very
small amount and right here sort of make
a determination where the horizons gonna
be and I'm gonna begin swinging this
upward just using strokes like so a
little bit more color don't have a
little water in this paint as you know
I'm I'm sort of a water fanatic like
that water little yellow in here okay
I'm gonna go right into some Van Dyck
Brown in the same way just tap the brush
into it okay let's go right up here put
a little brown right in here I'm
beginning to create these sky angles
just don't let him get too too straight
like this it'll it'll disturb you when
it's done
now I'm gonna take brown and a touch of
Prussian blue let me say that again
a Dutch Prussian blue is so strong just
a little bit miss brown and blue okay
yes we can bring that all together add a
touch of the midnight black to it so now
we have in the sky we have a little bit
of yellow ochre some Brown sort of
pression blue and some midnight black
we just gonna sort of work all of these
Baskerville colors together try to keep
the blue off that yellow or you'll get a
very pretty sky and then before we start
blending them we still have a dirty old
brush and we'll take some more the
Prussian blue and a little bit of the
black there we go and let's go ahead and
lay our water in both on the outside in
see if you start if you start from here
and go across watch what happens you
touch here and go across you get this
big line that's bad and then it's hard
to blend out so starting the outside and
come over and that way you don't have
that harsh line that you have to blend
out there we go little tricks like that
save ya save you a lot of agony we want
this to be easy we want it to work for
you okay a little bit more of the
midnight black compression blue mixture
don't want to kill all that nasty yellow
area that you have because of blue
little black ball heat it up in a
heartbeat okay a little darker at the
bottom then there's at the top that'll
help create your illusion of distance
okay let me wash the old brush wash the
old brush shake off the excess that is
the fun part
okay let's go right back up here and I'm
gonna begin blending this together
follow the angles in the sky I'm gonna
use long strokes
start in the light area and work up
toward the darker area that way you
brush is dirty when it gets to the top
use your clean brush in the lighter and
you can just begin bringing all this
together
all of those angles though okay that
gives us a quick happy little sky down
here we just go all the way across
straightens out the water and brings it
all together
and we're ready then I get a little fan
brush here we'll mix up
let's take a little black a little
ground a tiny bit of oppression blue and
a little bit of alizarin crimson into
that I'll put some white here and put a
little bit of that into it yeah add a
little more blue to that and the touch
more crimson there we go
that's sort of what I'm looking for so a
very dark lavender to the blue side it's
very dark it's almost a gray color this
is gonna be a great cloudy day okay let
me wipe off my knife now let's take the
old fan brush and go right through a
little bit of color don't need a lot of
paint on the brush yet stab just a
little and a small amount of Brown into
that a little a little more into the
brownish color there we go
good let's go right up here now back in
here you have to make a decision maybe
their lives some happy little evergreens
just take the corner of the brush just
back and forth
just sort of pop in just a little
evergreen some indications are some that
are even farther away all we see is just
the basic shapes I'm just touching and
sort of pulling it downward so he's make
all cants a little basic shapes see
touch use a top part of the brush if you
just give it a little downward snap
there a little more paint on the brush
maybe over here we got some to be
careful of these will get looking like
fence posts that's good enough yeah I
want to put a few more indication of
some trees that have a little more shape
to them and we're just using the corner
of the brush and just work them in back
and forth these little trees live right
in your fan brush sometimes you have to
sort of scare them out there and you
just put as many or as few as you want
in your world
there we go
he's got a little friend there just drop
them in yeah then I want to create the
illusion of mist back here I want this
to be very soft and very distant so
we'll take the 2 inch brush and tap I'm
using a top corner see look how hard is
hitting it's bending
really getting here and tap it and you
can create the illusion of very very
soft area back here you've let it come
up above some of these they're really
softened so these trees are already
there already just lost ready to be
missed
can you believe how that pushes all that
back
just that little tapping action ok man
now listen let's have another plane in
the painting and a plane I mean just
another area that's closer to you
so we'll take those same old colors
we'll use some brown I'm gonna put some
dark Sienna in there this toe and a
little bit of SAP green as things get
closer we'll begin to see a little more
detail just a little SAP green though ok
brushes are really full of paint let's
go right up in here there it is these
trees are a little closer they're a
little bit bigger
look at that turn it over over to use
both sides of it there we go this trees
stronger he's he got a little more light
okay we don't want him to get lonely so
we'll give him a friend too you know
friends are so important finally the
trees but to us
and through painting I have made oh I've
made hundreds and hundreds of new
friends all over the country and that
may be the most rewarding part of all
this most thrilling part there I take it
one here's a happy little tree you is
right there just sort of just sort of
visualize in your mind where you think
tria true you'd be happy and you put him
in there just put him in de take a
little bit of the dark Sienna and just
tap it onto this brush and then I want
to gather up some of this color that we
had on a tree and begin very softly
putting in little Hills okay there see
pick up some of that tree color and just
let it just let it go there was a tiny
bit of dark Sienna on the brush tiny bit
tiniest little bit see how you can set
those trees out up on a little hill and
they may be getting pulling that down I
don't want this to be very very soft
very quiet I like very gentle little
paintings that when you're doing yours
at home if you want it to be brighter
and stronger just use a little stronger
color cause painting is a very
individual thing there
okay now let's go right back into here
and load up just load that fan brush
full of paint okay tell you what let's
do let's have a tree that lives right
there yeah we take just the corner of
the brush and if we can't working him
down then you can just push that all
free right out of that brush a little
more paint gonna push it hard when you
get down this far when you first start
you're pushing quite easy by the time
you get down here yeah getting tough
with it just wrong with it
little more color okay I'll tell you
what just do it right here big side of a
gun see all these different sizes of
trees help create the illusion of
distance depth in your painting a
beginning to look like follow you sort
of a mean old sky okay now then the Mogu
back into a little tiny tiny a little
bit of the dark sea and a tiny can't say
that enough times and I'm gonna create
another plane here I'm gonna pick up
some of the tree color see ya and all
I'm doing is just tapping the canvas
just half I will bring you right on
cross add the least little touch more of
the sin there see it creates a whole
nother plane and pushes all those trees
back here back into the distance and
that's you
now I'm gonna have water here so let's
take a little bit of that color you just
pull it down so we have a little
reflection I'm using just a little bit
of the dark see I'm a little van Dyck
Brown on the brush to pull down and
create a reflection here just a just a
happy little reflection like right there
and it likely go across okay now then
then we'll take the same old brush
without cleaning it just same old dirty
brush and tap right into a little bit of
the yellow ochre and the bright red and
just tap it gently see just tap ok now
then here this is a little closer so
we're beginning to see an indication of
some highlights and same way just gently
gently tapping that was bright red and a
tiniest little touch of that yellow okay
now the red is very strong be careful
with it be careful of it it'll eat up
your whole world in just a second take a
little brown it was dark Sienna mixed
together pull it out cut across get that
small roll of paint right on the edge of
the knife okay just a little lay on
dedication scrubbing across the canvas
Tiny's little bit add a little white to
that same color like that and then it's
just an indication of a touch of
highlight here I don't I don't want much
highlight in this just to touch here a
little bit of the liquid white got
across it and we'll put just an
indication of a little water right not
too much not too bright okay yeah then
go back into my Browns CNN the Van Dyke
and I'm gonna grab some more this tree
color I'm gonna put a little peninsula I
think it comes right out here and when
you're doing this just step back and
look at your painting and make make
decisions just make decisions pull a
little bit of this color down just a
little go gently gently across the house
same old dirty brush back into my yellow
ocher and bright red mixture just a
little same old dirty brush you can get
over here and a little bit of this CAD
yellow to it sorry yeah see follow the
angles of the land the lay of the land
just follow it right on to have a
brighter on top and it darker darker
darker as it works down if you want to
show a little protrusion here see see
easy that is creates the illusion have
another little hill just by changing the
value of the color for the intensity a
little bit of that right down to the
water go across you have instant
reflections let's play a little bit over
here tell you what this do we use a
round brush and go right into my Browns
us the sienna and the Van Dyck
tap out the excess just go up here
back in here there's some happy little
trees maybe maybe these are the birch
trees and there we back in the distance
just put some little indications thanks
like so use the old script planner brush
just take it a little paint thinner on
it to go right into the brown turn it
bring it to a sharp point
let's put just a few basic very basic
indications of a tree branch here in
there little tree trunk I'm not looking
for a lot of detail same old dirty brush
now go into a small small amount of the
yellow ocher and the bright red smallest
little mouth I'm just barely touching
then I want to just touch right at the
top here put some indications begin
forming some basic little patterns some
little shapes into your trees don't just
throw these on the random I know I say
that in every show but I get the most
letters about that I said my my tree
shapes don't look right and that's
normally normally the problem 99% of the
time the problem is as a color is just
throw it on at random so to look at it
practice it a little bit of practice
here will pay you tremendous dividends
tremendous dividends
just a few little bushes and all kinds
of things okay tell you what a little
brown let's put a little land area right
there see right there I need a little
bit of a highlight color that's just a
little brown and white not too much just
a little here little bit of a liquid
white catus a little waterline I'm going
right back into the Browns I have yet to
wash this brush I've been going back and
forth between the Browns and highlight
colors and now I'm gonna put another
little Peninsula the libs right there so
you don't care if the bottom of it sort
of comes down because you just pull that
down mm-hmm that easy that easy makes a
little reflections and then lightly like
they go across go right into our color
now the ochre bright red little Indian
yellow here and there and they'll care
yellow but a few little highlights on it
okay I mean say ed you can put a little
land under that just a little dirt just
a little dirt like so
and maybe take a little liquid black
maybe there's a happy little tree dude
lives right out there there we go he
lives out on this little Peninsula give
me little foots to stand on don't him
don't him to fall over he's a strong
little tree but all kinds of little
films there we go
few little sticks and twigs down here
and when you're doing this at all you
put as many sticks and threes as you
want in there okay back to my Browns
with surplus bills let's build a little
more here come right down here so to
fill all this up I just see all kinds of
things
Oh - maybe about there once again when
you work in layers working stages
completing the most distant area first
and working forward always working
forward tell you what miss let's have
some fun
we'll put a little cabin back here a
little house would it be nice to live
here and watch all the big Canadian
geese come in and right there that's
where a little house will be we'll give
them a little roof just pulling over
right down there we go all I'm doing
here is blocking in color just pakka get
some color
okay we'll take some white from the dark
Sienna little bit of Van Dyke Brown
probably got flat a little roll of paint
okay I have there's some boards in this
old building that go this way see they
come right across like yeah doop doop
doop well cut him off but that dark and
then maybe down here just maybe a little
log cabin
there's my the indication of some things
going like here look at that look at
that it's now darker cut on this side
just put some indications and we need
something on the roof I had a little
fright red duster color just a tiny bit
and right down the roof here just better
knife sort of basket boo boo boo boo boo
boo boo got to make that noise or don't
work didn't work don't take at least a
little bit of light color just a little
white or something I'm just a highlight
that so it stands out and you can see it
just so you can see it dark down in here
maybe maybe this house had stolons
underneath you just take the point of
the knife in and just very quickly just
scratching in some basic hole stones he
has a basement in his house he's really
got a fancy cabin out here
and get the little toy for a second okay
take a little bit of the Venn diagram
let's have him adorn maybe he's got one
door right down here so we can come
right in the basement cut that right off
where you want it he was just a little
white on the knife to sort of highlight
that and it will take a small agent
knife little bit of Prussian blue just
put the indication of a few little
windows in there I'm that easy makes us
a happy little thing okay let's go back
to to bouncing right into some of this
color bright red yellow ocher CAD yellow
yeah let's come right down in here oh
that's a pretty light now if you have
any trouble at all we can your paint
stick add a little tiny tiny bit okay
liquid white or paint thinner
whichever good white will change your
color a little bit make it a little
brighter
one don't take the little knife again
come right in here we'll put a happy
little path coming out he's got that way
to get down to the lake catch a big fish
it goes down here that'll bit of land
some stones here and there just whatever
brown and white for some highlights
there we go now that let's go back into
our ogres and reds and Indian yellow and
let's begin bringing this right down I
like this little painting because it
really does give you the feeling of fall
just like little layers little things
happening all down through here I'll
tell you what maybe right in here is a
little tree maybe that's just a little
maybe maybe that's a little birch tree
like birch trees and they usually grow
in clumps so you're gonna put several
Evan three aware that birch tree grows
by itself
he's a community tree little bit of
liquid black yeah we can just put the
indication of a happy little them here
and there that really helps push your
little cabin back further into the
painting much further back tell you what
tell you let's have some fun let's go
back into the Browns put another little
peninsula right there and in your world
you put as many or as few of these as
you want just want to show you how to do
it and turn you loose on the world all
that straight down cow right across go
right back into my highlight colors that
yell up hookers and their heads just
come right out here say they're you know
happy highlights now won't take my fan
brush again go right into the Ben Dyke
Brown darks and I just mix them together
okay right here right here
right somewhere right here yeah just
make a decision drop it down big old
tree bagel tree and this big tree will
help push everything in your painting
back helps create much much more depth
than your painting give it a big hole
they go root stand on down here the big
tree has to be grouped just make an
indication of all they own that comes
right out just tap it on a fan brush man
we can take a little bit of the bright
red darks and white together I think so
let's cut across it let's go up here and
just put some highlights on use these
warm colors we're gonna make it feel
like fall hmm I'm gonna get my coat out
and start seeing if it's all right just
a few little highlights here in there
Andy back to my liner brush and right
into the liquid black I said let's have
some blooms that are just hanging there
every which way just drop some of these
in there is a line wherever you wanna
pull them out
see there and you can make all kinds of
beautiful things happen there bill
thank this one's getting close to being
done but a little the ground area right
in here touch a highlight on it and
we'll call this painting finished I hope
you've enjoyed this one it's a nice
little painting could give you a lot of
happy little ideas from all of us here
happy painting god bless