- Hello, glad to see you again.
Thought today we'd do a picture
that's right straight out of Alaska.
We'll do one of Mount McKinley,
the most almighty mountain in
the North American continent.
And we'll start off today,
and we use just a little bit
of Prussian blue, maybe
a touch of phthalo green
mixed with it here.
And let's dance in some basic shapes here.
I've already put the
Magic White on the canvas
to save a little time.
So we're just literally
mixing color right here
on the canvas, just let this brush
dance and play and have fun.
And all we're looking for is general basic
cloud shapes here, we're really not
trying to put anything in.
Just let it happen.
Just move the brush,
keep it moving, working,
playing, having fun, there we go.
Isn't that something?
There we are.
Put a nice little cloud shape
right there, what the heck.
Okay, keep the brush
moving, don't let it stop.
And sometimes brush is lazy, you have to
really push it a little
or it'll quit on you.
Make it keep moving.
Okay, now we'll take
the almighty brush here,
and we're gonna swirl this.
We're gonna pull the color, move it,
pull it, there we go.
Try to avoid a pattern, we
want this to go everywhere.
We're looking for a sky
here that has life in it,
has movement in it, we don't want a sky
that looks like at night
you pull the curtain down
and everything went black on you.
Wanna keep this moving, there.
Already you're beginning to see
all the little things happening up here.
Every which direction.
Every way, there we go.
Now you can blend this too
much and take it all out.
We don't wanna take it out,
we just wanna mix it up.
Stir it up.
Okay, while we've got some
paint on the brush here,
we'll add a little more
Prussian blue and phthalo green.
And we'll put us in some water.
We pull from the outside in.
And leave a little area opened here,
that will create the little sheen of light
that plays across the water.
You can go back with white
paint and put it back in,
but you've already covered
the canvas with Magic White,
so why not use it?
This is a lazy man's way of painting.
You let the paint work,
you let the brushes work.
Use what happens
naturally, don't fight it.
Okay, clean the old brush off,
and let's get out an
almighty fan brush here.
And let's build some happy
little clouds up here.
I'm gonna take titanium white
with the least little touch
of permanent red in it.
And load the brush full of
paint, just really load it up.
Now we'll start working on
some basic cloud shapes here,
and we'll dance in all these little areas
and let 'em just play in the sky.
Keep the brush moving, keep it moving.
You want areas that are
thick, areas that are thin.
Let all these little things happen.
And we'll take the big brush here
and gently, gently blend this together.
Very lightly.
And fluff it up a little and hypnotize it.
And right there you've
got an almighty cloud,
just that quick.
But they're very easily
killed, clouds are delicate.
Don't overwork it, put
it in, leave it alone.
Okay, and maybe we'll
have another one here.
We'll put a, layer these clouds some.
Okay.
Nature is so beautiful, just
let it go, have fun with it.
Very, very easy to work these to death.
Okay, we'll blend this in.
And you work in layers here, you do thing
that's the farthest away first,
have him finished, and then work forward.
There, we'll hypnotize that one,
blend this one a little bit.
Okay, little bit more red here.
There we go.
Don't wanna set these clouds on fire now.
All we wanna do is have a
slight warmish glow to 'em,
like the sun's playing along the top.
There we go.
Guess we better not forget
this side of the sky.
We'll put a little something over here.
Just some nice little clouds
playing around in the sky.
Okay, and mix these up a little bit.
(lively piano music)
Okay, maybe a little
streaky one right here.
Got baby clouds, too.
If you didn't have baby clouds,
you wouldn't have big clouds.
There, and we can work on
this one a little touch.
Okay, there looks like a nice place.
And we're really pushing
this paint into the canvas.
We're working that value
right into the canvas.
Just let it play.
Don't kill all the dark areas.
You can end up with great
big cotton balls in the sky
if you're not careful.
Guess that'd be considered a UFO,
big cotton ball in the sky.
There, fluff that up.
And work that paint.
And look at there, in
just a couple of minutes,
you have a sky that has so
much action happening in it.
There we go, okay.
(banging)
If you do this in your living room,
you can redecorate your living
room in a matter of minutes,
so be very careful, learn to control it.
Have you a box you can
shake your brush in,
and that way you don't have to worry about
covering everything.
Okay, let's take a little
bit of brown, some blue,
a little touch of alizarin
crimson and some white.
There we go, and don't
mix your paint dead.
Mix it marbley and leave it alone.
Okay, now let's do, since
we're gonna do McKinley today,
let's do the basic shape here.
McKinley comes down like
so, has another peak
running right off through here.
Make that just a little more rounded.
There, and we let this side
drop right down and over.
All you're looking for
here is the basic outline,
the basic shape of this mountain.
You're not worried at
all what happens in here.
Okay, take the big brush,
and we'll pull that down.
This takes off the excess paint
and makes the next layer stick better.
And also when you're doing mountains,
if you can see the entire
mountain, the top of the mountain
is always more distinct than the bottom.
At the bottom of the
mountain we have mist,
and now we have pollution.
We have a multitude of
things that break up
and diffuse light.
Okay, and we'll put some snow
on that almighty mountain.
Pull that paint out real
flat, just pull it out
and get us a little roll of paint.
And we'll just lay this on and
let it travel right on down.
And you want the paint to break like this,
to make all the little
things that happen in there,
the little shadows, the
light and dark areas.
Okay, and there's a little bump
that comes out right there
and works its way down.
And over here, let this drop just like so.
There we go.
Now for the shadow
color, we'll use a little
Prussian blue and white.
And once again, don't mix it dead.
You want it to be sort of marbley.
Okay, now we'll start with the shadows,
and we'll just lay these in here.
We wanna bring these
two areas here together.
So we just sorta work it back and forth
and let it come, there you go,
let it just come together.
And maybe this shadow comes
right down through here.
Every highlight needs
its own private shadow.
Okay, we'll put a little
shadow right there.
And see how that protrudes that up?
Makes it just jump right out at you.
The little ridges here and there.
All kind of little things
happening in this mountain.
And we need a shadow back here
behind this almighty peak.
There it is.
Just let him go.
Okay, and we want a peak that
comes right up through here
and just begins working its way back down.
(lively piano music)
There.
It's a nice ridge coming through here.
And we can bring these together.
(lively piano music)
A few little shadows in here.
Just here and there.
Okay.
And as we say, we want
this to be more distinct
at the top than the bottom, so we're gonna
diffuse the bottom of
it, and only the bottom.
And here we're just tapping the canvas.
We're trying not to destroy, only diffuse.
And this is where you really
depend on a firm paint.
If you have a loose, oily, thin paint,
you become a mud mixer here.
So when you try this at home,
if you find that you're
making a lot of mud,
check your paint, it
should be very, very firm.
Squeeze that tube, it
should stand up maybe about
three-quarters of an inch above the tube.
Then you have a nice firm paint.
Okay, I'm gonna make the same
color and make it darker.
Blue, brown, and alizarin added to it.
'Cause I want this
mountain to be in front.
This is a beautiful study
of how to make one mountain
look very, very big.
And we'll put some
little smaller mountains
here in the foreground.
(lively piano music)
Okay, another little peak here.
And we'll take the big
brush and pull that out.
Son of a gun, this comes right out.
That's the beauty of painting wet on wet.
You can move paint on the canvas.
And we'll put some happy little snow here.
Just let that run.
There we go.
Okay.
Our light is still coming
from the same direction here,
so don't let that fool you.
(lively piano music)
Okay, now we can work
in some shadows here.
Let's push that one into the background,
just come right on through,
and that'll push him back.
It's scary to have this much power
that you can move mountains.
Okay, this, there.
We can swing this around
and bring these two
right together.
Just make a nice little ridge out of that.
Okay, now we've got an almighty mountain.
I'm gonna take a little
of the blue, brown,
alizarin crimson, add a little
touch of sap green to it.
Looking for a dark color here, very dark.
I will load up this one-inch brush,
and we'll push in some
little dark areas here.
This'll be our little
trees that are way, way
back in the distance, bushes and trees
and all the little things
happening back here.
There we go.
Now with the big brush,
we can pull a little bit
of this color down.
And this'll be the beginning
of our reflections.
Okay, and we'll just give
it a little bit of ripple
to make it look watery.
(banging)
Okay, let's put some highlights on here.
I'm gonna use a little bit of Magic White
mixed with some cad yellow.
Little touch of permanent red.
And we'll just sorta go back and forth,
make a nice orangey
color here, bright color.
Mm.
There we go, all these nice little bushes
happening back here.
(lively piano music)
And then we'll reflect some of that
right down into the water here.
There we go.
Now with a big brush and
the most delicate, delicate
touch possible, just
enough to pull the paint
a little bit, we'll pull that down
and just give it a watery
effect, don't wanna destroy it.
Okay, now let's take...
mix up a lot of dark here,
blue, brown, alizarin,
and a little bit of sap green.
Should look black to you.
And we'll load the brush
full of paint, load it full.
A lot of paint.
And let's make some little evergreen trees
that are growing way back
here in the distance.
(lively piano music)
Okay.
Let's firm that one up a little bit.
It needs to be a little stronger.
There we go.
Maybe he's got a friend
that lives right over here.
Just dropped him in.
(lively piano music)
Okay, maybe they're
getting a little bigger
as it comes around the curve.
Maybe a little baby one back here.
Okay, we'll put a little
bush in front of him.
Okay, we'll take a little
touch of Magic White,
a little bit of brown,
and a little touch of yellow
just to make a nice sandy looking color.
And we'll lay in a little
water line back here.
There we go.
And we'll cut in a few little trunks
and sticks here and there.
(scraping)
Okay.
Maybe we need another tree right here.
Trees are getting closer,
so they're getting a little bigger.
They look bigger to you, this is the way
we push everything back.
Work with perspective here.
Okay, let's move to the
other side of the picture
while we've got a brush
full of paint here,
and we'll put an almighty tree right here.
These trees live in your brush.
You have to scare 'em out
sometimes, really work at 'em.
Little son of a guns
will try to avoid you.
And they're like everything else.
The first time you try 'em, they're gonna
drive you up the wall.
But you practice it.
If there's a secret to
this, it is practice.
You learn how to make the brush work,
how to touch the canvas with it.
And then it's just a matter of practicing.
First time you tied your
shoe, it wasn't easy.
You had to look at it and work at it.
The next thing you know, you're not paying
any attention, you just,
you get your shoe tied.
Same thing.
Okay, we'll just...
Maybe we'll make another little projection
come right out through here, there we go.
A little reflection in here.
And we'll pull that down.
(lively piano music)
Okay, we'll lay in some more of these
pretty colors back here.
There's a nice little bush right there.
Mm, there's one.
And right down here we'll
reflect some of these.
Okay, delicate touch
again, very, very light.
Just enough to move it a
little bit on the wet canvas.
And we'll put some land out here
so these bushes have a place to sit.
Don't want 'em fall off in the river here,
so we'll give 'em
something to set on here.
And we can take a clean brush
and just lift that gently.
This is a very thin paint
now, it's mostly Magic White.
So you can move that without destroying
what's underneath it.
And here we'll use a little bit of just
straight Magic White,
and we'll put us a happy
little water line in here.
There.
Okay.
Now then, you can, you can put some more
little bushes right in here like so.
And we'll drop some
reflections into the water.
And we'll pull those down.
And anybody can do this, this
is not some big secret thing.
Anybody can do it, we teach
people from the age of 10
all the way up 80 and 90 years old.
(banging)
And young people really, really like this.
They learn it very easily, very quickly,
and they see results very quickly.
I have a son that's a young man right now,
and he was, oh, he's been painting
since he was about 12 years
old, been selling his work.
So it's not just for the older person.
It will also work very
well for the young person.
The only trouble, like
my son, he's quite lazy.
He'll only paint if he needs money.
If he needs money, he'll paint.
But it is a nice way to put
a happy buck in your pocket.
And to make good things
happen in your heart.
Okay, we'll just have this come
right on down through here.
Fill that in.
Okay, now we can start
highlighting some of these things.
We'll take a little bit of
blue and yellow mixed together,
make a very nice little green color here.
And we'll just drop some
highlights on this tree.
Remember where your light's coming from.
Light's coming from the right,
so you want the right-hand
side of this tree
to be a little more distinct
and bright than the left side.
And if you're right handed,
you'll probably find
it's easier to have the
light coming from the right.
If you're left handed,
it will sort of vary
from person to person.
Okay.
Let's put some little highlights over here
on these little trees.
The sun wouldn't forget them.
There we go.
(lively piano music)
There we are now.
A little more Magic White,
thin that down just a touch.
And we can start finding all
these beautiful little trees
and bushes that are living in here.
Very important that you don't
kill all this dark area.
If you kill all the dark,
your picture's gonna be very flat.
Well, we might as well reflect that
right into the water there.
Okay, and there we go.
A little bit right in here.
And we'll reflect that right on down,
a little touch of red over the top.
Okay, there's another nice tree I see.
Little rascals live in your brush,
you just gotta push 'em out.
And let's put a touch
more of the Magic here.
There, nice ochre color.
All these pretty little bushes,
just let 'em flow off your brush.
And some little grassy areas
coming down through here.
Let's turn that into a nice reflection.
Just like so.
Okay, now let's give him
a little bit of dirt.
There we go.
This is straight van dyke brown.
And onto that, we'll take
a little brown and white
and give him just a
little touch of highlight,
make him look like little stones and rocks
playing through here.
Okay, let's put a few little
sticks here and there.
Here we're just cutting through the paint
using the point of the knife.
But it shows distance, it shows
all these different planes.
Okay.
And we'll put just a little
bit of Magic White under here
and give us a little water line.
(lively piano music)
There we go, and a few
little sticks over here.
Okay, but you see what you
can do in just a few minutes
with an almighty brush
and an almighty knife
and a beautiful painting in your heart.
All you have to do is let it out.
A few more sticks.
There we go, I think
we'll call that finished,
and I wanna thank you very,
very much for watching us.
I hope to see you again
in the near future.
Until then, happy painting, thank you.
(light guitar music)