(instrumental music)
- Hello, I'm Bob Ross
and I'd like to welcome you to
the 27th series of The Joy of Painting.
If this is your first time with us,
allow me to extend a
personal invitation for you
to drag out your paints
and some big, ol' unorthodox brushes
and I'll show you how to do
some fantastic little landscapes
that you can do.
So I'll tell you what,
today let's start out and
have 'em run all the colors
across the screen that you need
to paint this little painting with us,
and while they're doing
that let me show you
what I've gotten done up here.
Today, I've taken an
18 by 24, double prime,
pre-stretch canvas and I've
just covered the entire canvas
with black gesso.
And black gesso is just an acrylic paint
that makes the canvas black.
I've allowed that to dry completely.
On top of that, take a little
piece of contact paper here,
any sticky back paper
cut an oval, stuck it on there.
Then on the inside here,
after we have the contact paper on,
I've taken a little bit of liquid clear
and covered the entire inside.
Then we've taken alizarin crimson,
just plain ol' alizerin crimson
covered the entire canvas.
And on the corner over
here I've put a little bit
of phthalo blue, just so it's sort of a
lavender color over here.
I know it sounds complicated
but believe it or not
it is extremely simple.
Black gesso, liquid clear,
alizarin crimson, a little
phthalo blue in the corner
and just blend it out.
And with that let me show
you how much fun we can have.
Let's start today with a
least little bit of indian yellow.
I just want a very small amount.
Just a small amount.
And I'll go right up in here and get
a little bit of white on there.
So we have a little indian yellow
and a little bit of titanium white
on a little two inch brush.
Let's go right up in here.
Now, let's decide where
our light area will be,
and right in here let's
start making little X's,
little criss cross strokes,
something like that.
And we just begin letting that blend
outward and upward.
I want this to be the
lightest area in my sky.
So with that, all we have to
do is start making little X's.
Little more paint on the brush,
and we just continue to blend.
Isn't that fantastic?
I love these black canvasses
because you put the
transparent color on there,
they still look black,
but when you start painting
you add a little white, or
yellow or something in there,
and they come alive.
Notice that I'm always
taking the pure color
back to the lightest
area and working outward.
That way we assure that the lightest color
is right in there, and
that's where we want it.
Alright.
Look at all those beautiful colors,
they just... they happen automatically.
This is a very, very
easy style of painting.
Anybody can do this.
I get letters everyday from people
all over the country.
They say, "I never believed I could paint,
but I've tried what you
showed me on television
and it works for me.
It works."
Alright.
Now I want to make that
a little brighter yet.
So I'm going to take some
more of the titanium white
and a little bit of canyon yellow,
it's very bright yellow,
very strong yellow.
Just a little.
Now I'll go right up in here,
and just above there,
add a little bit of that.
There.
Just, still making little X's
with the criss-cross strokes.
Something about like
that, let it blend upward.
Once again, always start
in the lightest area
and work outward,
because you're gonna pick
up this transparent color
this on the canvas and automatically
it will get darker and
darker as you work away
from that center area.
Something about like so.
There.
We'll take the little blender brush
and come back and smooth
all that out in a second.
In the meantime I'm going
to grab another brush.
I have several of them
going so I don't have
to spend all my time just washing brushes.
Take a little white and let's get crazy,
shoot, let's get a little
bit of this bright red.
That's a gorgeous color
but it's very strong.
Be careful with it.
Just a tap a little into the bristles,
that's all we're doing, just tapping.
And maybe up here now we'll...
maybe... yep.
There's some, just some
happy little things
that happen up here in the sky.
Just little things like this,
and we'll dance a few
little colors in here.
In your world you put any color
or any shape that you want.
Painting is a very individual thing.
Everybody will see nature
through different eyes
and that's the beauty of it.
You can paint any world
that you want here.
Any world that you want.
Maybe there's a little
dooer comes out here,
I don't know,
doesn't really matter.
You decide.
Take a little blue, a little crimson,
just mix them on the brush here.
Make sort of a little lavender color
but to the reddish side.
Now the blue is many, many
times stronger than the crimson,
so proportionately you need
much, much more crimson
than you do blue.
Then I'm just gonna begin laying in some
little colors under in here
and wherever we want them.
Just have fun with this, let it happen.
Let it happen.
We don't do any drawings or tracings,
we really learn to create here.
We let our imagination take us
to worlds we never knew existed,
and in those worlds we find peace,
we find happiness.
Good things happen here.
Little blender brush,
it's a very soft brush.
Very soft.
Make a nice, nice makeup brush even.
But with that, because
the paint we use here
is very firm and very dry,
very thick paint,
we can take this little
blender and go right over it.
Just like that.
Isn't that something?
That easy.
There, we can just work on this a little,
and the more you blend this
the more it just goes right
into those background colors
and gorgeous things happen automatically.
Automatically.
Put a little white paint on there,
maybe we'll brighten that
a little, right in there.
I want that to stand out.
Something about like that.
Alright.
Okay.
Now that, it's time to
have some fun in here.
Let's get a little fan brush,
take a fan brush.
I'm gonna mix up,
we'll take some alizarin crimson,
a little bit of the phthalo blue,
maybe even put a little black in there.
Like that.
I'm gonna get a little titanium white.
I'm looking for sort of a... mmm...
that color.
That color right there.
Sort of a grey,
grey to the blue side.
Okay?
Let me wipe the knife off.
Let me just wipe the knife
of a little paper towel.
Take the fan brush,
and we'll load both sides full of color
just by going back and forth.
Alright.
Now then up in here, maybe
in our world back in here
lives some little evergreen trees.
and sometimes you can make
gorgeous little tree indications,
just taking a little fan
brush and pushing upward,
just push it upward.
We'll make all kinds of little trees.
I'm gonna add the least
little touch of white there
so it stands out a little better,
so for television it shows up.
There.
That shows up a little better.
But in your world you make them
any degree of darkness or
lightness that you want.
There we go.
Wherever, wherever.
And did you know, if you've
painted with me before,
we don't make mistakes.
We have happy accidents.
And all that means is
that very soon you learn
to work with anything that
happens on this piece of canvas.
Literally anything that happens.
Because sometimes things that
you think are big mistakes
and you're really worried about,
when the painting's
finished they end up being
the highlight of the entire painting.
There.
And each painting will
teach you something.
Learn from it.
As long as you learn from an experience
then it's not wasted.
It's not wasted.
It's only wasted when
you accept it as failure.
And we don't have any failure here.
We don't have any.
It's against the rules.
In Bob's world, that's against the rules.
Now then, I'll go back
to a two inch brush,
be sure it's clean and dry,
and I want to create the illusion of mist
down at the base of this.
So all we do, firmly, with
the top corner of the brush,
just tap.
Just tap it.
That's really and truly
all there is to it.
Then we're gonna lift slightly upward,
just enough to take out
the little tap marks
and sort of blend everything
together and make it very soft.
Now, it looks like a little
row of trees that lives
wee wee back here in
the distance somewhere.
Just happy little trees.
Now, I'm going to go into
crimson, blue, and black
same colors
but this time I'm gonna add much much less
of the white color to it.
Much less.
There, I want it to be quite a bit darker.
In a landscape painting, as you know,
as things get closer to you
they should get darker
and darker in value.
This is sort of a lavender color.
Load both sides of the ol' fan brush,
and let's put another row of trees.
Another thing that you find when
you're doing landscapes,
the more plains or the more
areas that you have in here,
the deeper that your painting will look.
That's what gives a
painting depth, distance.
That's what will make your
painting very, very special.
When people look at it they'll
say, "Oh I can look in there
and see forever."
There.
And that's what does it.
Maybe this comes,
yeah, why not?
Right up in here.
Something like that.
And we're just looking
for indications for trees.
These are too far away
to see a lot of detail.
We'll put a little detail
on them but not much.
Not much,
we get too much detail it
will ruin that illusion
of distance in your painting.
And that's a good friend.
We want that.
Alright,
now if you want to give
a few of these trees
the indication of a little
more detail, just do that.
Take the corner of the fan brush
and make it look like here and there,
and there and here,
there's a big strong tree
that lives up in here.
Maybe he got more sunlight or more water,
and he grew big.
Just wherever you think they should be.
Just drop them in.
Like that.
Shoot, I think we about have that.
Maybe a couple over on this side.
But that easy, we can make a
pretty nice little background.
Go back to our little two inch brush here
tap a little on the bottom,
just enough to create
that misty illusion again.
Very lightly.
Lift upward.
Something like that.
You know for many years I
was a traditional painter,
and one of the things, when
I was a traditional painter,
that was extremely difficult
was making reflections,
and in this technique it's
one of the easiest, nicest,
most effective things that happened.
Watch here.
Come right up in here.
All you have to do is
touch the canvas with
a little titanium white,
we have color on the canvas already
and pull it straight down.
It's important to come
straight down though.
Straight down.
It'll pick up all those
gorgeous transparent colors
that we had underneath there.
That easy.
And very gently, we go across.
Just like that.
See there?
And instantly it begins
looking like water.
Time to wash the ol' brush.
If you've painted with me before,
you know this is really the whole thing,
it's the most fun part
of the entire procedure.
Shake it off.
And just beat the devil out of it.
I thought maybe today we'd
have a little snow scene.
I'll show you a very
easy way of making snow.
Very easy way.
We'll just take titanium white
we use that same ol' two inch brush.
This is one of the simplest ways
of making very nice snow.
Tap it.
If you've painted with me before
this is the way we make
little grassy areas,
but I want to make snow
that looks powdery,
like, well skiers call it powder so
sometimes snow looks like that.
All you do is just tap.
Just tap.
Something like so.
Very gently.
There.
See?
That's all there is to it.
All there is to it.
All you're doing is
just tapping the canvas.
And we'll go back to this very, very soft
blender brush.
It's very soft.
Get a clean one
and gently
just graze it just enough
to bring it together.
And it'll give that
indication of very soft snow.
Watch here,
watch here, watch here.
I get excited.
I've probably painted a
million pictures, I think,
and I still get excited with this.
Maybe in our world
maybe this tree
watch here
you can grab trees and pull
them into the foreground.
This easy.
Just gonna take that tree
bring it right on down
and we'll bring it right here
so it pushes that little snowbank back.
It goes back behind it now.
It works so good in me we'll
have one over here, too.
I like that.
And this is your world so you can do
anything that you want here.
Any ol' thing that you want,
there it goes.
Have one there.
Let's give him a friend.
I like to make evergreen trees.
They work so well and
they're a lot of fun,
and they're gorgeous.
Absolutely gorgeous.
Now we can go back to our ol' brush here
that has the titanium white on it,
load a little bit.
And you work in layers.
See we did the thing that
was in the background first.
And now we'll begin working forward,
forward, forward.
Always starting with
the most distant object
and working forward.
There we go.
On the other side we'll do the same thing,
we'll bring it right underneath this tree.
Just right on out,
a little join together there.
There.
Alright.
But isn't that a super easy way
of doing a very effective illusion?
Just making snow?
Back to our little blender brush.
Very lightly.
Two hairs and some air.
Very lightly, just blend that.
Now we have that white on the brush,
let's go back and
reinforce this reflection.
I want to make it a little brighter
so it jumps out at you.
Just like that.
And go across.
Now then,
just take a little bit
of the liquid white.
Liquid white is just an oil based medium.
And we use it to thin paint,
we use it to cover the canvas,
and we use it to make water lines.
Just cut across, can you see that?
Just cut across with a knife.
And we go right up in here
and let's just cut in a little water line
that lives right there.
Right there.
That's all there is to it.
These water lines should be
basically straight though.
By that I mean going
back and forth across,
because if they're not straight your water
look like it's gonna run
right out of the painting.
You might have to tie a bucket on the side
to catch the overflow.
There.
Maybe down in here
there's a little ripple.
Whatever.
It's up to you.
Totally and completely.
There we are.
Like that.
Now then,
you ready to get crazy?
Let's do it.
Let's have some big fun.
Let's take a phthalo
blue and alizarin crimson
and no white,
it's just blue and crimson.
I'm making a very deep lavender
that should look black.
Tap the bristles of the brush firmly
into the paint.
Give it a little push.
And time to get crazy,
this is your bravery test.
Maybe we've got a big tree.
You know me, I like big trees.
Yep, there it is.
There it is.
It lives right up here.
And I'm using, just mainly
the corner of the brush
oops went right over that tree.
That's alright, we know he's back there.
Maybe, maybe, maybe in our world
maybe there's a big bush.
You're right, he lives right there.
Just sort of make these
things up in your mind
and let them go whever you want them.
Maybe there's...
maybe there's a whole
little group of bushes
that live here.
I don't know.
A little bunny rabbit has
to have a place to hide.
And that's a pretty good one right there.
We can take our liner brush,
use a little of the dark sienna,
and I'm thinning the paint because
one of our golden rules is
a thin paint will stick to a thick paint.
Thin will stick to thick.
Taken this dark sienna, a
little bit of white in it,
just enough to dilute it a little.
And here and there we're gonna just put in
an indication of a few
little tree trunks and sticks
and twigs that live back.
Not looking for a lot of detail.
Not yet.
We're gonna put some
detail in the foreground
but not yet.
And we'll probably cover most of those up
but a few of them's gonna show through
and it'll look like you worked
yourself to death up there
trying to get all those.
Let's go into a little
white and a little touch,
a little touch,
of phthalo blue with it.
Just enough to cool it.
Not much.
Titanium white, but push it,
push it.
You can see that little
ridge of paint right there.
There's one just like it on your brush
and that's what we end up painting with.
Push it, about a 45 degree angle.
Now very lightly, using just
the corner of the brush,
just begin tapping in all kinds
of little things in there.
Okay, maybe we need to load
a little more paint on the brush.
Now if you have trouble making a stick,
add the least little touch of liquid white
or paint thinner.
The liquid white will make your color
a little brighter,
the paint thinner will
leave it the same color.
They both work very well,
make up your mind what you want to do.
If you want it to be a little brighter
then add the liquid white.
If you want it to stay the same color
paint thinner.
But very little, no matter what.
Very little.
The secret to this painting technique
is to keep your oil paints
as firm and dry as possible.
That way you can continually
paint over the top of it
without them mixing together.
You don't want to become a mud mixer.
And if you've painted,
we've all mixed a little mud.
There we go.
See?
Now think about, think about
little individual bushes
and stuff that live in here.
I'm gonna dip the brush
into a little touch
of the liquid white myself.
Just to thin that down
so it sticks easier.
There we go.
Think about shape and form.
Don't just throw these in at random.
One at a time.
Do the one that you think is farthest away
and work forward, forward, forward.
Always working forward.
There we go.
One at a time.
I know you get tired of hearing that,
but it works for you.
And I want this, I want you
to enjoy success with this.
Cuz if you enjoy success
you'll get hooked on it.
I enjoyed some success with this
many years ago.
And it has become my entire life
and I love it.
Let's go into vandyke
brown and some dark sienna.
We'll just mix them together.
Vandyke brown, dark sienna
bravery test time.
Maybe in our world there lives
you ready for this?
There lives right here,
in one stroke,
let's put a nice tree trunk.
Alright let's give him a friend.
Yeah I know, I think everybody
should have a friend,
even a tree.
Even an ol' tree.
A little titanium white,
this is a birch tree, I've decided.
Touch, give it a little round-ward pull.
Let me exaggerate. (whistle)
That way.
Gotta make that little noise, too.
See there?
Just make it look,
no pressure.
Let the knife just barely, barely touch
so the paint breaks.
And by breaking I mean it leaves
all those little open holes in it.
There.
On the other side, a little
bit in the other direction.
Like so.
There.
Wherever you think they should be.
Something like so,
we can go back to the dark sienna
and vandyke brown mixture,
add a little bit right in the middle,
and when this dries
and it dries,
it will feel like real birch bark.
It'll project off the canvas.
The paint's think, there's a lot of it.
It really, really jumps
right off there.
Let's go back to our little liner brush.
Get a little of that vandyke
brown, paint thinner.
The thinner's there
only to thin the paint,
make it very thin.
Very thin.
And here and there let's
just put an indication
of a few little limbs and
little things that live out here.
This little tree needs some arms on him.
Shoot, he's got to reach
out and talk to this guy.
There we go.
Just a few.
That works so well, I think it's time
to really get crazy.
Let me put a little bush down here.
I want to cover up his foots.
Down here at the base of this,
just wanna cover his foots up.
Right now they're sort
of just hanging there.
But we'll make them come
right out of that little bush.
Right there, right there.
I'm going back into my brown.
Big bravery test.
Right there.
Maybe this is a different
kind of tree here,
just to break it up a little bit.
Let's take some white,
a little dark sienna,
mix it together.
Put a little vandyke in there, too,
what the heck.
Take a little bit of paint and
all we're gonna do is just begin touching,
just touch,
something like so.
There we are.
Just touch it.
Touch it.
That's all. Touch.
And as you work around
we're gonna let it get darker and darker
and darker and darker.
As it goes around the tree.
Put a little brown with your color,
a little of that vandyke brown,
see it gets darker automatically.
Once again when this is dry it will
actually feel like bark on a tree.
Alright, wipe the knife off.
Back to the paint thinner.
Little bit of vandyke
brown with paint thinner.
Just to thin it.
And let's put an arm on this tree.
Maybe it lives in our
world right out in here.
Boy, this would be a gorgeous
place for a tree to live.
Gorgeous place for a tree to live.
Maybe there's another arm right here.
It's up to you.
You decide how many arms are on your tree.
Or how few.
Maybe your tree died
last year, or sometime,
and it's just about
just about over.
Make up little stories
when you're painting,
little stories just in your mind.
And then you actually project yourself
into that scene.
And when you do, this
becomes a reality sorta.
And you know, painters are expected to be
a little strange so,
that's alright if you stand
around and talk to yourself
about this scene and the
ol' guy that lived out here
or whatever,
that's alright if people
look at you a little strange.
Painters are supposed to be that way.
Maybe out in here there's just
a little ol' stick that lives.
Use a little of the light color here.
Wherever you think that should be.
It's up to you.
Up to you.
I'll tell you what, maybe
there's an ol' limb.
Right there.
Something like that.
He's a tired old limb.
Now you can take the knife
get that brush clean,
and you can scrape through this and
allow the black canvas to show through.
And it'll look like
little sticks and twigs
that live back in here.
I hope you can see those.
When you do your own
painting you'll see them,
they'll be there.
Something about like so.
Alright, that's all there is to it.
I think we're about ready to
take the contact paper off here
and see what we have.
This is the moment of truth.
So we just grab the paper
pull it right off.
And all of a sudden you have a painting
that's right there in that oval.
And it comes out so gorgeous,
and it just,
these painting's excite people.
I know none of us are
interested in those happy bucks
but if you're out selling paintings,
these are different.
You'll be surprised at
how people will come along
and they'll marvel at how you did this.
It's very very nice.
I think it's time to
sign this ol' painting.
And with that, we'll take a
little bit of the bright red.
Signatures are as unique as painters.
Each person will develop
their own signature.
So find your own signature.
I've had people that sign with initials,
with their whole name,
I've even known people who've signed
with a little symbol.
It's up to you.
But pick a signature and stick with it,
because it becomes your trademark.
And people a hundred
years from now will look
at your painting and recognize
exactly that it was you.
Alright, let's go right in
here and just sign this one.
I have a very short
name, so it's quite easy.
We'll sign it, call it done.
There.
And I hope you enjoyed this one.
It's a very easy painting,
I'd love to see some photos of your work.
From all of us here, I'd like
to wish you happy painting
and God bless, my friend.
(instrumental music)