hi glad to see you again today you ready
to a fantastic seascape I thought that's
what we'd do today so let's start out
and have run all the colors across the
screen that you need to do this seascape
with me and that's going up here let me
talk just a little bit while they're
doing that I started with a good old
standard 18 by 24 inch canvas but I've
done something a little bit different
today the top part of the canvas is
totally covered with a thin even coat of
liquid white all the way up here down
you can see this little line here now
from here down is covered with liquid
clear now this is just like liquid white
only it's clear that's all so let's go
and do a fantastic little seascape I'm
gonna start out with a 2 inch brush and
a small small amount of the CAD yellow
very small amount just beat it into the
bristles a little bit can't go up here
now then maybe we'll have a beautiful
bright little sky today so I'm just
gonna start with a little yellow do
something like so just let that mix with
the liquid white there now without
cleaning the brush go right in to a
touch of yellow ocher load the brush the
same way go back up here now right
around the edges of that see there still
use the little crisscross strokes we'll
just bring that right around sort of
like so there we go
and if a little happens to get down here
in your painting don't worry about it
don't worry about it it's no problem at
all
okay still without cleaning the brush
will go right into bright red a little
bit some very strong okay now that right
around those edges take a little bit of
this beautiful red color just like so
not pretty already we have a we have a
painting for the Museum of Modern Art
here you can just stop right there now
that I want to put a little bit of red
over here and just let it work right
along right in here is gonna be the
horizon there we go
and we just very lightly blend all this
together okay now then I have several
brushes go in son I'd spend all my time
washing I'm gonna take straight titanium
white just straight white and go right
up in this area and I want this to be
very bright too so I'm gonna take white
and put it right there straight titanium
point now it won't show up much because
light against light is nothing but you
just wait I'm gonna grab it and pull it
just pull grab it and pull we don't care
what happens in here we're gonna cover
all that effort we now then let me wash
it a brush
and we just wash our brushes with
odorless paint thinner shake them off
and beat the devil out of them
okay we can just use this same old brush
I'm gonna go into a small amount of
phthalo blue and reach up here and grab
a little touch of alizarin crimson so we
have phthalo blue and alizarin crimson
proportionately much more crimson than
blue I want this to be a little bit to
the reddish side okay there's very
little paint on the brush let's go back
up here now then let's take and use just
the corner of the brush using little
circular little circular strokes and
let's just begin laying in some happy
little clouds maybe there's one that
lives oh look at there look at her there
he is
hanging out there look at that see how
easy it is to make all kinds of
beautiful little cloud shapes all you
need is just the corner of the brush
there we go
okay man then over here we'll put him
had a little clout Liz right there there
we go and in your world you decide where
the clouds live and you put as many or
as few as you want
cheery decision there we go
just wherever maybe there's one right
there still using those tiny little
strokes little circular strokes just
with a corner of the brush okay let's
say I have I have several brushes going
here now with a clean brush I'm just
gonna very gently blend this a little
don't have to over blend it just enough
to sort of mix it up like so there we go
still using little round strokes little
circular strokes you can blend this till
it absolutely goes away all we want to
do is blend it just enough to soften the
edges so it comes already a minute watch
here then we'll take this and very
gently three hairs and some air very
gently just bring it all together you
don't want to lose your shapes
I just want to soften all the edges and
then you can even do like Katniss the
head just brings it right over makes it
look like little light streaks coming
through there now then to really add a
little more contrast I'm gonna mix a
little more color the same color crimson
and phthalo blue there's room crimson
they go blue but a little darker a
little more on the brush and right in
here I want to show a cloud that's a
little closer so for that we'll just use
a little darker color and it'll give the
impression this cloud is closer to us
see how easy that is you can create all
kinds of beautiful little things
happening in here all right
they would go back to our clean brush
stir this up a little bit
just mix it don't over to Don over to
it's easy to get carried away and then
very lightly two hairs of some area this
time it gives the impression now that
that cloud is in front a little bit
so it helps creep the illusion of depth
and distance in your sky and you can put
a couple hair in there wherever but that
easy you can make a fantastic fantastic
sky looks like a nice sunset already and
if you if you want to you can go in here
with a fan brush and you can add some
little streakers little streaky clouds
that easy
and you can put as many of these in as
you want just want to show you how clean
dry brush and then blend them right into
the paintings there we go in that a
beautiful sky and you can do it wash it
and brush I have some paper towels over
here I just dried a fan brush that's the
fun part of this whole technique already
now then we have to make a big decision
here let's take that's take let's take
just take earth phthalo blue alizarin
crimson and I'm gonna make a dark dark
lavender color on the palette it should
look black all right we got her mixed
here now then probably let me show you
one other thing first one of the easiest
ways to help you with a seascape
because it's sort of hard at first till
you practice a little I'm gonna take the
little filbert brush here and to that
I've added a bunch of paint thinner so
this is thinners water nearly sort of
sort of come in here and sketch out
where you want the major wave to be and
let's just say it's gonna live boom
right there and this is not a commitment
at this time you can still change it
soon comes up like it maybe it comes
over maybe the foams gonna crash up in
here somewhere like that
now our shoreline maybe it'll come oh I
get something like it that just helps
give you a little bit of sort of a
layout and it'll really save you a lot
of trouble
okay after you practiced a while maybe
you don't need to do this but at first I
really recommend you do it that way too
it'll help you lay it out here I'm using
that dark color we made it's a very dark
lavender color see if we've we had used
liquid white here when we put this on it
would pick up the white and you would
lose this beautiful beautiful dark color
there liquid clear allows us to mix on
the canvas without changing the value of
the color we'll just come right on down
in here in here we're gonna have the
transparency or the or the bright spot
of the wave that's the part of the wave
if you into selling paintings that's the
part of the wave it sells that's what
everybody wants to see that big big
crasher will come right in here hmm just
sort of follow this guide all we're
doing here is putting in some dark color
so our light will show later on I may
add a little more color a little more
color that's repentance
phthalo blue now when you're doing these
at home you can add all kinds of colors
other times Balogh green is very pretty
and seascapes oh it is dynamite color
beautiful it's very strong and be
careful with it see all of these we have
all of our dark areas blocked in when
you're using a big ol two-inch brush you
didn't take but a second met a beautiful
rich color alright now we can really
start playing let me grab my fan brush
I'm gonna take same old colors alizarin
crimson and phthalo blue and let's head
let's put some on the fan brush here
just load it back and forth like it not
a great deal of paint on the brush okay
let's go up here maybe there's a little
footling back here that's a fancy name
for a rock sticks out in the water mm
little Peninsula we back in the distance
and this is too far away to show details
so don't worry about it all we're
looking for here it's just a basic shape
okay tell you what - that was so much
fun this - another one maybe there's
another bigger stone in front of it here
bigger foot but this will help create
the illusion of distance in your
painting and you can put all kind of
things back here you can put little
trees on these foot limbs and just
whatever but it really helps so you
chose different planes in your painting
hope you can see that
now if it if it doesn't show up quite
low enough you can take and they had a
little little highlight to it they just
you get it to stand out a little more
maybe that'll help can see that a little
bitter now there we go good okay and
that click we've got a happy little
putting back here alright now we can
begin putting in some of the good stuff
how to start with just plain ol titanium
white
and we'll go right up here and just
begin putting in some happy little
highlights we back hearing a distance
barely barely touching barely touching
and sort of like you make all these
little things happen bring it right
around the base of this little little
foot line back here now then let's have
some fun let's go like right in here
watch here grab it and discover all
right I've liked it Oh what have we done
now and maybe there's another one right
here and back and let's go right along
here like that
right along there it's got easy that is
cleaning off the old brush here okay now
then I'm going to taken another fan
brush it's clean and very gently very
gently yeah I'm just gonna begin doing
it like so
see just work that back pay very very
close attention to angles all you want
to leave in here is the dark area this
is a time when the dark areas are much
more important than the light areas that
right in here same thing same thing see
just blend that up like you
hmm that's began they looked pretty
already okay yeah we can go right into a
little bit of white sea and begin making
all these little things that are far far
away little swells that are far in the
distance don't want too much detail back
there okay good
this is this painting it'll teach you to
be an expert brush washer let's go back
into our blue and crimson blue and
crimson just mix it right on the palette
all right now this area here we have to
put dark in before we can put our light
in so that's just add a little bit of
dark color right here see how easy that
is
follow that basic angle so look at that
oh we're doing is just applying dark
we'll come back later put all the
highlights on the good parts everybody
wants to jump on these good parts but
you have to do this you have to do the
framework first okay now that we got
some dark from there let's take some
white I'll just use some titanium white
a lot of paint on the brush now a lot of
paint I'm okay
madam grab this and pull it pull it
strokes are very important you might
need to wash you or wipe your brush
sometimes you can just wipe it in
between each stroke because you're gonna
pick up some of this under color see
here my cat
okay
yeah then that's let's get our little
filbert brush here I'm gonna go into
white and the least least little touch
of cadmium yellow white and yellow white
yellow okay let's go up here now then
let's go right in here this this is the
part that makes the painting so pretty
this is it all we're doing here it is
scrubbing in some color and the light
would come right along the top of this
wave because the waters thinner here
look at that just like so maybe there's
a touch even right over in here just a
little bit right in there with a clean
dry be sure it's dry it's most important
clean dry 2 inch brush come right in
here very very gently just begin
blending this
we're gonna begin picking up some of
this nice rich lavender color we have
down here and blending it right up into
it this is where we begin forming the
basic angle of the way now
I beat the brush just to remove excess
paint is it doesn't matter if a little
that color goes up in there that light
the light area will remain let's grab it
before okay let me find my little
filbert brush here we'll use some of
this lavender color that we have same
old lavender color how to touch it white
end there we go now let's begin putting
some foam and first we put the shadows
in and you take this brush and just lay
it over and just really scrub it in get
tough with it
get mean with it think about water
churning and bubbling and maybe it comes
away up here and crashes and splashes
and all kinds of fantastic little things
are happening and this is only the
shadow only the shadow will come back
and put the highlights on you in the
second
fill this in this needs to be good and
dark also like the aunt and with our
clean brush we want to continue this
angle just grab it and bring it through
okay now be sure you're filled with
brushes good and clean and dry now comes
the fun part
this is what we wait on take white CAD
yellow load a lot of paint into the
bristles just really fill the
son-of-a-gun up okay now then sort of
hold a brush here and give it a little
upward push and it's that upward push
that's where the splash happens and when
you begin running out of paint turn it
over and use the other side to brush and
usually you just wipe off the excess you
don't have to go through the whole
cleaning procedure you want to keep this
color as pure as you can I'm just gonna
mix with what's on there okay plenty of
paint on the brush plenty of paint
splashing we appear all kinds of
beautiful little things are happening
continually wipe that brush keep it good
and clean
and we'll have a little bit mm well you
get carried away with these you can
really get carried away in the hewa
super tire seascapes are fun okay
coming off the brush okay now with a
good clean dry brush you just want to
sort of mix this together that'll make
it sort of make a different value a
medium value here cuz it'll mix with the
dark and the light brings it all
together just stir it up a little bit
okay
good clean dry two inch brush just the
corner and just mix this up all you have
to do it's just very gently bring all
this together very gently this is two
hairs and some air barely barely
touching and that easy we have it yeah
I'm gonna take a paint thinner yellow
and white and be sure your paint is as
thin as ink so a very thin water
consistency let's go right up here this
nice bright area here there's gonna be
all kinds of light shining through just
put all these happy little things paint
at home when you have unlimited time you
can just really go in here but all kinds
of beautiful beautiful little things
okay
come ride along here and just Sparkle
that like so mm-hmm all right yeah let's
take some white a little touch of the a
little blue very little blue white and
blue and let's begin working on some
happy little things that are just
floating right on down through here all
kinds of little this is where you begin
forming the wave this gives it shape and
gives it character okay
back in here
just bring it right on back let's have
some fun right into that light area I'm
gonna go right into some CAD yellow
we'll just throw that right on there
right into the yellow ocher just like we
did this guy let's drop it in right into
some bright red we got us a fireball
going here then I'm gonna reach into
dark sienna a little bit more dark
sienna here then right into Van Dyck
Brown over here I want to get quite dark
so it makes that light really stand out
okay now then let me touch you white
right there and then with a clean brush
all you have to do is blend all this
together just blends together Specter
color sort of mix and then lightly
lightly quickly let's go across like let
go across then we'll take a fan brush I
want to put titanium white or the least
least little touch of a little blue on
it and it must come right in here and
begin making all kinds of happy little
foam things just laying out here having
a good time leave some of these dark
areas leaves and dark areas
don't kill them all
begin paying attention to the shape of
the wave it's very important very
important over here
yeah well I got to brush going I'll just
take it right into some brown and that's
half maybe just some sand right here
all right there it is look at there just
put this is just brown with a little
touch of white that was left on all
right down like yeah a little bit of
sand on the beach Van Dyck Brown dark
Sienna a little touch of white little
seagulls we got to have a place to run
okay yeah take a little paint there with
some dark paint we just run a little
lion and into here like so
paint thinner with some of the light
blue and we can just put the indication
of a little a little bit of water
playing all down here on the beach but
all kinds of little lines and stuff here
and there see how easy that is
it really makes some nice nice effects
and let's have a happy little stone
lives right there this is just Van Dyke
Brown
shoot I tell you I will have that a
little stone right there go a little bit
down grab it makes a reflection take the
little knife and we'll put the least
little touch of some highlights on here
like so the old clock on the wall is
telling me got to stop for today so with
that I think what called this painting
finished I sincerely hope you've enjoyed
it
that'll give you a good idea of how to
do a fantastic seascape happy painting
god bless
you