right glad you could join me today today
I thought we'd do a nice beautiful
little winter scene it's sort of warm
and has a beautiful little glue and I
think it will make you happy so let's
have them start off and run all the
colors across the screen that you need
to do this painting and they'll come
across in the same order as I have a
moment palette now I've already covered
the canvas with it then even co2 the
liquid white it's wet and slick it's all
ready to go let's have some fun start
today with a little one-inch brush going
to a little bit of cad yellow the
tiniest tiniest little amount of the
bright red tiny little milk can't say
that enough just work a little bit into
the bristles go ahead up here i'm gonna
have a son in this painting so you'll
have the sun right about there and we
start off just making a little circle so
you got to do like so okay now i'm going
to wash the brush now we wash our
brushes and odourless thinner just beat
the devil out of it okay now then I'm
gonna go into titanium white and will
come right down here and get a little
touch of alizarin crimson just like so
okay ask her right up in here and we'll
work this in using a little little
crisscross strokes a little excess if
you use these little crisscross strokes
rather than draw on a big circle it's
much much easier to blend all of these
colors together I'd really recommend to
use these little strokes
like so maybe I'll add the least little
touch of crimson here and make it a
little bit brighter so you can see it
better on you said anytime some of these
colors are so soft it's hard to see
we'll bring it right on out like it
normally when we're doing these
paintings for television be painting a
little brighter then we would at home so
when you're painting at home you paint
in any way that makes you happy bring it
right on down like that okay
I'm gonna go to a two inch brush it's a
little bit faster now go right into the
crimson tiniest little bit tiny little
bit and now I'm going to add just a
small amount of the dark Sienna
to the crimson make a very warm Brown
case go back up here yeah very lightly
right around here still making the
little crisscross strokes very soft
quiet gentle little sky but very
effective very effective this is a tight
painting that people put in their living
rooms just make it look warm they're
good sellers if you're interested in
selling things so many people write and
tell me that they're selling paintings
at the ending they believe they could
paint what that really makes me happy
when people write and tell me that and
it's not the money the money is not
important it's what it does to your ego
and inside here because if somebody's
willing to pay you for something you
paint it with your hand then I'll makes
you want to go home and paint ten more
paintings that's what's important it's
not the money going right into Van Dyke
Brown sometimes I talk too much I have
to hush get excited
Van Dyck Brown still making a little
crisscross now this is mixing with the
liquid white and all of these beautiful
little things just happen a little bit
more of the brown and right there looks
just like an egg I cook this morning bad
news
I'm not much of a cook I'll take just
lay a little tiny bit of this brownish
color down in here and without him
cleaning the brush the least little
touch of a little blue tiny tiny little
amount okay it will just lay out a
little bit of that just hear it just
hearing there and you can add other
alizarin crimson I'm just putting some
colors down here don't worry about
blending them together or mixing them at
this point
alright let's lay that brush down and I
have several these two inch brushes
going and I'm going to go right up here
and again blending still use the little
crisscross strokes and you really want
to blend this out just blend it blend it
blend it working outward and you don't
want to bring the dark color in toward
the center blend it out right there
and you want to blend this till you
can't tell where one color stops and the
next one starts very soft very gentle
then very lightly just take out the
brushstrokes if you happen to get a hair
on the canvas like I did there just take
the corner of the brush and pop it off
it's obvious to you now there now let's
have some fun we'll put a Sun up in here
and for that I'm gonna use my finger
let's go right here take a little white
and I'm just gonna rub it right in just
make a little circle Sun looks a little
better if it's round M square Sun sort
of bother you there you go see you just
push that right in there make a little
circle now if you tried blending that it
would smear so take your knife come
right up here and watch take your knife
and just go hoop take it right off the
value or the color remains in the canvas
now you can come along here let's see
you can blend that and that easy and
easy you have a happy little side
alright and that completes our sky now
we can have some fun and begin painting
now you have to make a decision here
okay I'm going to use the round brush go
into Van Dyck Brown little dark sienna
I'm just going to mix them on the brush
just tap it see just happen there we go
let's go ahead up here
maybe there's a happy little tree that
lives right here then we'll start at the
base of this tree and work upwards so
automatically automatically it's going
to mix with a liquid white and it's
going to be darker at the bottom and it
is on the top and you have your shadows
without even trying darker darker darker
down toward the bottom
maybe there's a happy little tree or
bush it lives there begin thinking about
the lay of the land or the way the
ground flows I'm going to have a little
hill here so that's what I'm again
working on we're not worried a great
deal about detail at this point but
already interested in is a general lay
of the land oh there's another one so
you just put these little things just
sort of fall out of your brush they live
in there sometimes you have to tap them
out a little bit but they live in there
we go and we'll pull a little bit of
that color down just the bottom because
that'll end up being our shadows in the
snow so you use all these things where
you get so dark color on the brush you
can use it now then I'm going to take a
little bit of a liquid black out here on
my pallet take my liner brush add a
little paint thinner and then work out
brush in there and turn it turn it
bring it to a super sharp point look at
that very sharp all right now that in
here in here but just the indication of
a few little trunks little stems
whatever you want to call them Leones
arms whatever okay now one of the
questions I get asked a great deal is do
you pull it down or you go up it doesn't
matter try it both ways and most people
will find it works better one way than
it does the other now normally I pull
down because it's easier for you to see
it that way when I'm painting at home a
lot of times I'll pull up I don't think
there's any rule you just sort of
practice and find which way works for
you there we try to show you as many
ways as possible and turn you loose on
the world
okay now then we'll take the round brush
and dip it right into a little touch of
the liquid white just a little touch I'm
going to add the least least little
touch of bright red here to tie her
knees a little bit tap that brush tap it
tap it tap it can't go up here now then
let's put some beautiful little
highlights up here on these trees just
use just the top corner of the brush and
we can tap in here see there but think
about shapes in here don't just throw
this on it random leave some of those
nice dark areas in here see the patterns
that's what gives you tree shape and
form now if you have trouble making it
stick add a little bit more the liquid
white to it I'll put a little more red
in there want to stand out a little here
we go there we go beautiful you can see
that much better thing okay just go
right along here and make some decisions
how many trees how many bushes oops
there's whatever writer C layer that
creates depth this is where the little
bunny rabbit hides is behind that bush
and then up here all winter long the
little tree urchin stays I bet you
wonder what a tree your chin is that's
what I call a little squirrel I have a
big walnut tree in my yard and the
little squirrels come and they eat
walnuts and we have little little power
struggles over who's going to get to all
nuts be at a squirrel guess who wins
squirrels got a nest full of nuts and I
have none right up here
there I've got one in Little Rascals it
decided he liked my garage better to eat
it out during a cold he moved into my
garage can you get that little devil out
so I put some mothballs in his nest dad
stinks
there now once again while I have this
on my brush I'm going to begin pulling
in some basic shapes and I'm not worried
at this point about much of anything
except the lay of the lamp
just pull it in just like so all right
now then we can take the old fan brush
the old fan brush with a little quiet on
it and we can begin working on some nice
shapes and stuff here this is where
again laying in the snow and you can go
into a tiny little bit of the pale blue
and add shadows it doesn't matter fact
it's desirable if you pick up a little
bit of this brown and begin working it
in here here we go always always paying
attention to the lay of the land and
thank where the light would hit snow is
very really really smooth it has little
bumps colors rocks and stones and all
kinds of little happy things that are
underneath the snow you may not see them
but they they cause bumps into snow okay
maybe tell you why let's go right here
and push in there there's a happy little
little grassy area just runs right down
the hill see there just make all kinds
of little things happen here all right I
like to do these little winter scenes
are a lot of fun I've fun and it easy
let's make you happy okay tell you what
tell you what maybe years ago a old
trapper
maybe he built him a little little house
right there so it takes them some of the
Van Dyck Brown cut across and get a
little roll of paint on the knife
there you see right out of the edge is
most importance right out on the edge of
the knife let's go up here okay maybe
the little house lives does now right
there there it is see paint that little
back you first I tell you what to put a
frightening little food fried on the
other side
see just sort of in your mind think
think what a house looks like and he
needs a little side over here too
all right man take a little quiet a
little brown
I was hot very flat get us a little roll
of paint and that's let's put a nice
little touch of highlight on there
barely touching very touching just
caress the canvas okay now see we can
see that the lights coming from here so
this sites going to be a brighter this
one over here this one's going to be
almost dark almost pure brown don't
worry about too much color over that say
for that guy Liz and there is freezing
because there is no roof of his house
let's give him a roof
let's give him a roof there we go just
that easy man he's got a half a roof
let's feel sorry for him getting about a
half don't want him to freeze okay
little snow on the other side just sort
of bring all that together
and that easy she got a cabin needed or
don't get locked in there and keen get
out all Wed her there you got a little
door take a little white go around edges
they're making rascal stand down we'll
take the small knife now we'll put a
little window right there just a little
blue and white just give the indication
of a happy little window like that okay
whoa chimney we use a small edge of the
small knife or you put a little chimney
take a little tiny little touch of the
bright red skews mahram there maybe he
don't have his fireplace let a little
snow laying up here on his chimney there
we go that easy until you one take a
little bit of liquid black maybe there's
what remains of an old fence and it went
right off here this is just straight
liquid black there it goes and there's a
fuel rails left on it right off into the
distance and then need to do to dirt
with
wash the brush now take a little bit of
the liquid white help look at their
little snow laying up here on his fins
and a little up here on top there think
and you just make all kinds of little
things we take the fan brush and grab
just a touch of that flame to death all
right now we can fix up the foot of this
cabin take and work on your perspective
look at there you can just cut it right
off wherever you want it ever you wanna
take a little white little touch it blew
into it I come right on here and there's
a big ol bunch of snow laying right
along there maybe even create the
illusion he's been walking right here
this using the little tiny tiny bit of a
little blue white and we go back to her
paint her colors it's got a little pink
in there begin building all this in
still paint very close attention to the
lay of the land its most most important
that you always keep in mind the way you
want this I am the flow if you don't
they will get away from you run right
out of your pay T pretty soon you had
land going in every which direction so
pay attention to that that's it's
important so little details that make
you make your paintings better make you
happier when you get done with your
painting
it's nice to step back and look at it
and feel good about it you want to feel
good about it
despite their back you see they get a
little larger down here cause
perspective wise
let's get them closer to you all right
all right leave out one side done here
fine okay let's get serious
let's get serious final round brush here
let's put something over here on the
other side have some fun back into my
dark sienna and like round tap petal
brush in there so you really beat that
son of a gun this is where you take out
all your frustrations is it better than
kicking your dog of course fees like
mine you're kicking he'll take your leg
off there we go right
work it up see once again we're starting
from the bottom I've been working up for
10 so it's darker to bottom and it is on
top maybe that ends right up into there
mmm I like these very salt earth tones
Browns and stuff you're so striking so
effective there we go
maybe two but right there very tan tell
you what I must do we get just so brush
go into so much fun let's go right over
on this side
and maybe right here I'm just gonna push
upward see just push look at all the
thousands of little leaves and stuff it
makes their and that easy it looks like
a dead bush there's one right there -
we'll have a couple of these little
rascals
just drop them in wherever you want them
and you take a the old fan brush you go
right back in here and we can working
some of these out create all kinds of
pretty things so you can make make the
lay of the land go anywhere you want to
go wherever see Mike all kind of little
snowdrifts up there sometimes it's just
so pretty it hurts okay
and let's let's change let's change the
flow of the lay on here the lay that I
watch right here see take it this way
and bring it up in here automatically
grab some of that Brown pull it down in
there automatically you can change the
lay of the land so that you can see
there's a separate entity here it goes
back father pushes everything back okay
yeah then let's take I'll use the old
knife here let's just put a quick little
indication here of a little tree trunk
it Doupe Doupe Doupe it's like that few
little Leone's here in there little
brown and white a little highlight just
a tiny touch of highlight you take just
a pointed knife look at there straight
through and make all kinds of little
doers in there little valves and stones
and twigs it's that easy okay
yeah then let's find that's right there
it is the round brush let's have some
fun let's get crazy here and we'll take
a little the bright red little yellow
ocher little Indian yellow but very
small amount don't don't get too wild on
this very small amount okay let's go
right up here maybe this tree here got a
little bit of color on it still fall
just drop in some happy little things
once again worry about patterns shapes
think about Leila's in there and I'm
just using the very top corner of the
brush just a very very top corner look
at that top see all the little things
and this creates a little warmth in the
painting um sometimes I paint winter
scenes that are so cold
who gosh you almost have to put on a
coat to look at them these are very warm
and very soft and they go well in
people's homes people like these kind of
paintings these are the type paintings I
do for special friends and as gifts for
Christmas and birthdays and weddings and
all kinds of things like that brings up
another thing a lot of people ask us
what we do with all these paintings that
we do on TV most of them are used to go
into the books that we do but all the
rest of them we donate we donate them to
PBS stations all around the country into
charity organizations for them to make a
happy buck with so if you would like to
have one one of the easiest ways to get
it is to call your PBS station and say
hey you know get one of Bob's paintings
for your next auction and we'll be glad
to donate one to them and it helps
everybody out you get better programming
that way in the PBS station
he puts a happy book in his pocket and
you get a you get a painting so keep
that in mind if you want one that's let
your station know just drop in a few
little blue and white grassy areas here
Oh
kinds of little things going on in here
all kinds of oh thanks
man I tell you what let's use a knife
maybe that's what remains there he's an
old fence right here there's a post put
one there
tell you what three three looks better
ins a little bit of brown and white for
some highlight doop doop there we go
maybe there's still one old one old post
is hanging across there just like that
that easy okay let's have some fun let
me get an old fan brush here go right
into the Van Dyck Brown little dark
sienna
I think yep look at there Shh big old
tree big ol tree I put a big tree up
painting one time the lady screamed at
me
absolutely screamed at me so if you
don't want a big tree in your painting
don't put one in there and then scream
at me this is your world so you do
whatever you want your painting okay
then I'll take the liner brush little
bit of liquid black and we'll just put
the indication of a few limbs here in
there now sometimes I add a little paint
thinner to the liquid black to make it
really flow easy just let it go just let
it really work right off your brush come
right on around there look at there see
and have some of these limbs that go up
and across the tree you don't have them
all just going out to side seeing you
can put all kinds of little tiny things
in there just by stroking the canvas you
see then mmm just get sort of crazy and
let them go
there man will take the knife and a
little bit of white brown let's put a
little touch of highlight on this tree
there
it's barely touch give it a little pull
it's like the paint grab this is a thick
thick paint so it'll grab hang on there
maybe this one comes right down in front
I can't see there you can just make all
the trees you want in your world okay
yeah
take the old fan brush and put a little
slow down here on his foots dad take
care of his old foots Bigfoot's take the
liner brush put a little liquid white
and just lay on a little highlight here
and there create the illusion of a
little snow and I think with that we
bound have a finished painting so let's
take a little bit of a bright red liner
brush and we'll sign this one the old
clock on the wall tells me I got to
leave you for today but I'll be back
next time hope you have your easel set
up class of T you all ready until then
happy painting
god bless
you