welcome back glad you could join me
today you know they say that time really
goes by when you're having fun and here
we find ourselves on our last show of
this series so I thought today you know
since I lived in Alaska so long I'd do a
special Alaskan painting so if you come
on up here to canvas I'll tell you what
we've already done now I've taken a
black canvas as you can see now we
painted this with just a flat black
acrylic paint allow that to dry and then
on top of that I've put all different
kinds of transparent colors I've put
some right and here's some alizarin
crimson over in here some phthalo green
they little blue and green mixed all
over the canvas so it's completely
covered with a thick paint so it's all
ready to go so let's have them
graphically run all the colors across
the screen that you need to paint this
project with me and I think today we'll
do some Northern Lights so come on up
here unless let's get started I want to
use the old fan brush today so probably
one of the best ways to do this is sort
of take and you can just on this black
canvas you can draw in some basic shapes
and if you've never seen the Northern
Lights a lot of times they're in what
they call curtains or just layers now if
in your part of the country there's no
such thing as northern lights you can do
the same scene leave the lights out and
maybe put a little moon in this guy and
it'll be just as effective but once
again for my friends in Alaska today I
want to do a Northern Lights picture
start with the old fan brush right into
titanium white now we already have all
those beautiful colors on the canvas so
all we need is white does go up here now
decide where these curtains or these
lights are gonna be and just begin
tapping see all I'm doing is just
tapping and tapping the color in and
make your basic shapes just very basic
shapes
and a little more paint where you want
to be a little brighter we have one
coming right across here and I'm just
tapping titanium white on there
sometimes there's little ridges and they
put balance around it that counts
just right on the round right down
around it we will have three layers of
Lights in this painting and you can have
as many as you want or as few as you
want it's up to you up to you now then
this is where the fun starts
let's take a one inch brush and I'm
gonna begin grabbing this and lifting it
upward just grab it and pop it just pop
it up already you can see it begin
picking up some of the different colors
and here like so this one Johnny Horton
wrote a beautiful song but Northern
Lights boy didn't lights were running
wild in the land of the Midnight Sun and
I lived there for over a dozen years and
that has to be that has to be one of the
prettiest countries in the world God was
really having a good day when he made
Alaska now then I'm gonna take the 2
inch brush and go all the way through
this and lift up all the way through
follow the same angles all the way look
at that there are you going you can pull
these as high as you want them and some
parts of the country they don't see a
lot of color in Northern Lights they see
maybe only White's or yellows and you
can do yours at play where I lived right
outside of Fairbanks in a little town
called North Pole
sometimes we would see lights in every
color in the rainbow
makes it a little more interesting so I
figured if I did a bunch of colors you
would find your color too here somewhere
okay you see now right in here this is
where the crimson was you have sort of a
lavender feel in here and blue and here
over here there's a little phthalo green
mixing with if they low blue make some
beautiful beautiful colors in the sky
let's wash the old brush give it a shake
this beat the devil out of it
and no painting of Alaska would be
complete without an almighty mountain
take a little bit of black put a little
brown in there very dark pull it out
flat cut across get that little roll of
paint right on the edge of the knife
okay let's go up here you have to make
the big decision where's your mountain
to live right there takes a very little
paint because the canvases are just
black put little bumps and hills and
valleys whatever you want in your
mountain
she just drop it in there like so and
scrape off all the excess paint you
really really can't scrape too hard then
go take a large brush grab it and pull
this just basically removes excess paint
the more of this paint that you can get
off but easier the next layer is
distinct let's take off all of it you
can get off this is also an excellent
way using brush strokes to begin letting
out your highlights and shadows see see
how you can pull all kinds of effects
there maybe you want to have and you're
not committed you can just keep changing
this and playing with it maybe you want
a little shadow you can see there that's
that easy to find out how your
highlights and shadows were looking
there pull it through or you just keep
going
spend all day just play in there
okay now then let's use our old knife
I'm going through the titanium white and
a little bit of blue just a small amount
of blue there just just enough to ten it
okay pull it out from very flat as flat
as you can get it get tough with it and
come across get that a little roll of
paint right over the edge of the knife
just go back up here now then let's have
some snow just coming right down the
side of this moment wherever you want it
to go no pressure no pressure at all
just let it flow you want that paint to
break all these little holes listen
there you go see and you can wiggle that
knife and cause all kinds of little
effects to happen let it go can you
write up here on the top we want a
little bit of snow right up here there
it comes right damn
maybe joins together you have to make
big decisions here maybe there's some
light striking right over here on that
little Ridge let's begin with our
shadows for the shadows gonna take blue
and white mix it together maybe we'll
make it a little bit lighter still a
little dark for what I want
that's much better cut across it our
little world of pain again okay
now then no pressure no pressure just
let it barely caress the canvas yeah
just begin elating of all kinds of
little things anywhere you want a little
Ridge just drop it in this is your
painting dear world you can do anything
that you
here little bit right back here see now
we can take this one
and pull it distinctly through and it
pushes that one right back hmmm
do you know you had that kind of power
could you push a mountains around why
did I go home only thing push around the
chair but here I can push around to
anything from the mountains and trees
and rivers there we go put a happy
little Pete Freddy's hair now we're
using a very firm paint here we want
this point to be as firm as possible
okay now see this little point here it
needs to have its own private shadow it
doesn't have its own check and it won't
stand out like an individual and you can
just bounce it back and forth here and
pull a chute look at there baby baby
there's another one there's right there
as many or as few as you want in your
world is your creation but each one of
them see here now once again right here
we need to have another shadow there we
go all the time this is mixing with that
beautiful color this underneath it
allows all kinds of things to happen you
know let's take a clean dry two inch
brush and I'm going to gently gently tap
following the angles in the mountain
always follow your ankles and tap more
down here at the base then you do up
here up here you just barely want to
whisper it down at the bottom you want
to tap it a little bit harder if you
would get into collecting some paint on
your brush just take beat the devil out
of it and that'll remove the excess
picking right off your brush without
going through a lot of cleaning
yeah Soph has to get into them over here
if you follow these angles always pay
attention to the angles in your mouth
and that's what you're looking for
they're very gently lift upward this
takes out all those little tap marks
softens balloons creates the illusion of
mist just like so fantastic okay yeah we
can play some more
that's fine as a fan brush I think we'll
just go right into this mixture we had
before we made the mountain with it it
was black they look blue little vendek
Brown just mix them on the brush load
that brush full of paint look at all the
paint's in there just go back up here
maybe there's some happy little trees
live back here huh these are far away
and all we're looking for it's just
little indications a little evergreens
that are far back in the distance
get a little more paint so you're using
the top part of that brush and just tap
downward that's all there is to it
hey you don't want to kill all this
misty area you kill this mist it's right
up here all little happened is these
trees will run right into the mountain
you wanted to stay separated so don't
kill you misty area save them they're
precious the good friends right here in
this mountain everything they do your
best friends so cherish him so now if
you get these two far apart they're
gonna begin looking like fence post so
if you if your little evergreens that
are far in the distance begin looking
like fence post chances are you just
don't have enough I had a few more and
see if it didn't doesn't help take care
of that little problem not easy we get
some happy little evergreen definitely
you back here in the distance all the
way across yeah then we can take another
fan brush you know I have I have several
of them going here so I don't have to
don't have to continually wash him we
take a little blue and white this was
just a little the shadow color is left
over let's go up here I want to just pop
in some indication of some happy little
tree trunks just on the bottom touch it
pull it straight up
touch pull straight up very lightly very
just enough to create a little little
light area down here at the base of
these trees just makes them a little
prettier so you're playing light against
dark dark against light continually
potato that's what painting is all about
baby hey we back here in the distance we
can start playing with a little detail
we'll take that same old black color
just a lot of paint in the brush just
black blue a lot of paint look at there
that the brushes are really full okay
let's go right up in here yeah we just
pop in a few little little bushes don't
want to kill all the little little tree
trunk areas that you made there you see
that little light area now is your
separator to divider just like so yeah
then I'll go back to this fan brushes
get mainly white on it can you take what
I'm gonna do and when I have it the
least little touch of the liquid white
to it to make it a little thinner just
go back up here nothing I want some I
want some bright things happening here
so I'm gonna take this and begin pushing
upward accrete just some happy little
grassy areas back here allow it to mix
with that color it's underneath all the
blues and blacks crates all kinds of
little things there we go maybe comes
right along in there whatever you want
maybe there's one out there will have
this will go up just sort of make a
decision let it happen yeah then let's
take a 2 inch brush and I'm just gonna
tap it into a little of the titanium
white just just gently tap it you see
okay let's go up here yeah I want a
happy little reflection to live right
underneath here oh you need his wife
because the color is already on the
canvas let's pull it straight down
straight down and start where you want
it to be the brightest and then work
outward in both directions and
automatically it'll get darker as it
works away from that area now with a
clean brush pull it down firmly like so
let's pull it straight down and then go
lightly across look at that
I don't take a little bit of liquid
quite and a little bit of titanium white
and mix it together pull it out flap
let's get a little roll of paint on the
knife tiny to the roll there it is and
let's go up here and just put the
indication of a little snow it's laying
right along the base of it and just
barely touching the canvas just barely
touching it allow it to mix with that
covers underneath don't fight these I
don't know just let them happen
there we are okay
that maybe tell you what let's play a
little the blue in the black on the fan
brush maybe right here an evergreen
that's a little bigger he's a little
touch closer I'm gonna drop him in right
there just like that and he lives right
out there but give him a little friend
we don't even meet lonely
he's just sitting right here watching
the northern lights or aurora borealis
whatever you want to call it easier to
take Northern Lights I'm gonna take a
little touch of that blue and white
mixture loaded on the fan brush and come
right along here I just put the
indication of a few little highlights
these trees are far away I don't want
too many if you get too many just take
your dark paint go right back over me
leaned it or right up all right all
right
now then let's have some fun let's put
in some bigger trees same old color just
use the blue and black mix it well
okay let's go right up here maybe yep I
see a big tree that there's right there
start with just the corner of the fan
brush work it back and forth back and
forth
and as you work down the tree add more
and more pressure down here you're
getting tough oh you're really taking
out all your frustrations down here
banging there's another tree here see
nothing everything's like people I've
known so many fantastic friends with
painting I think everything's got to
have friends trees and bushes and
everything needs friends everybody needs
a friend I'm going on the other side
over here let's get crazy I want one
that goes way up and goes all the way
through this Northern Light now there's
as many different ways to paint Northern
Lights as there are painters this is
just one interpretation and this is what
they look like to me who are they
it really makes a beautiful painting and
these black canvases when you change the
light source the painting changes you
put this under three different lights
and you'd almost you'd almost believe
you had three different paintings it
changes that much it's almost
unbelievable
and at home try these black canvases
with any transparent color I've got
letters that have asked me how do I tell
what color is transparent there's a very
very simple test fact I tell you why the
cameras right there I'll show you take a
color like blue bring the camera right
in here so we can see see if you take
this blue and rub it on here that still
looks black that color is transparent
and then let's take a color okay
let's use bright red that's a very
opaque color now when you put it there
whoo see what happens that color is not
transparent
it will not do for what we're trying to
do here that's a good test of course now
we got a red spot on the canvas hey
paint another tree tree he's cover up a
multitude of sins
we'll have another one yeah okay we'll
get a one-inch brush we'll use it for a
little bit take a same color the blue
into black we'll grab a little bit of
this lighter color and put it in there
pull that brush in one direction the
loaded full of paint so very dark blue
James go ahead up here now maybe we're
gonna have some happy little
snow-covered bushes so all we're doing
it's just beginning to lay in some of
the very basic shapes you're not looking
for detail yet only very basic shapes
very basic okay let's go right over in
here maybe there's a happy Bush yep
that's right tear comes right now or
just wherever you want wherever you want
can have as many or as few just just let
your imagination take you
if you've never been to Alaska you know
where to go see it it's almost unreal I
was born and raised in Florida I was
almost 20 years old before I ever saw
snow and my favorite uncle Uncle Sam he
sent me up there in January thought that
would be funny and it was funny I I got
off the plane the first thing I did was
stepped on the ice and fell on my bottom
because I didn't know how to walk on ice
I'm taking some liquid white and going
right into titanium Hoyt pull it in one
direction I'm gonna put a little tiny
bit of blue in it one direction look at
all the painters on that brush it's a
really full okay let's go up there now
then you begin picking out or all these
little bushes live and just barely touch
give it a little push and create all
these little snow-covered bushes and
Alaska they have ice fog and ice fog
occurs normally when it's about 30 below
or colder and it covers everything
everything with frost it is so beautiful
trees look like they're in full foliage
it's so beautiful in the light place
through it and these all these little
ice-covered frosty things they act like
prisms and they break up the light and
you see all colors in the trees and the
dead of winter you can see just you have
to go see it I can't can't explain it
all to you
so pretty but there's a nice Bush just
grows right out of that brush we'll put
another one right there there they go
let's drop them in just half the little
bushes happy little bushes there well
with the completion of this painting
this will Enda at the eighth joy of
painting series it's hard for me to
believe it we have over a hundred shows
now over a hundred shows hmm taking a
little blue here put a little highlight
on these trees
I really hope you've got to see all the
shows if there's any of them that you've
missed you'd like to see them give your
station to call I don't know I don't
know what you want to see and when they
need some help give them a hand there we
are let's go over to this tree told him
to be left out
just hearing their don't kill all the
dark contrast that's what makes it
pretty and you know me I gotta have a
little cabin in here so maybe with all
this paint I have on here I'm gonna
scrape out just the basic shape to get
rid of that loose paint it's also a good
way to layout you your initial cabin
shape start with a little bit of vendek
Brown and I'll mix some dark sienna
right in that I've just mix them
together hold it across a little friend
on that cabin here you know and as we're
winding down this series I'd like to
take just a minute and thank the people
here at the television station we have
one of the finest crews in the country
and they they make some of these
beautiful television shows and you never
see them you may never they never get a
thank you if it wasn't for them they
wouldn't there wouldn't be any show a
little bit of brown and white here just
put some highlight on him give him a
little taller yeah tell you why
let's put some snow up here on his roof
just like so and it gives us a quick
little cabin we can just bring some snow
right down Mike Landess see how easy it
is put some snow over here on the other
side the roof we don't want that one to
be left out but that wherever you want
it okay
maybe sounds coming there just like
see and pay attention to your angles
when you're playing the snowing angles
are very important very important put
all kinds of little snow things here
okay let's go back in here pick up some
of the liquid point go right into my
titanium height owed to brush for and
this pop a few more little bushes right
in working layers completing the most
distant part of your painting first and
working forward just like so see little
bushy things over in here and we're on
the verge of having a completed painting
take the knife scratch - these two twigs
show and this one's about done once
again I'd like to thank you for being
with me during this eight joy of
painting series we have the ninth series
under production already so we'll see
you again from all of us here happy
painting
[Music]