("The Joy of Painting" by Larry Owens)
- Hello, I'm Bob Ross.
And I'd like to welcome you
to our fifth painting series.
If you've been with us before,
I hope you have your
almighty easel set up,
and you're all ready to go along with me
and paint a fantastic little painting.
And let's go across the colors
that we're going to use.
I'll have them graphically run
the colors across the screen,
starting with the titanium white,
and going all the way around.
and they'll come across your screen
in the same order that I
have them on my palette.
If you haven't been with us before,
hang around.
I think you'll really
enjoy what we're gonna do.
I've already covered the canvas
with a thin, even coat of Magic White.
And the Magic White, it makes the canvas
wet, makes it slick.
It allows us to literally blend
color right on the canvas.
So, let's go up here and do it.
And I'll start with a big old
two and a half inch brush today.
And we'll go right into a
little bit of thalo blue.
And we'll just work some of that
right into the bristles here.
Just beat it into the bristles,
so you have a nice, even
distribution of color.
(thumping)
Kay, let's go up to the canvas here.
Maybe we'll make a, let's just make a
happy little sky here.
We just use a little,
little criss-cross strokes.
(brushing)
And just let the brush
just sort of bounce around
and play and
just let it have fun.
Let it have fun.
A little more color.
And we'll go up here in this corner.
(brushing)
And I'm not coloring the
entire canvas evenly.
I'm leaving some little
spots here and there that
oh, hopefully when we're
done it'll look like
some happy little clouds
floating all across the sky.
There.
(thumping)
Now, it's easy, it's real
easy to make the sky darker.
But, it's a son of a
gun to make it lighter.
(scraping)
So, use very, very little
color when you first start.
You can always go back and add more color.
Now, while I've got this
old dirty brush going here,
I'm gonna reach right up into this color,
which is a little bit of thalo green.
And we want very, very small amounts.
Extremely, extremely strong.
And we'll just mix it right on the brush.
There we go, a little
thalo green and thalo blue.
Okay, let's go back up here.
I wanna have some water in this painting.
I love water.
And water is always level.
It's still water, it's always level.
(scraping)
So, just come across.
Try to keep the strokes
as straight as possible.
Okay, now let's go to the other side,
and pull this way.
(scraping)
Painting, see how the color's blending in.
It's continually mixing
with the Magic White.
Now, you could do all these
things on the palette,
but they would take you a long time.
Here we let it happen on
the, right on the canvas.
(scraping)
Mkay.
Now, I'll wash the brush.
And we wash our brushes
with odorless paint thinner.
I never, never wash my
brushes with turpentine.
Only with odorless paint thinner.
(tapping)
Shake off the excess.
(banging)
And, that's the most fun of all.
Now, with a clean, dry brush,
I'm gonna go back into the sky
and just very quickly,
blend it out a little bit.
(fast scraping)
Those light spots remain.
There.
Just let this happen.
We really just sort of let it just flow
right out of our mind,
right onto the canvas.
And you don't have to spend a great deal
of time planning and worrying.
Just let it go. Let it go.
Mkay.
Tell you what, let's do.
Let's take an almighty fan brush here,
and we'll make a happy little cloud.
And I'm using a number six fan brush,
and some titanium white.
Tell you what, let's put the least
little amount of permanent red in there.
Put a little sunshine on it.
Want some sunshine in our clouds.
Load a lot of paint into the bristles.
Lot of paint.
Kay, now let's go up to the canvas here.
Maybe.
Maybe, maybe, right here.
Using just the corner of the brush.
We'll put a happy little cloud.
And clouds are very, very free.
Very free, just let 'em
bounce around and play.
And we're looking for
areas here that are thick,
areas that are thin,
areas that have no paint.
Keep the brush moving.
Keep it moving.
If you let it stay in one place,
and keep doing this, you're gonna
you're gonna end up with a
big cotton ball up in the sky.
Let it move.
(scratching)
I tell you what, let's go
over to the other side here.
Maybe there's a happy little cloud that.
Yeah, there was.
He lives right there.
Just let him go.
There he is.
And you put these clouds
wherever you want 'em.
This piece of canvas is your world.
It's your world.
And you make your world
the way you want it.
Now then, I'm gonna take
a clean, dry, two and a half inch brush
And I wanna blend, I want to blend
the bottom of these clouds out
without touching the top.
So let's start right
here, and very lightly.
Very lightly, very lightly.
Three hairs and some air.
Just let it caress the canvas.
Barely, barely, barely touching.
Blend the bottom out.
Leave the top of the cloud alone.
Kay, let's do this one.
And work in layers.
(scratching)
Kay now, let's fluff this cloud.
Now watch what happens.
We're gonna lift this cloud up.
And you're gonna pull little,
little stringy things of paint up,
don't worry about 'em,
don't worry about 'em.
You want those to happen right now.
And then very lightly, you just blend 'em,
and it brings all of it together.
Kay, let's do that again
over here on the other side.
Just blend the bottom of the cloud out.
(scraping)
Just like so.
Fluff it up.
And then blend it.
And this little son of a gun here,
we don't want to forget him.
And we'll just blend him out.
And fluff him up.
And then very lightly,
very lightly.
And that easy,
that easy, you've got some beautiful,
beautiful, very effective little clouds.
Okay, I'll wash my brush.
There's a screen in the bottom of this can
that I scrub the brush against.
It really helps.
Helps get the paint out of the brush.
I tell you what, my home
is in Fairbanks, Alaska,
so I'm sort of hung up on mountains.
So let's build a fantastic
little mountain here.
Go ahead and take some thalo blue,
some Van Dyke Brown,
and we'll use a little
bit alizarin crimson.
So we have thalo blue, Van Dyke Brown,
and a small amount of alizarin crimson.
Now, the more crimson you put in,
the more purplish your
mountain's gonna be.
Pull this paint out very flat,
and just cut across it so you
have a small roll of paint.
There, right out on the edge of the knife.
Let's go up here.
Now, you have to make some
decisions in your world.
Where's the mountain gonna live?
I'm gonna have my
mountain live right there.
And you're really, really pushing
this paint into the canvas.
Really push it into the canvas.
And anywhere you decide there's a bump
or hill or big stone,
put it in.
Put it in.
(short scraping)
This is where ya exert your
fantastic power
is right here.
Kay, now
See you scrape off the excess paint.
(scraping)
And the canvas will keep what it wants.
The value is in the material.
Kay, now, I wanna remove more
excess paint and blend this out.
Because the canvas is wet,
this paint will move, it'll slide.
You can move it all over the canvas.
There we go, and just pull it out.
And when you're painting mountains
always remember
if you can see the entire mountain
it's always more distinct at the top
than it is at the bottom.
At the bottom of the mountain
we have mist and
now we have pollution.
All these things have a tendency
to break up and diffuse light.
And you can see from that the top
of the mountain's very
dark, it's very strong.
And down at the bottom of the mountain
then it's very soft and quiet, peaceful.
And that's what we're looking for.
Kay, now I'm gonna go
right into my titanium white.
We'll put a little snow on this mountain.
Little bit of snow.
Pull it out very flat.
Very, very flat.
Just like we did before.
And then cut across it.
Get that small roll of paint.
Okay, let's go up here.
Now, you have to make some decisions.
Which one of these peaks
is the farthest away?
The one that's farthest
away, let's do it first.
There. Just follow
right down the mountain.
No pressure. Absolutely no pressure.
No pressure.
All that's touching the canvas is that
little roll of paint that's on the knife.
And then you begin thinking about
where the light would strike as it
just comes through here.
Now, some people find it easier
to put the shadow on first.
Personally, I like to put
the highlight on first.
And then put the shadow in later.
But, either way that works for you.
There are no set, firm rules in painting.
You find what works for you.
And that's what you do.
(light scraping)
There we go.
And you can bring this down to
wherever you want it.
You can end up covering your
whole canvas with mountains,
which is a super way to practice.
I'm gonna take some thalo blue
and titanium white and
we'll mix that together.
And to that, I'm gonna add a
small amount of Van Dyke Brown.
The brown is there
just to dull it down.
And I'm not worried about overmixing that.
Just leave that paint marbled.
Okay, and once again we'll
take that little roll of paint.
Let's go up here.
And, we'll go in the opposite direction.
The opposing direction,
whatever you wanna call it.
And, put in some shadows.
And every shadow
needs it's own little, private highlight.
Or he won't play.
He'll just disappear on ya.
Look at that, look at that.
I've painted for over
20 years and it still
excites me to see these things happen.
It's unbelievable.
I was a traditional painter for many years
and I suffered and ah my gosh.
Would spend weeks and weeks
and weeks on a painting.
And when I got finished
I had turned it to mud.
Or I was so tired of looking at it,
I didn't want to paint on it anymore.
And this
this offers you unlimited freedom.
Unlimited freedom.
And that's what we're all looking for.
Little bit of highlight right there.
Now, let's just sort of
bring these together.
Maybe it comes from right here.
And just let it
just let it sort of work together.
I guess I'll
come right there
Just like that.
And you can keep adding
just wherever you think there should be a
almighty peak.
That's where it should be.
(scraping)
There.
And on this series, we're gonna try to
I'm gonna bring in a couple of friends.
I think I'll bring in a couple of friends
and let them to show you some
fantastic things that can be done.
The more people that
you see that can do this
the more you'll understand
that you can do it too.
There's no big secret to it.
Anybody can do it if they're
willing to practice a little bit.
Now, we'll take the large brush.
I wanna create some mist down here.
So, here I'm tapping.
Just lightly tapping.
Paying particular attention to the angles.
Always follow the angles in your mountain.
And then we'll lift up.
Very lightly, lift upward.
And look at that.
Creates a very soft misty, misty effects.
Maybe, let's play a game.
Let's play a little bit here.
Maybe one of these peaks here
show you how to bring a mountain.
Oh let's, I tell you what.
We're having such a good time here,
show you something else
too while I'm here.
I'm gonna take a little of the Magic White
and add it right into my titanium white.
So it's a little bit thinner.
One of our golden rules.
Thin paint will stick to a thick paint.
And I wanna
I wanna put a cloud coming
right across the mountain here.
Just, let it come right across.
You know, these old clouds,
they just sort of drift across a mountain.
So, just barely touch.
And this is a thinner paint
and it'll stick on top of that thick paint
that's already up there.
Okay, maybe he's got a little friend
that lives right here.
And maybe, shoot who knows.
Maybe there's a happy little cloud
that he sort of, maybe
he fell out of the sky,
and he just floating right down here
at the bottom of this mountain.
And, we'll take the big brush.
Just blend that.
Looka there.
Fluff it up.
Fluff it up, up.
And then very lightly, we'll
just blend all this together.
And we'll put a happy little cloud
right there at the bottom of the mountain.
And you can put as many of
these in here as you want.
(scraping)
And maybe, tell you what.
Let's just bring this one
right down in front of the cloud.
And you can just keep
adding on and on and on.
Wherever you want it to go.
Look at that.
(scratching)
Then we'll drop a happy
little shadow here and there.
See how that shadow makes it just pop out.
That's where it happens.
Now, we could spend the whole show
working on mountains here.
But, I'm sure we wanna
look at some other things.
So we'll just put some mist right here.
(bump scratching)
Over here, we follow these angles.
Soften all this up.
And go from there.
And that easy.
Now you can see how
this plane projects out.
The little mist in here and the softening.
It just brings it right out.
Tell you what, I'm gonna mix up
we'll just use the same mountain color
and we'll put sap green into it.
So we have blue, brown a
little alizarin crimson
and now a touch of sap green into it.
(scraping)
Just a little though.
Okay. Now let me clean my knife.
We'll use the fan brush.
And I'll just quickly
lay a little on here.
Now, I wanna have maybe,
like a little tree line
going up the side of this mountain.
So I wanna do in here where
the fan brush is just touching.
And you still, still need to follow
the angles in that mountain.
Always follow the angles in that mountain.
And that easy. That easy.
You can put a whole forest nearly
just climbing right up
the side of the mountain.
There we go.
And all we're doing is laying
it on with the fan brush.
(tapping)
Just lay it on.
Then we'll take a one-inch
brush, just clean and dry.
And very lightly
begin lifting straight up.
Just straight up.
There we go.
Barely, barely touching.
Now this softens and
brings everything together.
That easy.
You know it's hard for me to believe
that we're into our fifth series.
Oh my gosh it was
it's
you can't believe what wonderful things
it does to my heart to know that
you've allowed me into your home
this many times and you're
inviting me back again.
You've
literally made a dream come true.
All my life I have wanted to
to be able to share
my views of nature
with everybody.
And you've allowed me to do it.
And now,
I want to thank you from
the bottom of my heart.
It's very special to me.
Kay, let's go up here.
Maybe
back in here there's
There it is.
You knew it was there.
Some happy little trees
that live way back here.
(tapping scratches)
And this is that same color.
Same, same color.
(tapping scratches)
There we go.
And all you're looking for is distant,
distant indications here.
We don't want
We don't want a lot of detail yet.
When things are far away
you don't see all the detail that you see
when they're close up.
So, lack of detail sometimes
can be as important as detail.
Just let these little trees grow
wherever you think they should.
And don't worry about
covering up some of this
because it's gonna show through,
and that's what makes it look real.
Nature doesn't move trees just so it's
pretty for ya.
They grow wherever makes 'em happy.
(scratching taps)
Very quickly here we'll just drop in
some happy little things here.
Same color, same color.
That's all there is to it.
Same, same old color.
Very dark color.
Now, this fan brush has
a little white on it.
I wanna put some little indications maybe
a few little tree trunks back here.
So, all I'm doing is lifting upward.
Very lightly.
Very few. Don't get crazy.
Don't get too many here.
Just a few, just a few.
And if you get one that's too light,
all you have to do is rub it a little bit,
and it'll pick up that
dark color underneath,
and it'll go away.
Now then, let's put some highlight here.
I'm gonna start with
this is cadmium yellow.
Put a little yellow ochre into it.
And some sap green.
And we'll just mix these
right on the fan brush.
A lot of paint in the brush.
Lot of paint.
Just work that brush.
But, you can see all the layers of color.
And when you mix on the brush,
you get all these different layers.
You don't have one flat, old, dead color.
And we're looking for
a bright, shiny color.
Kay.
Now we touch and push
bend upward.
Just bend that brush upward.
Can you see how that's a
touch it, push it and bend it.
And that makes all those
little grassy things.
Way back here in the distance.
Far, far away.
Maybe there's, maybe, maybe
comes right down through.
Wherever you want it.
There it goes.
There it goes, right up through there.
(scratching taps)
Right on up
And you just sort of make
these little paintings
up in your mind as you go along.
Let 'em happen.
Now, I want some reflections on there.
So, I'm gonna touch
a small, small amount of the thalo blue.
I want the reflections to
have a little more blue
cast to 'em.
And go right up here and
I'm gonna pick up a
little bit of the color.
And it's gonna mix with the blue.
And all of it's gonna
mix with the Magic White.
And instant, instant reflections.
This may be one of the
most fantastic things
that happens in this technique.
Is some of the most
spectacular reflections
imaginable.
And it's easy.
So easy.
(scratching)
There we go.
And then, very lightly, go across.
This'll give it a watery appearance.
That easy.
Now then.
Maybe there's some stones back here.
So let's take some burnt umber.
And I'll use yellow ochre.
Yellow ochre and burnt umber.
Put a little titanium white in there too.
What the heck.
That'll be our highlight color.
And then we can start with
just straight Van Dyke Brown.
And put in our base color.
We'll just drop in some
happy little things
♫ do doodle do do doo
♫ do doodle de do ♫
There you go.
Just let 'em happen.
And painting, painting
should make ya happy.
Should bring a song to your heart.
Make you appreciate life.
All the beautiful things that
are happening around you.
Take time to
Take time to look at nature,
to appreciate it.
Sometimes we
we look at it everyday and we
we have a tendency to overlook it.
Okay, this is that highlight color.
It's yellow ochre and burnt umber,
and a little titanium white.
See, and you get all these things
because you don't over mix your paint.
Let it
Let it happen.
Don't fight it.
That's what it's all about.
Just relax.
Be calm, peaceful.
And let it go.
Okay, now then
we'll take
and let's just drop in some
some little grassy areas coming
right down through there.
Wherever you want 'em.
Over here a few.
And that sort of just
ties it all together.
And now I'll use a little
of the Magic White.
Very thin.
And we'll drop in a happy
little water line back here.
Just like so.
(zipping)
And the beauty of this,
the beauty of this technique
is that right in the middle of it
you can change your mind.
You can redesign paintings.
Because this is your world.
You can do anything that you
want to do in this world.
Anything that you wanna do.
(liquid swishing)
Wash that brush real quick.
Okay, a little of the Magic White.
A little titanium white.
Maybe, who knows, who knows.
Maybe back here there's just a
little indication.
There it is. Look at that.
Look at that.
A little stream lives right there.
And just, it drops right in here
and puts some water
right into our painting.
Right into our painting.
A few little happy, grassy things.
And that easy.
That easy.
You can just put you
a happy little stream.
Little foam here where it's
coming out into this river, lake or pond.
Whatever you want it to be.
Okay, now we can
we can get over here into the foreground
and really have some fun.
So, I'm gonna take all the
dark colors that I got.
There's brown, there's blue
oh there's some crimson,
big gob of sap green.
Big thing is that it's dark.
Kay, let me get a big brush here.
And I'll just use this old, dirty brush.
We'll go right up into this color.
Wiggle that brush.
Wiggle, wiggle, wiggle that brush.
Bring it to a nice sharp, sharp edge.
See if you can see that. See.
It's a very nice, sharp, chiseled edge.
Let's go up here.
Now, right here, in my world, there lives
There certainly better live there now.
A big evergreen tree.
And he just lives right in this brush.
And all you do is just go back and forth.
And push him out.
Just push him out.
And there he comes.
There he comes.
Don't be afraid of this
brush because it's big.
It will do absolutely fantastic things.
And right here there's
a little bush and a tree
and it comes right across.
Wherever you want it.
We'll just fill all this up with dark.
You need the dark
in order for your light to show.
We can't have light without dark.
You know it's just like
it's just like in life.
You can't know happiness
unless you've known a
little bit of sorrow.
So, Good Lord gives us all
a little bit of sorrow,
so we can know the
happiness when it comes.
Tree trunks.
Little burnt umber.
♫ do do da do do to ♫
There we are.
Little highlight color.
This is a little yellow ochre.
Kay, now then
I'm gonna take a
one-inch brush
put a little paint thinner
on it to thin the paint.
Sap green and yellow.
And let's just very quickly here
drop in some little indications of
a few highlights.
Just a few indications.
Darker, darker, darker
as they go down here.
If your paint,
if you have trouble making it stick,
add a little bit of paint thinner
or Magic White, that'll thin your paint.
There we go.
Drop in a happy little bush right there.
This is sap green, cad yellow.
Just drop 'em in, wherever you want 'em.
It's your world.
Tell you what
gonna add a small amount of indian yellow,
yellow ochre and some permanent red here.
I want one that
that shines right here.
Just like so.
And I really hope you've enjoyed this.
It's a lot of fun.
I hope to see ya every week here with us.
And we'll teach you some
of the most fantastic
and easy paintings you've ever seen.
And they're very effective.
They'll make you happy (laugh)
Your friends will never
believe you've done 'em.
Mkay, now with just a clean knife here,
we can drop in a few
little sticks and twigs.
That easy. Wherever you
think they should be.
Just drop 'em in.
(tapping scraping)
And I think we have a finished painting.
And with that,
we'll stop here.
I'd like to wish each and every one of ya
happy painting.
I look forward to seeing you next week.
Good bye.
(" The Joy of Painting" by Larry Owens)