- Hey welcome back.
Certainly glad you could join us today.
It's a fantastic day here and
I hope it is wherever you are.
Tell you what let's get right on it today.
Let's start out and run all
the colors across the screen
that you need to paint along with us.
While they're doing that let me tell you
what I've got done up here already.
I thought today we'd do the
little opening that you see.
The painting that the little painter man
is wiping off with a big brush
and I want to show you
how that one was made.
So I've taken just a plain
old 18 by 24 inch canvas
and I've picked up some masking tape.
It was laying around the studio here and
I've just put one square
here and one square there
of just masking tape,
that's all it is
and I've covered the whole
canvas with a thin even coat
of the liquid white.
So it's all ready to go so
let's just have a good time.
Let's start out today with a
small amount of yellow ochre.
Very, very small amount
on the two inch brush
and this won't be an exact
duplicate of what you see
on the opening but it's close
enough you'll see exactly
how it was made and then
you can do your own at home,
but just paint right
over the masking tape.
Just like it wasn't even there.
Just like so.
You had a little bit of
yellow up there in the sky.
There.
About like that, that's
all we're looking for
and this is just plain yellow ochre,
but it's blending with
the liquid white that's
already on the canvas
and all these fantastic hues
happen automatically, automatically.
Okay.
Tell you what,
I'm gonna grab another brush,
I have several of them
so I don't have to spend
all my time washing brushes
and go right into a small
amount of the midnight black,
don't need much, just a little,
just a little.
Let's go back up here now.
Now over here we'll just take that black
and we'll just begin on
the other side of the sky.
Now once again this also is
gonna mix with the liquid white
and the black of course
is gonna become grey.
So we have a grey sky with
a little bit of yellow in it
and that's all that's in that
sky that you see in the opening.
I like that opening
that little painter man
is so cute.
That was the idea of a
special friend that works here
at the station, Jerry Morton.
He put that thing together for us.
He's very talented and I
thank him for doing that.
There.
Okay, just blend these together
so you can't tell where
one color stops and the next color starts.
That's all we're looking for
and then very lightly,
very lightly go across the entire canvas
and that just removes the brush strokes.
Maybe blend a little more right there.
Okay great.
Something like so.
Now then, okay.
Let me wash the old brush here
and as you know we wash our
brushes with odorless thinner.
Shake of the excess.
Hm, just beat the devil out of it.
Oh I've got to show you something here.
I have to show you this.
A gentleman made this for me.
This is a cane that he carved and
it is unreal,
but he's actually put an image of
old Bob on the end of it here
and this was done by Mike Weaver.
He's one of our certified
instructors in Missouri
but as you can see he's
talented in many ways
but that's really
fantastic cane, isn't it?
I think he's trying to tell me something.
Okay.
Let's keep going here.
We'll take a little of the black.
Put a little mountain in here,
little black,
little touch of,
little touch of phthalo blue in there.
Maybe even a little alizarin crimson.
Pull it out very flat, cut across,
get our little roll of paint.
Now these little squares
we're going to play some games here
with different planes.
So I'm going to have a mountain
that projects above this
right here
and comes down.
Something like so,
but I'm going to stop it right
here at this piece of tape.
There,
we'll let that come right on down
like so,
here's another peak right here.
Just wherever you think a
little peak should live.
That's exactly where it should be.
Right on down
and we'll stop it right
there at that piece of tape.
Okay a little color right under there.
Now we can take a clean
dry two inch brush,
and just grab that and pull it just like
we normally do to make a mountain.
There,
but I want to be careful not to let
that color go past the tape.
There.
If you like this painting
you can certainly do it
without the tape and it's
still a beautiful painting.
Or you could make your own designs.
These designs are very
interesting and people like them.
Try them.
It's very simple, you can do
it with tape or contact paper.
Just any old thing that'll
stick to the canvas.
Mm-hmm.
Now let's just take some titanium white.
We'll pull it out very flat,
cut across,
get our little roll of paint again.
Always have that little roll of paint.
Now we can go up in here and
just start laying on some highlights
right on this mountain.
Barely, barely touching.
Barely touching.
Just graze the canvas.
As I've mentioned before,
when I was teaching my son
Steve to paint,
I used to tell him just to
pretend that he was a whisperer
just floating right across the mountain.
It's that light.
It's that delicate of a touch.
You oughta see what kind of
mountains he's painting today.
Well you might of saw him on
some of the previous shows.
Does some fantastic mountains.
He does better mountains than I do.
Don't tell him I said that.
Let's take little white,
a little bit of phthalo blue.
Mix together.
and we use that for shadow color.
Okay, I just take little edge.
Let him go up in here
and maybe I'll just sort of
pull downward a little bit.
Make the indication of some little
ridges back here.
Sometimes it's fun to play
little games in your mountains.
Then we can come back here.
Just let all these little things happen.
Little touch up in here.
Just so we can see a little.
Now we know there's tape there.
Nothing's gonna show so we don't care.
We'll just bring that right across.
There
and wherever we need a shadow then
we can just lay it in.
Little touch right in there.
We'll push that little rascal right back.
That easy.
On this canvas you have unlimited power.
Can do anything here.
You can change your world.
Anything.
Little white we just play
some games back and forth.
Let that just sort of float in there.
Wherever.
Now we take a clean
(beating brush)
and very dry two inch brush.
That's what all that beating was
I was just making sure it was dry,
and then very gently lift upward.
That'll help create that illusion of mist
down at the base of the mountain.
Over here.
This direction and lift upward.
Sometimes you can grab
just a little bit of that
and pull it.
Looks like a little
light has spilled over.
It's quite pretty.
There.
(brushing)
Okay.
Now then we're ready to start
putting some little footie hills in.
So for that,
take we'll just use
that same old mountain color.
Same old mountain color
with a little be right back.
A little bit of white in it.
Just wanna lighten it up,
but it's the same basic color.
There.
Let's go ahead up here.
Very simple little foothill.
We just have it come
right on down,
down, down, down.
Maybe, maybe right along there.
All we're doing is tapping with a corner.
Now but watch,
come back over this way.
Watch right here.
See I'm gonna let this go into this plane.
Notice the mountain stops here,
but this one is gonna
come through this plane
and on over.
This about as close to
an abstract painting
as I've ever done on television.
'Course I've made some mistakes at home
and we call those abstracts
but this is
the first one we've done intentionally.
I normally don't do paintings
that I have to explain.
There.
Okay, now let's have a little water
down here while we have
this color on here.
We can just come right in here.
Put in the indication of
a little bit of water floating around.
Something like so.
(brushing)
There,
and this is just basic old mountain color.
(brushing)
Okay, a little bit on
the other side over here.
I'm gonna keep right in here.
I'm gonna keep it inside of this border.
(brushing)
There,
and maybe down here we'll let it slip out.
Something like that,
but just play games with different planes
in your painting
and you'll be surprised
at what you can create.
You will absolutely be amazed.
Now then,
same color.
We'll pull a little of that straight down.
Straight down,
and that'll end up being our reflections
under that little foothill back there.
Gently across, that easy.
Instant reflections,
that's sneaky isn't it?
There,
a little bit of the liquid white.
Pull it out as flat as you can get it
and then take a knife and just cut across.
That's all there is to it.
Then go up here and act just like you're
trying to cut a hole
right through the canvas
and this old canvas is tough,
you're not gonna hurt it.
Not gonna hurt it,
I don't think.
If you get out the butcher knife in your
kitchen you certainly can,
but this knife is dull,
you're not gonna hurt it
and right on over into here too.
We want it to be all the way over.
Okay.
Now gonna mix up a little more color here.
We'll use black.
Some phthalo blue,
maybe I'll put a little
Prussian blue in there too.
I'm gonna begin darkening this blue down.
Put a little alizarin crimson in there.
Something like so.
Least little touch of sap green.
Alright.
Okay let me wipe the old knife.
Now then,
shoot let's get crazy.
I'm gonna use the one inch brush today.
Fan brush should work just as well
but since I have it let's use it
and let's go in here.
Now this one stopped at that plane.
Let's have this group
of little distant trees.
They're bigger,
closer to us.
I remember they come right
down something like so
and we'll have these work their way.
Whew, there they go.
Right on up and right off the canvas.
So now each plane in the painting,
each layer of the painting has stopped
at a different point within this tape
and that's one of the things
that make this painting
so interesting when people look at it
and I guarantee if you paint this one,
people will look at it.
There, pull that down a little.
Now I wanna create mist right at the base.
All you have to do is just tap.
Tap it, tap it, tap it
all the way across and lift upward.
Upward, upward
and that'll create the illusion of mist.
Now then,
let's take,
I'm gonna add to that
same color we just had,
some brown.
Little bit of brown.
Little bit more of the black.
So it's a very dark color.
Okay tap a little of that in there.
Now I wanna have some land areas here.
I think the one that
you see in that opening
has land areas that come
right out like that.
So we put some dark in
only so our light will show.
You have to have dark
in order to show light.
It's just like in life.
If you don't have a little
sadness in your life,
you don't know when the happy times come.
There.
You know, while I'm doing this,
this is very repetitious,
I'm just gonna be putting
in some dark areas.
I wanna share a piece of video with you
from a young friend
that is just unreal.
This may be one of the youngest painters
that I've run into
and this young man's
name is Earl Glen Russell
and he comes to us out
of Springfield, Missouri
and he is just a fantastic little painter.
I had the pleasure of
having dinner one night
with Earl and his mother when I was there
and they're some of the loveliest people
I've ever met in my whole life
and this painting introduces
you to so many new friends
and Earl and his mother
are just two of many people
that I've had the opportunity to meet.
Just through painting.
There.
(brushing)
Okay,
but isn't that little rascal good?
I mean he can paint.
(beating brush)
All I'm doing is just making
some reflections in here
while you're doing that.
Look at that finished painting
and if I remember I think
Earl was nine years old now
going on 40.
(laughs)
Isn't he something?
I am so proud of that young man.
All I've done is just tap
in a little dark color here.
Trying to remember basically
where we had things.
Maybe that came down about like that.
Somewhere in there,
but notice as we're doing this,
we're putting the
reflections with each layer
because if I didn't pull this down,
before I did this part it
would mess up that of course.
So each layer, pull your
reflections down just like so.
Before you do the next layer
and that way it'll work so much easier.
There,
now we can come back.
Put in all kinds of little things in here.
(brush tapping)
Something like that.
Think that came right on out right there.
Okay.
Now then.
We can just,
we'll just use that same old brush.
We can go right into
a little of the cad yellow,
yellow ochre,
Indian yellow
and then I'll hit a little
touch of the bright red,
but mix the color on the brush
so you have a multitude of
colors happening right there
on your brush.
Okay let's go back up here.
Now,
we'll put some nice green highlights
right out here on this little peninsula
that juts out into the water.
Just tap.
Tap, tap.
Now then, watch.
Let's play some games.
Sometimes it's fun,
let me find,
we'll use a number three fan brush today.
Let me pile my color up.
If your color gets too flat on the palate
you have to sort of pile it up
so you can load a brush.
So if you ever have trouble
loading the brush yet you
know there's enough paint,
just put it in a pile and
then you can load your brush.
Otherwise you just polish your palate.
There.
Okay let's,
go right in here and make it
look like there's some trees
that just go right out like that
but you have to put that grassy area
back in here first
then put your trees and then come back
and put your next layer.
So that it looks like there's layers
and that's what'll make your painting
stand out and be special.
Alright, now then,
back to our big brush,
with all the little grassy things on it.
We can come right back in here.
See there?
And begin laying in
all kinds of little areas.
There.
You can make this just
as soft as a meadow.
Okay.
Now then let's have some fun.
Gotta mix up some more color.
Let's use some Prussian blue,
some black,
alizarin crimson, sap green.
Sounds good.
Might as well mix up a
pretty good pile of paint.
We're gonna use it before
this one's finished.
Get a big fan brush, it's time we get,
got strong here.
There.
Okay.
Just fill the brush up full of color.
Lot of color.
Now then we have to make
some big decisions here.
I think right there.
Right here.
We will have a nice evergreen tree
and I'm intentionally letting
this go right over the tape.
So when we pull the tape off,
you'll only see part of the tree.
Maybe we'll give him a friend.
You know me,
think everybody needs a friend.
There,
and as I say that's one
thing that painting has done.
As Annette and I have
traveled around the country
teaching people,
we have made so many fantastic friends
that have been with us for so long now
and that might truly
be the joy of painting
is the friends that you make doing it.
I'm gonna take,
I'm gonna tell you what.
I was about to leave this trunk out.
Poor little thing would
fall over from weakness.
Take a little dark sienna and white,
little roll of paint,
and our little evergreen tree here.
Let's just put
least little indication
of a tree trunk.
There.
Now then,
I have dark green,
the little brush,
doesn't matter which brush you use
I just happened to pick it up.
Put a few little highlights
on this rascal here.
There.
Alright.
Now then let's take some van dyke brown
on the old knife
and let's go right in here,
put some banks underneath this grass.
Just some little banks,
wherever.
Maybe there's a lot of
dirt showing right there.
There
and wherever.
We can go ahead and put
some down in here too,
'cause we know it's going
to end up being there
and here and there maybe
there's gonna be some dirt
up in here wherever.
Doesn't much matter.
Little touch of brown and white
and we can just tip that a little.
Just to make it look like rocks and dirt.
There.
All kinds of little things are happening.
There they are.
There, okay.
Now I'm gonna take my fan
brush that has the green on it
and go back in here and pop in
a little bush here and there.
Just enough to sort of break up that edge
and bring all that together.
Maybe there's some nice
bushes right here in front of
those little trees.
Take the knife,
scrape in few little sticks and twigs
and sometimes I scratch down,
sometime I scratch up.
Just depends on what kind
of mood I'm in. (laughs)
That you'll find by
touching it and pulling up
you'll get a sharper point on the end.
There if that makes sense.
Let's go we'll use a one inch brush.
Maybe we have a
big bush if I remember correctly,
it lives right about
here.
So we just throw some dark
in so our light will show.
Push upward with a one inch brush.
Create all those little,
little leafy feelings.
I'm gonna take another one inch brush,
dip it in liquid white.
I'm gonna go through the cad yellow,
be right back here,
a little sap green.
Pull the brush in one direction.
Loading it fully.
Lot of paint.
Look at all the paint.
Lot of paint on that brush.
Let's go up here.
Now,
gently push upward.
Just gently,
gently,
and turn the brush
to form all these individual little limbs
and branches.
Don't just push them all in one direction.
It'll look like you're lazy.
There.
Okay we can change the
flavor just a little bit
with some yellow ochre,
little Indian yellow.
Put another little thing right in there.
Just wherever, wherever.
Go back to the old two
inch brush that had all the
greens on it
and maybe
tap in just an indication,
some little grassy areas back in there.
Come right down here.
Somewhere in like in there.
Now,
let this one come right on out.
Wherever you want
and once again,
this is not an exact
duplicate of what you see
at the beginning of the show,
but it will show you
exactly the way it was made
and it may turn out better
than the one that you see
at the beginning of the show.
Who knows.
Okay we can take a little paint thinner,
a little brown.
Make it thin like ink
and we had,
let's see here.
We right here,
we'll have a nice little tree
that lives right up there.
There he goes.
In fact there was two of them.
Other one goes right
on over there somewhere
and then we can put all
kinds of little limbs
and sticks and twigs and
whatever you want on here.
There we go.
That's nice when you have a lot of time
and you can just sit and put all kinds of
little branches and sticks on here.
That's so pretty.
There.
Little bit more of the thinner.
Make that one a little fatter,
'cause he's the big guy.
Give this one a little more body
and we're in business.
There we go.
Now then,
let's have some fun.
Think it's time to take the tape off
and see what we have here.
Alright,
grab the old tape.
(tape peeling)
And just pull it right off there.
Okay and now we'll come back,
let's get this second one.
(tape peeling)
Pull it right off,
and isn't that neat?
Already we have all that stuff there done.
Okay.
There we go.
Tape gets stuck on everything.
Now then, now we can have some fun.
Now I like taking the liner brush.
Once again make that paint very thin
and let's go back over
and I wanna pull one of these
trees through this line.
It just,
just sort of makes it interesting.
Everybody will be interested in this.
When you do it this way.
It's so different.
There,
and then, now this one,
I don't wanna come through this one,
but over here I'm gonna bring it through
if that makes any sense at all.
So it looks like it looks like this one
is behind that line.
There.
Alright.
Now then.
You know me and my big trees here.
Let's take,
let's take the old fan brush.
Fill it up full of that dark, dark color
and go right up here.
I think there was a large tree that lived,
boy he does now.
Right there,
and just start,
corner of the brush,
working back and forth,
back and forth.
There.
Now the one that we show at the opening
has a naked spot right there. (laughs)
He didn't grow ant fir right there.
That's why they call them fir trees.
Okay.
Right on down,
letting go
and all we're doing is
putting in some background
color right now.
Now then he had a friend,
lived right there.
There we go.
See,
and I'm gonna let him project right out
clean over where the tape was.
So that'll push everything back.
This whole painting is a game of planes.
It's a lot of fun.
Lot of fun,
you'll enjoy it.
Tap in little bit of dark stuff here.
We can go back,
put the least little touch of highlight
on this big old tree.
Little green and yellow,
that's all we're using.
Something like that.
Take our one inch brush,
dip it in the liquid white,
go through our yellows,
greens,
and let's just make a happy
little bush or two down here
and we got it.
There.
See, little touch of the
yellow ochre here and there
just to break it up.
There we are.
But isn't that a
fantastic little painting?
Guarantee if you do this one,
it will certainly get people's attention.
They will love it
and I think with that we're
going to call this one finished.
From all of us here,
I'd like to wish you happy painting
and God bless my friend.
(upbeat music)