- Hi, welcome back.
Certainly glad you could join me today.
You know, we get hundreds and hundreds
of letters here concerning
the Joy of Painting.
And one of the things we
here over and over again
is people feel intimidated,
or they're a little nervous
about putting the first stroke on canvas.
So, I thought we'd devote
this entire show today
to teaching you how to
just sort of loosen up,
and take life easy, and enjoy painting.
We're gonna use a very limited palette,
and maybe I'll just use
something like a two inch brush
and maybe a palette knife.
Very simple, but I wanna
show you how to get
over this fear of your first painting.
So, let's have them run the colors
that I'm gonna use across the screen.
And let's just have some fun today.
Just drag out the old easy chair,
and get you a big glass of iced tea,
and kick back, and sort of enjoy this.
If you have your paintbrush out,
I invite you to paint along with us,
and I think you'll enjoy doing something
that's a little different.
It's very free, very
relaxed, and it gets you over
this tightness, or this
fear of your first painting.
So, I'm just putting a little
Liquid White on the canvas.
And basically here, all we're
looking for is just a nice
thin even coat, of the liquid
medium all the way across
the canvas.
This just makes the canvas wet and slick.
It's what allows color to blend on here,
and maybe we can really demonstrate today
how color blends on this Liquid White.
Now, this is a pre-stretched canvas.
It has give to it.
It's not a canvas board,
we don't recommend those.
Because they have cardboard in the center,
and what happens, they'll
absorb this Liquid White,
and very rapidly your
surface will become dry.
And it's no fun to paint on it anymore.
Because this is wet you
need it to stay that way.
All right, let's take
a little Yellow Ochre,
and I'm just gonna play today.
Let's just have fun.
A little Yellow Ochre.
Be right back, don't go away.
Little touch of the black into it.
Very little.
And we just make a light
little color, like so.
And we still have Liquid
White on the brush.
So, we're just letting that blend.
We're gonna make a very soft,
maybe a little muted
area in the background
back here.
And just play with color.
You know, maybe one of the hardest things
to do in painting is to
is to get over this fear of canvas.
It's natural.
And if it bothers you a
little bit to jump up here
and start throwing a bunch
of color on the canvas,
it means you're normal.
You're just like me and everybody
else that's every painted.
You go through this until
you get over this fear.
So, that's what we wanna
we wanna play with.
Then, we'll take a little
touch of the Prussian Blue.
So, this begins to get a
slight greenish hue to it,
but not much,
not much.
And let's just begin playing with color.
Just play, maybe we ought
to decide what season
it's gonna be, at least,
before we get too far involved.
And maybe something in the winter colors
that's always fun.
A little bit more of the Prussian Blue,
and black.
A little touch of Yellow Ochre,
but mostly just blue and black.
And just let these colors
sort of blend together
and play, and have fun.
But really and truly don't worry about it.
The way to learn how to paint
is to be relaxed and
enjoy, and just let it go.
Things work better for
you when you're relaxed,
and you're really happy
with what you're doing.
So, try to let it happen that way.
Maybe on this side, we'll
put a little bit more of that
there.
See, we just sort of let these
colors come together here,
like so.
But very loose.
Very loose.
There.
Okay.
And we let them go wherever.
Doesn't matter.
There we are.
But see, that easy.
You have a very nice little sky.
One of the best ways to do this,
nearly every time you do a painting
you're gonna have a
bunch of color left over.
This is a super, super way
of using up that old color,
and enjoying the freedom of just painting.
And just letting your
imagination run wild with you.
So, try this.
I'm serious, there's
nothing that I know of that
will teach you looseness more than this.
I want to make this side over
here a little bit darker.
See, and as you begin painting,
you begin seeing things.
All these little things
just sort of happen.
So now automatically we have a light area
over in here.
Just because we made these
sides a little darker.
I'll make it even a little
darker yet, what the heck.
This is our world, so we can do it any way
that we want.
We'll just make a little
cross criss strokes.
We'll do it backwards today.
There.
And very lightly, I'll just
sort of blend that out a little.
And we have all kinds of
things happening in this sky.
That simple.
And if you wanna blend it more,
just continue to blend.
You can make it as soft as silk or velvet,
just by doing that.
And maybe in our world,
maybe way back here in the background
maybe we can visualize
some little distant tree
indication.
Just take the brush, lay it like that,
give it a little gentle push.
But I want these to be very soft,
and very light.
Far away.
See?
Now, the other side.
These are just little indications
of things that are far
back here in the distance.
Far away.
Don't let them get too distinct.
Or you'll ruin that illusion
of distance in your painting.
And we're just gonna play here.
Enjoy this.
Let it go.
Let it happen.
Maybe there's another one right there.
I don't know.
Wherever you wanna.
But this is mainly a
little Midnight Black,
a little Prussian Blue,
and there's a touch of
Yellow Ochre left in it.
You can add maybe the least
little touch of Van Dyke Brown,
but the color should be
very soft and very muted
at this point.
Very soft and quiet.
Maybe this one goes way up here.
We don't know.
Just push harder if you
want it to look like
it's a bigger tree.
But this background idea is a way
to make very soft scenes that
you wanna show a lot of distance in.
And it's a very, very simple and effective
Okay, a little more of
the color on the brush.
Tell you what, maybe there's
a tree that lives right here.
Maybe this one, maybe this
one is sort of crooked.
And it goes all the way off the canvas.
Who cares?
In your world, you can make
it any way that you want it.
These are just, once
again, distant indications
of things that are happening.
Very soft and muted, quiet
peaceful little places.
This is where all the little
creatures live and have fun.
There.
Some of them you can hardly see in there.
They're so far away.
There, maybe.
There we are.
Let's see, we said this
was going to be winter.
So, we need to keep that in mind.
I'll mess around here,
and forget what season
I said it was gonna be.
There we go.
Now then, down here at the base
we're still using the same colors.
The same ol' colors.
We can tap in a few little happy bushes
that live right down in here.
This is just a tiny bit darker.
So, it indicates that
it's a little closer.
Now, if this is our light source here
less pressure on the brush.
Let it get lighter, and lighter.
Very gentle.
Just sort of fade right into that.
Where you want it to be darker,
just get a little tougher.
Push,
and let it go right off there somewhere.
There we go.
Maybe over in here
Tell you what, maybe
maybe there's a few little trees that,
yep you're right,
live right here.
Just little indications of little things.
See, and you can just turn the
brush in different directions
to create all types of effects.
There.
And just sort of look at it once again.
This is such a fantastic way of painting
because you have no
you don't trace a painting up here,
and you don't have any guidelines.
The only thing that restricts
you here is your imagination.
Just your imagination, nothing else.
And imagination is like anything else,
it's like a muscle in your body,
if you practice with it, you
exercise your imagination
it gets stronger.
Very soon, you're able to
visualize more and more things
in your mind.
So, use it.
God gave you this gift.
Take advantage of it.
We may be the only creature on Earth that
has a vivid imagination.
There.
Then again, we may not.
I don't know.
Don't know that it matters.
There.
And we'll start adding
Mmm, we'll take a little more
of the black, and the blue,
Van Dyke Brown, maybe a little
tough of the Dark Sienna
here and there.
But as we work forward, I
want this color to begin
getting a little darker.
And see, I'm just loading the brush
by just going back and forth.
Doesn't matter how you load it.
Doesn't matter.
There, a little blue, and
black, a little Van Dyke Brown.
All those beautiful, beautiful colors.
Now, then maybe
watch here.
See, all you gotta do is take
this brush and push upward,
like that to make.
Look at that.
See, that easy you can
make the illusion of little
grassy areas back in here.
Just like so.
Shoot, maybe we'll have some over here.
And we're gonna sort of
change the lay of the land
here a little.
So, it has some interesting
things happening in here,
it's not just all the same.
Let these little things just happen.
There.
All kinds of little doers.
Maybe over in here again.
See, you begin seeing these little doers.
But just pushing upward,
bend the brush very hard.
You're not gonna hurt the brush.
But it makes all these little
grassy looking effects.
They're very simple, and you can do them.
I know you can do them.
'Cause you can do anything
that you wanna do.
As long as you can believe you can do it.
Anything that you believe you can do,
you really can do.
Let's take a two inch brush.
And I have several two inch brushes,
so I don't have to spend
all of my time here
just washing brushes.
Just gonna pull through a little
bit of that Titanium White.
This is gonna be winter, maybe.
Maybe in our world there's a
little snow laying back here.
But I want the snow to
reflect some shadows
from whatever it is we have in here.
So, go up into the color
a little, and grab it,
and begin pulling.
Now, watch here, let's
just mess something up.
If you mess up the top of this one,
don't worry about it.
You can either completely wipe it out,
or you can go back and
very simply drop it in.
'Cause you know, if you've
painted with me before,
we don't make mistakes,
we have happy accidents.
Because there's nothing that
you can do on this canvas
that with a little practice you can't fix.
Think about the lay of the land now.
Watch here.
Let me grab this other old brush.
You can go right back in here.
See here?
And pop that right back in.
And that's nice because
now it looks like there's
snow behind it.
See?
These little things work for you.
See you could put one over here
like that.
See, and it looks like
there's snow back in there.
There, and you can make
this just as smooth
and peaceful.
Maybe, we'll grab that.
See, we got quite of bit of color there.
That's nice, that'll make
a very nice shadow area.
There, and just sort of bring it together.
This old two inch brush will just do
wonderful things for you.
Just fantastic things.
Now, already though look
at the depth in here.
And you've really done nothing.
You've really done nothing except just
take a two inch brush and play a little.
Let's take that same color we're using,
take a little paint
thinner on the liner brush.
Maybe we'll have a few little
sticks and twigs in there.
Maybe a few.
Just pull this out.
Turn it, so it brings it to
a very sharp point, okay.
Now, we want these to be
very subdued and quiet.
We don't want these to be too bright.
Too strong.
Very subdued.
There, a few little things
that live back in here.
Ooo, that's what I'm looking for.
You almost can't see
them, but they're there.
They're there, you'll see them.
There.
See?
And just pick out where you
think a little twig would live,
and drop it in,
drop it in.
So, now I mentioned we get
a lot of letters from people
who are a little nervous about
trying their first painting.
We also get a lot of letters
from people who are painting,
and they're doing some
of the most fantastic
things imaginable.
Maybe in this series we'll show you some.
But people who have never painted,
just from watching the
show have picked up a brush
and they're doing marvelous things.
And maybe more important
than the painting,
is the fact that they can do it.
Is the fact that you can
achieve a creative process
like this.
And it's a nice way of
oh, I think everybody has sort
of an urge to be creative,
and it's a nice way of
letting that urge come out
and it's so enjoyable.
That's one of the reasons
we like to show you.
Shoot, let's get crazy I
talk too much sometime.
Let's go back into some
of our blue, and black,
get a little brown, be right back here.
Well, see I'm gonna have
a little more brown,
a little Dark Sienna.
I may even reach over here
and get the least little
touch of Alizarin Crimson.
Oh nice, nice.
Now, if your color gets too dark on you,
or you think it's too dark,
you can reach right over
pick up a little white,
and lighten it up.
Because you can do anything.
Let's load the brush up.
Tell you what, let's
load it to a chisel edge.
Let's really have some fun.
Chisel edge, turn it
around here so you can see
how sharp that is.
See, it comes to a
beautiful sharp chisel edge.
There we go.
But you must put enough
paint into the bristles
to stick the bristles together
to make the chisel edge.
Let's go back up here.
Maybe in our world there
lives a little tree,
or a big tree.
Maybe this is a big tree.
And we can, if it helps, you
can put in a little center line
like that.
Get a little more color here.
Now then, think about
where you would have nice
branches living here.
Just take the corner of the brush,
and just put out a branch here and there.
Just let them go.
And maybe they aren't all just even.
Maybe these aren't all
potential Christmas trees.
They're just trees that grew any way that
they wanted to grow.
All evergreen trees are not
gonna be Christmas tress,
some of them's gonna be crooked,
some of them's gonna be sort of,
they gonna be sort of poor.
There.
A little more paint.
Now, just to have a general
idea of where we're going,
and let's just take the corner
of the brush, once again.
There.
Just tap in some very basic little shapes.
There we go.
Maybe even we can see a little
touch of the trunk here.
Who cares?
This is your world, you do it
any way that you wanna do it.
So, maybe this tree had
a bad year right in here.
It didn't grow too hot.
Maybe when he was little
maybe some hungry creature decided to chew
on him a little bit.
We don't know.
Don't know that we even care.
Okay, now as the trees come closer,
they should get a little darker.
So, I'm gonna add a little bit
more of that Prussian Blue,
and a little Van Dyke Brown, Dark Sienna.
But they begin taking on a darker tone.
Black, blue, brown.
There we are.
Sounds like my body condition
when I stay out too late.
Black, blue, and brown, that's
what I get when I get home.
There we go.
Maybe in our world there
lives another little tree,
right there.
Okay.
We'll just let these little
trees just fall right
off the brush.
Wherever,
wherever.
Doesn't matter.
Black, blue, and brown.
This one goes all the way off the canvas.
What the heck.
He's a strong tall tree.
But if you practice this
painting very loose.
You will not believe, number one,
what you can do.
Secondly, it'll create a
looseness, and a freedom
in your painting that you've
never experienced before.
And I think you will find
that's very refreshing.
Very, very, refreshing in your painting.
I have a lot of people who
have painted for many years
that take classes with
me, and my son Steve,
and the other teachers that we have,
and they take classes
in this technique mainly
to learn to be loose with their painting.
Because it's very easy
to get tight, and stiff,
and used to staying in the lines,
and just drawing little pictures,
and following those.
This will give you freedom.
Absolute freedom.
There, let's go to the other side here.
Little blue, black, back
to our brown, Dark Sienna,
just mix them together.
There, wiggle that brush though
that brings the paint right up to the end.
We need to make it sharp.
All right.
Maybe look at what a
sharp line that is now.
See how sharp you can make that line?
Now then, just the corner of the brush.
Let's put in some little
things here and there.
See that?
You can do this.
You really can do this.
There.
Let's give him a friend.
You know me.
I think everything, and everybody
should have a friend.
Friends may be the most
valuable commodities
that we have.
Treasure them, take care
of them, treat them good.
There we are.
Now maybe, look just push upward.
See?
Maybe there's a whole
'nother thing that comes
right out like that.
Just by pushing up with the brush,
you can create that illusion.
Just by giving a little upward push.
Let's go back to the brush that has some
white on it.
And with that, let's come back in here,
and we lay in a little snow.
Once again, pick up some
of this color though,
and drag it out there.
Get tough with it.
Because the canvas is wet,
you can move this color.
If this was a dry canvas,
you might be able to move it,
but it would be very difficult
and you'd work yourself
half to death trying to do it.
There we go.
Maybe on this side, once again though,
figure out how the lay
of the land is here.
How the
how it flows.
And it's sort of nice to
have a little recessed area
right in here.
It just gives you a nice
place for the animals to walk,
and just good things to happen.
But any of these little
bushes and stuff here that
you don't like, you
just lay snow over them.
Just like nature does.
So there.
Look at that.
Now then, we can take
some of that same color
on our knife and here and there,
if you wanted to, you
could add the indication
of a little stronger trunk.
Depends on what you're looking for.
Once again, very loose,
very relaxed.
Just let it go.
This is fun painting.
There.
You know, this would be a super place
to have a little cabin.
Let's do that.
I think we have enough time.
And a lot of people have
problems with a cabin,
so let me show you.
Let's go right up in here.
Decide where your cabin lives,
and let's just scrape out
a very basic little shape.
Maybe we'll have a big cabin in here,
it shows up better.
See, just take the knife and
scrape out your basic shape.
Now, right there's where there
is where the stretcher bar
is don't worry about
that, we'll cover that up.
Now, one of the things
that you're looking for
when you're doing a cabin
is your perspective.
If you're gonna have a cabin, like so,
one of the most important
things you can do
is have this part of the
roof a little bit higher
than the back.
Otherwise, it won't look right.
Try to keep that a little bit higher.
If you put that a little lower,
which is almost a natural tendency,
it'll look like your cabin is sort of
well maybe the front of
it fell down into a hole.
I live in Florida, and sometimes there's,
we have sinkholes there.
And it almost looks like your
cabin fell into a sinkhole.
See there, all right.
Let's just put a little
We'll just Dark Sienna,
and Van Dyke Brown,
mostly Van Dyke Brown.
And let's just lay in.
All I'm doing is laying in some color now.
Just laying in some color.
There.
You could do this with a cement
trowel, it doesn't matter.
A little something like that.
See, and the bottom at this point
don't be concerned with.
Because you can come along
here with your knife,
and do a cabin-ectomy,
and decide exactly where
everything should live.
That easy.
And maybe, we said this
was gonna be a log cabin,
or something that gives you
the impression of a log cabin.
So, we'll take a little brown, and white,
and let's just come along in here.
And think about this angle right here.
And let's just tap in
some little indications
here and there.
See there.
All right.
Okay, just drop it in.
There.
We can take that dark color
that we picked up earlier,
and go back,
and help create that illusion.
There.
Over in here, this is gonna
be very dark on this side.
We don't want much color over here.
Think I'll put a tree
there, what the heck.
Put the indication of the end of the logs.
Just using the point of the knife.
That easy.
Maybe we got a door in here,
let's put a little door.
We gotta have a way to get in and out.
That's all there is to it.
Put in a little door.
A little light around the door.
Now, we need a little
Let's put a little snow
up here on the roof.
See there.
But just pull it down.
Just pull down.
We said we'd have a tree in front of it,
so we don't have to
worry much about the back
of it at this point.
We do need a little bit
of snow over on this side.
Just so there's snow on both sides.
Now then, let me go back to my brush here.
Let's take, watch how
you can move the trees,
let's take some of our
brown, and black, and blue,
a little Dark Sienna.
Okay, and let's go back up here.
Now maybe, let's take
this tree right here,
right here,
and let's make a big decision.
This tree lives on this side of the cabin.
See, how you can change your mind?
You can pull this tree right over here
in front.
That easy.
On this canvas, you have unlimited power.
Now then, maybe
See there a little
grass growing over here.
Maybe a little right in here.
Whatever.
Let's take our brush with the white on it,
come right up to the bottom of the cabin.
There we go.
Put a little snow right in there.
Watch here, watch here, watch here,
touch, push.
Bend, bend the bristles.
Just do this in layers.
Continually in layers though.
Grab the bottom,
give it a little pull.
Like that.
See how that just all comes together?
Shoot, tell you what maybe,
maybe there's a little sprig
right here.
And that way it looks like
there's stuff behind it.
There.
Shoot, I'll tell you what,
let's go on the other side
over here.
Maybe over here, in our world there lives,
well there does now,
maybe there's a little doer
that lives right out here.
Now then, once again, take
a little Titanium White,
grab that, and just let it flow.
See there?
That easy.
Maybe...
See, how you can break that up,
and it creates the
illusion of depth in there.
Shoot, we messed around here,
and about have a painting
that's not half bad.
And I was just going to
show you how to relax,
and enjoy this.
But I really hope you
try something like this,
because it's a great deal of fun.
It teaches you how to use the equipment,
it gives you confidence with equipment.
And once you have the confidence,
then you can do anything.
You can do anything.
We'll put a few little
sticks, here and there.
There's one.
And you can just go
around it, here and there,
and tap in a few,
like that.
That's really all there is to it.
Wherever you think they should be.
And I think we'll call this finished.
I really hope you've
enjoyed this experiment,
and I hope you try it.
Let me hear from you.
From all of us here,
happy painting,
and God bless.
(mellow guitar music)