Hey welcome back I'm glad you could join
me today today I have a very special
treat for you I'm very proud to present
my son Steve Steve's a fantastic artist
that we send all over the country to
teach the joy of painting and I've asked
him to come in today and to show you
what he can do in just a couple of
minutes so we're going to turn the show
over to Steve I'll be back at the end of
the show and see what you've done thanks
Dan well I've already covered the canvas
with a thin even coating of liquid white
and the way I'm going to start out today
is just touching the brush into a little
bit of a lizard and crimson and bringing
it out into a separate space on the
palate just tapping it straight down
turn your brush over tap tap
now when the alizarin crimson hits the
liquid white it will turn a pink color
it won't look like it does on the palate
so I'm just going to start right in
using horizontal strokes but holding the
brush sideways instead of the
traditional flat way like this this
gives you a little bit more movement in
your sky
and with that same dirty brush can get a
little bit more alizarin crimson
and maybe a touch of phthalo blue and
I'll come right up here to the left-hand
corner and you just kind of bring that
right down under the alizarin and always
keep your corners the darkest because
your sons coming from the center of this
painting maybe a tiny bit of light blue
in the center and a little bit more blue
and alizarin and we'll go up into this
corner and make a real dark to
and we'll pick up a little bit more that
and throw some water in real quick while
we got it on the brush it's important
that you use mostly the same colors
throughout the whole painting it
captures the eye better if you do if you
use 70 different colors in one painting
it usually doesn't look too good and I
might even throw a little reflection in
the center there now that we got all our
shapes in here I'll go back with a clean
brush and just blend that out blending
the alizarin first because once you hit
blue with your brush it'll destroy any
alizarin it hits always using that X
that's what gives you that movement if I
was just to brush it straight back and
forth across that just be one solid
color
and since your corners are real dark
make sure you blend them real firmly the
more pressure you add on the brush the
more the paint will move for you and do
a little hypnotizing and come down here
in the water just pulling this all
straight in okay now I'm going to use my
fan brush and just going through a
little bit of titanium white and you can
add a touch of a lizard into that maybe
make your clouds kind of pink
now this painting is going to have big
clouds and it won't start one right here
sometimes you don't want such a bold
looking cloud and if you didn't you'd
use a probably number three fan brush
rather than a number six like I'm using
it's really your choice little clouds
big clouds whichever you prefer and
that's what you do if you get it here in
your cloud
clouds are usually real flat on the
bottom and nice and puffy on top if you
remember that you really can't go wrong
on clouds now with my big brush
preferably a clean one I'll blend the
bottom of the cloud out I never touched
the top of the cloud that's where you
want the most of your highlight to stay
and just pull up on it a tiny bit this
is real light three hairs and some air
as my dad would say and hypnotized it
okay and that about does it for the sky
now I'm going to take my pallet knife I
go through a little bit of brown and a
little bit of a lizard and a little bit
of blue kind of stripe them out like
that into three different piles then
take a little bit from each one and put
them together in the center and mix that
together real good kind of gives you a
dark purple color and will come right up
here and make a big bold mountain now
it's important that you don't kind of
linger around here and and mess around
with the shape too much because it
really doesn't matter as long as you
have three or four peaks the highlight
is what really counts it's what really
makes your mountain
probably the thing I would want to tell
you to stay away from right here is
getting too much paint on the mountain
you want to scrape it all the way down
to bare canvas and then go back in with
your big brush and pull it out and that
way you get some of this paint glow down
here to mix in with the mountain
sometimes whether you do it on purpose
or not it's good to leave a real dark
line in back of the mountain because
that kind of makes it look like a super
super dark shadow when you're doing
putting the highlights and shadows on
sometimes that just turns out as a happy
accident it usually just ends if they're
on purpose in other words and all I'm
doing is just getting a roll of paint on
the knife like this just pull it out
flat go straight through and you get
your roll and touching and just barely
just as light as a feather pulling
and I've got a tiny bit of a loser in
there just like in the clouds
and maybe this mountain will have a big
Valley and it you ever see that show the
big Valley that's where this mountain
comes from now I'm going to mix up a
little bit of shadow color and to do
that you just use the base color that
you use for the mountain a little bit of
white and some Prussian blue now you get
a roll on your knife just like you did
with the white except this time you push
up into the white a little bit and pull
away from it and that drags some of that
light out onto the shadow side of the
mountain too so it doesn't just look
like it's split directly down the center
push up and pull
it gets kind of tight right in these
curves and the valleys right there and
you have to come back and clean that up
a little bit sometimes see like right
around this edge I don't want to come
back
and maybe over here we'll have a tiny
little glacier and that need how you can
just decide what you want in a painting
and just put it right in there
makes it so easy just like my dad I use
little brushes for a long time before I
ever started using big ones and it's
just there's no comparison at all too
much too much pedaling around with
little stuff okay throw a shadow behind
that and we're just about ready to make
our mist
and to do that we take our big brush tap
tap tap tap with the angle of the
mountain and pull up with the angle and
if you have a shadow crossing over your
light like right here then you can come
back and put one or two little strokes
there because obviously you can't have a
shadow casting a highlight okay now with
my one-inch brush I'll take a little bit
of our base color brown alizarin blue
and mix those all together and maybe
I'll even throw a tad a SAP green in
there and to that you mix white
probably the ugliest color you could get
at this point would be the best one to
use because ugly colors look more
natural in a painting than real bright
flashy colors you know see what I mean
here in a minute
now without destroying the mist you have
on the mountain you just want to tap in
a shape kind of a rolling yellow shape
don't make it any harder than it is
though just as easy as it looks
just splattering it right in and with a
clean brush I'll come back and lift that
up just maybe a quarter of an inch right
on the top and this gives you the
illusion of little trees in the
background
now if you don't pull it straight up
it'll look like grass and we're
definitely too far away to be seeing
grass now when you get down in here just
pull all this up and then take the edge
of your brush and smash in and this will
create mist down at the bottom you can
pull that up now with that same dirty
brush I used for the first foothill I'll
add a little bit more Brown and blue
always makes your paint on your brush so
you can get a marbled effect in your
color if you mix it up with a knife and
you just have one flat color and you
don't usually see that in nature
and try to keep your shapes a little bit
different on this one and like before
pull this up if you want to get really
realistic about it then you should pull
these trees up a tiny bit higher than
the last row because they are getting a
tiny bit closer to you
I've been traveling around teaching
classes since I was about 15 years old I
started out with my dad and by the time
I was 17 I was teaching my own classes
and I'll tell you one of the biggest
things about teaching painting is not
really the teaching of it but what you
get out of the teaching of it and what
you get out of the teaching of it is
practice of course when you go into a
classroom and teach people how to paint
you might do 30 paintings worth of
bushes or something trying to show them
exactly how to do it
so sometimes teaching can be a way to
learn now over here on the left side I
think I'll throw in a bushy tree
and what trees are is just a lot of
bushes in one so you make each
individual bush and kind of bring them
all together see how this is a bush here
and this is one here and this is one
here I'll just kind of bring a row of
grass that's a little bit darker right
in front of the foothill and you want to
kind of make it come around like this so
that when I pull the reflections out
it'll look like this is around the bend
or something it leads the eye into the
painting rather than out of the painting
if I had the land going up like this
then you'd want to just have your eye go
right out now I'm going to put in a
little trunk this is just using Van Dyck
Brown just touching and the way I'm
doing that is just getting a tiny rule
paint and touching the canvas real
lightly down here at the bottom of
course the trunk is going to be a little
bit fatter to hold up that top part and
maybe a little bit of highlight on that
I'll just use a little bit of brown and
white together
just kind of pulling across the brown
letting the thick areas pick up the
light this will be an old birch tree and
with the same and dirty brush you used
to make the tree you can go into a
little bit of paint thinner and threw
some cadmium yellow just kind of pulling
through the paint until you start to see
little bushes in the paint like right
there and that's when you know you're
ready to turn the brush over where that
heals to the top and come in and just
barely touch sometimes it looks like
we're taking a run and jumping leaf and
smashing it in but we're really not
we're just doing it real lightly
and remember where your light source is
coming from it's coming from over here
so you don't want this side of the tree
over here to be darker and don't bring
leaves all the way down to the bottom of
the tree there now with that same color
well I've already got it on my brush
I'll go out here and make a few little
bushes one here and one there you don't
want to make them all the same color
so I'll take a little bit more paint
thinner still using that same dirty
brush you can almost get away with not
ever cleaning the brushes if you do it
just right this is yellow ochre I'm
using now not the prettiest color but
like I said at the beginning of the
painting all colors aren't supposed to
be pretty and maybe some Indian yellow
there's a little trick that I teach my
students when I'm not traveling around
if you're going to put any sort of red
in your painting then you want to put it
in the center because the eyes always
must attract it to the brightest color
and if you put red in a painting then
obviously it's going to be the brightest
color I like to mix red and Indian
yellow it gives you a real fire color
and you don't need but maybe one of
these are one little teeny idea of red
you can see how much difference that
makes now underneath all of this stuff
hanging over the water will drop a
little land and you do that just by
getting a roll like you did for the
mountain and touching and then pulling
and sometimes you can even pull and then
drop over like this that gives a real
good effect
still keeping that round Bend look and
to highlight that we use that same old
brown of white color maybe with a tiny
bit of blue in it and I'm just letting
the white pick up on the brown where
it's real thick and real dense and it's
important that you let some Brown come
up into your bushes and stuff too so I
can come back with a fan brush and a
little bit of yellow on it maybe a drop
of paint thinner to thin that down and
make some grasses
okay now I take my big brush and pull
just a tiny bit of this out just barely
grabbing the edge of the land and see is
the land gets bigger so does a
reflection naturally so when you get all
the way over here pull it all the way
down to the bottom and then you can use
a clean brush or semi clean in this case
to go back and forth make it look more
like water and now I'm ready to make my
dreaded water line this is where I run
into more problems when I'm teaching
everybody has problems with their water
line you pull it out flat like I did
there and you cut across it and what
you're doing is just getting a real fine
line white on the edge of your knife and
then you're cutting it straight in
almost like you're trying to cut a hole
through the canvas and keep it straight
all the way around the bend I know that
sounds hard and you'll have a tendency
to want to put in a sideways line but
don't ever do it always keep it straight
okay and maybe right over here we'll
have one big huge pine tree and pine
trees are real easy you just kind of
make them in a in a zigzag shape see
just kind of zigzag it right down a lady
in one of my dance classes used to call
these Z trees because you make it
basically like a Z and here maybe a bush
or two now with that same dirty fan
brush you can go in and put a little bit
of highlight on your tree and see how
that dirty color you had on there mixes
with the yellow and makes kind of a
green that's what you're looking for and
not every branch but maybe every third
branch or every second branch you want a
little bit of highlight and a small
trunk maybe let's see
and to finish it up some real bright
bushes up front well as thieves finish
to this painting up I would like to come
in here and thanks to you very much for
demonstrating the joy of painting today
and we look forward to seeing you again
so from Steve and I happy painting and
God bless bye bye
you