(light music)
- Welcome back.
Certainly glad to see you today.
I thought today we'd do
a painting that's just,
it's a lot of fun, very simple,
and I think you'll enjoy it.
So let's start out and have them
run all the colors across the screen
that you need to paint
this with me at home.
While they're doing that,
let me show you what I
got going up here today.
I have my standard old,
well, I'm using an 18 by 24 inch canvas,
but you use any size that you like
and all I've done is
covered the entire canvas
with a very, very...
Let me say it one more time.
A very thin coat of liquid clear.
Now, the clear's on here
just to make the canvas
wet and slick
and that's really the
only reason it's there.
Be careful when you're using this clear
because you can't see it up here hardly.
It's hard to,
it's hard to tell if you have enough.
If you have any doubt...
Because usually, you put too much on.
If you have any doubt,
take a paper towel and wipe it down.
What's left will be just right.
It's better to have too litte
than it is to have too much.
You just wanna make the
paint slide on there.
Let's have fun today.
The old two-inch brush.
And I'm gonna use very, very little color.
Pull the smallest little amount,
smallest little amount
of the blue out here.
Little, tiny bit of blue.
Very small amount.
Let's go up in here.
Now,
very gently
I'm just going to begin
applying some color up here in the sky.
I want the...
Let's do a winter scene today.
So,
let's make it very soft,
very misty.
One of those winter...
Tell you what,
let's get crazy.
Let's get crazy today.
Let's have a...
Maybe a few little buildings down here
like a little farm scene or something.
I don't know.
Just sort of do it and see what happens.
It doesn't matter
because as you know,
in our world, we don't make mistakes.
We just have happy accidents.
It's the only world I live in
where there's no mistakes at all.
That's what makes it so wonderful.
Very little color.
Shoot, while I got that going,
let's just keep going.
Maybe we'll just
put a little bit of this blue all over.
We're gonna have a winter scene
and we're gonna need
some shadows in our snow,
so by applying a little blue down here,
we'll use that later on.
Automatically, this
will become our shadows.
And if worst comes to
worst, what the heck?
We'll turn it into a nice lake or pond or
whatever we want.
Doesn't matter.
That's what's so nice about this.
You can change your mind right mid-stream.
Okay, fun time.
Fun time.
Let's wash the brush.
As you know,
we wash our brush with
odorless paint thinner.
Shake it off.
And just beat the devil out of it.
Now, let's go back
with titanium white.
First of all, the prussian
blue is transparent.
It's very transparent.
Now, I'm gonna go into an opaque color.
The titanium white
and it is very opaque.
Very opaque.
Just a little color on here,
and let's go up in here
and let's just play a little bit.
Let's just pick out some areas
like this.
We want this painting, as I say, to be
very soft, very gentle
quiet little painting.
I don't want a strong,
distinct sky here that,
that,
will be distracting.
I want a very gentle,
quiet little sky.
And so that's what we shall have.
There.
In our world, we can create
any illusion that we want.
And today,
I want softness in our world.
Tranquility, quiet.
Peaceful.
Shoot, there's too much bad
stuff going on in our world.
We're gonna have a very peaceful place.
Everybody's happy,
even the little creatures.
There we are.
That's really, that's
really about all I want
for this sky.
I don't wanna do much more than that.
Something about like that.
And I get to wash the brush again.
All right.
I really, really just
wanted to wash the brush.
Shake it off.
(laughs)
You know they...
If you're gonna do this at home,
I suggest you get a little
thing called a brush meter rack.
It goes down in a garbage can,
'cause if you do this in your living room,
you're not gonna be very popular.
Guarantee.
All right.
Let's go into a little black.
Very small amount of blue,
but there's very little paint.
Very little paint here,
and I just wanna
tap in some little indications,
barely touching the canvas.
Little indications far away,
far away,
almost the same color as the sky.
Very light, far away.
Remember that.
I keep saying it because it's important.
Now, you can take this...
I wanna blend the edges
out so it just disappears.
Just sort of disappears softly.
Softly.
I don't do a lot of soft
paintings on television
'cause they don't show up quite as well,
but I thought today,
we'll do one anyway.
There.
Softly.
Blending those edges out a little bit
so it just sort of disappears.
If you want to make this
sort of look like it just,
I don't know, like it sort of flows,
almost like a watercolor,
leave a little more paint
thinner on your brush
because paint thinner and liquid clear,
they have a violent reaction
and it'll sort of just
grow and it's beautiful.
Looks like watercolor.
There.
Something about like that.
That's a little background
or something that's way back here.
We don't even care where it's at.
Far away.
Let's have one in the foreground,
a little closer to us.
We'll use the same color,
only a little more paint
and I'll add the least,
least little touch of
Van Dyke brown to it.
But there's still not a great
deal of paint on the brush.
Not a great deal. Let's go up in here.
Tell you what, let me show you something.
I'm gonna take
just the least little
touch of paint thinner.
Remember I told you that paint thinner
and liquid clear have a violent reaction.
Wipe off all the excess. Don't want much.
Then we just sort of tap
all these colors together
and
right here,
let's just begin tapping in
some basic little shapes.
Very, very basic.
There's paint thinner in here.
Not a lot.
I wiped all of it off, as you
saw, that I could get off,
but I didn't beat the brush.
So there's still some in here.
We're just putting indication
of all kinds of little things
that live up in here.
There.
All right.
What's the old saying?
You don't have to be crazy
to do this, but it helps.
Sometimes it does.
You really...
This is where you enjoy freedom on canvas.
Just let things happen. Let them happen.
There.
Now, this will continue
to dilute the paint thinner.
Will continue to dilute the liquid clear
and you'll get reactions
maybe for several hours.
It'll be very slight,
but it'll be a little bit different.
Let me show you. Watch here.
You can even take a little
paint thinner on the
fan brush and flick it.
Look at that! Look at that!
Isn't that gorgeous?
Look at those effects.
It makes one of the neatest
little nicest things
and all you gotta do...
See? Just flick it.
And you can use the knife to flick it
or I'm just using the side
of the palette, whatever.
Doesn't matter.
But that'll continue to work.
It looks...
Once again, it looks like a watercolor.
All right.
Let's put another little
bush. Same colors.
Just tapping.
Each layer gets a little bit darker
as it gets closer to us.
And maybe in our world,
there's one more little tree
lives right here.
We don't know.
Don't know that we even care
at this point in our life.
There. Just make all
kinds of little things.
Okay.
Yep, there's another one there.
Here's one here.
Sometimes you can just
take and push sidewards,
create all kind of little illusions here.
Is that another one?
Then I'll take it and pull it.
Lift it.
See there?
Pull those little things out.
That paint thinner
and clear will continue to
work for a while once again.
I like these kind of little paintings.
They're so soft.
So nice.
They're very moody little paintings.
Yeah, there we are.
Okay.
And that gives us a fairly
good little background.
You can enhance that a little,
taking a little paint thinner,
a little pit of white paint.
Put a little blue in it too
just to dull it a little.
And maybe, in our world,
maybe they're some little tree trunks
that live up through here.
Just a few.
There we are.
See?
You can pull it down, you can lift it up.
Whatever works well for you.
Few little things in here.
You can actually just
take plain paint thinner
and do this.
It'll lift the paint off the canvas,
and you can get basically the same effect
by just allowing the
canvas to show through.
There.
All kinds of little doers happening.
Now, we decided early
that this was gonna be winter.
Let's get the bravery test out here.
We'll go right into titanium white.
Titanium white. Let's go up in here.
Where is the snow?
The easiest way there ever was
to make snow.
There.
Just like it.
And it goes (makes painting
noise) right on across.
I don't know.
Now see, intentionally,
I went around this tree.
Now it looks like this tree is forward.
Does that make any sense?
I hope I'm saying that
right so you understand.
Sometimes I get so excited, I,
I don't say things right.
But that's just a neat effect, ain't it?
Look at that.
It's setting down in the snow.
Right out there.
Let's see.
We decided we was gonna have
some buildings out here.
Maybe one of the easiest ways
that I've found to make a building
is take the knife,
and just firmly
scrape out a basic shape.
It does two things.
Most important, it removes excess paint.
Secondly, it allows you
to lay out your buildings.
Let's put a shed on
this one. What the heck?
Maybe that's an old
barn with a shed on it.
Like it.
But you can lay out a
whole series of buildings.
Maybe there're more than one.
Right there.
We don't care.
Without being committed, anyway,
that's what I'm trying to say.
You're not committed at this point.
There.
Let's take a little Van
Dyke, little dark cyan,
and mix it together.
Van Dyke and dark cyan.
I'm just gonna use them together.
And now, we can figure out here
where the dark part is.
And in my world, I think it's right here.
You don't have to stay in the
lines that you scraped out.
You can go anywhere you want with this.
There are no rules here other than
it should make you happy,
and whatever works, is good.
Whatever works.
Painting is such an individual thing.
Every person who's ever painted
has a different opinion of why it works
and how it should work,
but I believe
that it's an individual thing,
and if you're happy with your painting,
then the world's happy with it.
What's the old saying about
if you smile, the world
smiles with you and all that?
Same thing here.
We were gonna have a shed here. Forgot.
There.
Now, we can come back.
Still using a knife,
take a little bit of paint,
and maybe,
maybe this building here is straight on.
Let me get a little more paint there.
Straight on toward us.
And sort of allow that to break sometimes.
Makes it looks like the
snow sorta sliding down.
(makes sliding sounds)
Straight down.
Woops, got a little
doer hanging off there.
There.
All right.
A little bit more here
for the little shed.
There he is.
Looks like icicles right there already.
There.
Something about like it.
And that's quick enough
to give us an idea of a little building.
And we take a little
brown and a little white,
mix them together.
Little brown, little white.
Ooh, that's nice.
Don't overmix.
Touch.
Just pull gently down.
In my mind, I think this little shed
is not gonna get as much light,
so it's gonna be a
little darker back here.
So I'll make it a little darker
so he's pushed back a little more.
I think in my mind this side of the house
will be a little lighter than the front
or the barn, whatever this is.
I don't know what it is.
Whatever you want it to be.
A little more brown in there.
This side over here now is
very dark in comparison.
It's sorta, this is sorta
like a three-quarter view.
All right.
Clean off the knife.
Choose a little edge
and maybe there's a few
little windows in here.
Just doop, doop,
three...
There.
See? Whole line of little windows.
Maybe the cows live in here
and need a place to look out.
They wanna see what's
happening out here too.
There.
We'll put a couple
little windows in there.
It's your world.
You decide what's in there and what's not.
As I've mentioned many times before,
I sort of make up little
stories in my mind.
I'm just pulling a little
brown through there
to make it look like old
boards living in there.
But these little stories,
they really help me.
I don't know if they'll help you,
but I believe they will.
Make up little stories about your world.
Boy, that's some rough looking snow there.
Old snow laying up there.
We need snow on this other building.
(makes swooping noises)
There we are.
Little bit there.
All right.
Now, sometimes when you
have the clear there
this doesn't want to stick too good.
If that's the case, add
a little liquid white
to make your paint a little thinner.
Then it'll stick.
It's all you have to do.
Over here on this side,
put a little snow out there.
Little touch of brown, for
the eve or the overhang.
Like it.
Shoot.
We're 'bout to have an old building there.
And I want these to look like they've,
they've had a rough life.
Real rough life.
We'll take our big brush.
Little bit of snow right there.
Make a little shadow in the snow.
All we have to do is put a
little blue in there for that.
Little darker blue.
All right.
Over here (makes swooping noise).
Cut that off like that.
The side like it.
Now we're in business.
So we have two little buildings out here.
Little bit more of the blue color.
I put some blue down here,
but it's not as dark as I want it to be.
I want it to be a little bit darker.
So I'll just add a little more,
because in our world, we can
add anything that we want.
There.
Over in here.
You know,
a couple of shows ago,
I've mentioned something about this easel.
We have a brand new easel in this series.
And we've been absolutely flooded
with requests wanting
to know more about it.
What can I tell you?
It's a very unique easel.
The greatest thing about it
is the top comes off and
makes a tabletop easel.
It has four legs.
Most tabletop easels have three.
When you use a brush this big, you hit it,
they fall over.
That's always been a problem,
so we designed an easel
that has four legs
for the tabletop.
Then the nice thing about
it, you can order it
with just the top.
You just want a tabletop.
Then maybe later on you decide
you wanna get serious about it.
You can go back and order the bottom
and they go right together.
There.
And it...
It's available
I think it most better art stores
across the country.
If you can't find one, drop me a line.
I'll find out where they
are and let you know.
Okay.
Take a little blue, little white,
mix them together.
Maybe in our world...
Let's put the indication of...
Starts out here at nothing.
We'll just let it come round through here.
Just, maybe there's
just an indication of
a little path or road.
Little road.
Goes right through like that.
Just a little dabble.
Like it.
Comes right off the
edge of the canvas here.
This is just blue and white.
There we are.
And we'll bring a little
snow right up to it.
Let it just disappear right off the edge.
And you don't have to
be careful or anything.
You can clean that up...
when you come back with the snow,
you can clean up the edges.
You don't have to worry about it.
Just enjoy.
There.
Because maybe,
maybe the wind's blowing the snow
half way over this little road.
You just can't make out
that there's a road there.
The old cows in the barn.
You gotta get up there
and take him some hay.
All right.
Don't want the old cow left out.
A little touch of the
alizarin crimson into the...
Least little touch into the white.
And maybe
nice distinct something right there
just to break it up.
There we go.
Little touch more of that crimson.
That gives it a little warm effect.
There.
See, it creates a whole other plain there,
even in the snow.
You know, look at this.
I think this farm's deserted.
The more I look at it, the more I think
I think this old farm were
abandoned, this place.
Yeah, all right.
Let's take a little of that brown.
Little paint thinner.
Liner brush.
Very thin paint.
Lot of it on the bristles.
Liner brush holds a lot of paint.
Maybe in our world...
Yup, maybe there's an old fence left here.
We can just do this
with a little liner brush.
As they go away from you,
let them get smaller
and closer together.
Closer together.
There. See?
And that'll help create
that illusion of distance.
Now, maybe there's a little snow on there.
I'll just dip into a little
bit of the liquid white.
Just pure liquid white
and we'll put the
indication of a little snow
hanging up here on some of these.
There.
(makes dropping sounds)
There they are.
Gotta make those little noises though,
or it won't work.
Take just the knife
and I'll go through a little bit of brown.
Use just the heel of the knife.
(makes swooshing noise)
Go right down, we'll put a
little wire on that fence.
Just the heel.
So, let it get wider as it comes forward.
There. Two strands of wire.
That easy.
Wish it was that easy to
put that wire on your house.
Maybe there's a...
There's another old post up here.
I don't know.
Some kind of big old
post that lives there.
Little liquid white.
Need a little something hanging on him.
Sometimes it's nice to add a little blue
to the liquid white.
It'll make your snow look colder.
Much, much colder.
Let's use a one-inch brush.
I'm gonna go into a little white,
a little bit of the blue.
Little white, little bit of blue.
I want this to be sort of a,
a medium blue.
In our world,
maybe there's a few little
bushes that live back here.
I'm just looking for a little dark color
to make some light show up.
Maybe there's a happy bush lives there.
Looks like a tree.
Maybe,
maybe there's another one right in here.
I don't know.
Maybe this gentleman takes
care of his yard like I did
and the bushes and the
trees are growing up
and taking over his farm.
Now,
another white
or another one-inch brush
going to liquid white.
Now, most important how
you load this brush.
Come right down here and watch here.
Pull that brush in one direction.
Isn't that a great close up?
That is fantastic.
Pull that brush in one direction.
Load a lot of color in it.
Watch.
Now, I'm gonna turn it over.
See how that's rounded?
You want that rounded
corner to go to the top.
You can also see right there,
we just taped this furrows.
I had people write in and they say
how come your brush looks
different than mine?
We put a little tape on those furrows
just to keep them from shining on TV.
It's identical to your brush.
Guarantee.
Now, with that nice, white color,
all you gotta to is just go
up here and barely touch.
Just barely touch.
We'll put a few highlights on these
snow covered now.
There.
Over in here.
Just a few little things.
Don't want a lot.
Just a few.
Now, my brush has got white on.
It'll work just as well.
Come in here.
And with that, you can very gently
clean up the bottom.
Sort of begin to bring all this together.
Just using white paint.
There. Pull that out.
See there.
We didn't add a simple
and super little,
little way to do,
maybe like a little farm
scene in the winter.
Now, if you live some place
where there's a lot of farms,
you can look around
and see the type of farms
that are in your area
and paint them to match
what you're used to seeing.
It's up to you.
It's really up to you.
I just wanna show you how to do this.
What you do
is very individual.
All right.
Something like so.
Okay.
Shoot, I think we about got it here.
You might take...
Let's say this guy didn't keep his
grass cut very good,
so maybe around here,
we can put a few little sticks and twigs
around some of these posts.
They usually grow there because
you can't cut close to them.
There.
Something like it.
Let's take a little red,
a little paint thinner,
thin it down 'til it's the consistency,
almost the consistency of ink
and let's sign this little rascal
right there.
Just like so.
If your paint's very thin,
it'll flow right over the
top of this thick paint.
That easy.
Hope you've enjoyed this one.
It's a very, very simple little painting.
If you've never painted before,
this one you can do.
From all of us there,
I'd like to wish you happy painting
and God bless, my friend.
(mellow music)