- Welcome back.
Today I'd thought we'd do
a little picture that's
little different than
what we've been doing.
And today I wanna emphasize
how to do several ranges
of mountains and have
some in the background
that are very quiet, and very
distant and then come forward
with it and let's see what happens here.
I've already prepared
the canvas with a layer
of magic white, just
brushed in both directions.
Okay, we'll start with a
little bit of Persian blue
and we're really working to
the bristles of the brush.
And we'll start right at the top
working across
and we're picking up the magic
white as we go across here
and automatically it
makes the sky get lighter
as it works downward.
We don't want a sky that
just looks like you
pulled the curtain down.
We're trying to avoid those.
Okay, let me real
hypnotize it a little bit.
Okay.
And while we've got some
blue on the brush here,
we might as well go ahead and
put in a little bit of water here.
This is still the Persian blue.
And we'll just hypnotize
this a little bit,
bring it all together.
Anyway it doesn't matter where
you get your waterline here
because when you put
all the other stuff in,
you can bring it to
whatever points you want it
so don't worry about it.
Okay.
We will wash this old brush.
Alrighty, let's take some blue
and a little bit of brown
and little bit of white
just to make a gray color, blue gray here.
And maybe we're gonna have
this mountain come way up
on the canvas, what the heck.
And just let it roll around.
We're gonna have a little bump right there
and let it wander right on off.
Very little paint and
we're pushing that paint
right into the canvas,
just really push it.
And we'll put a little bump right there,
another little hill.
Okay, now we'll take and
pull that paint down.
We want it to get lighter as it goes
toward the horizon here.
So we pull it down.
Once again it's mixing
with the magic white
that's already on the canvas
and automatically this occurs.
Pull this one down a little.
Okay.
Like so.
Now this time we want very little paint,
very little paint.
All we wanna do is give
little indications back here.
Just a little,
few little highlights.
Light plane right through here.
And you'll find if you're right handed,
it's normally easier to have the light
coming from the right.
If you're left handed it will
vary from person to person.
So you have to find what's
comfortable for you,
and maybe a little spec of
light back here on that point.
Okay, maybe we'll just let
these two work their way
together here.
Just make an almighty ridge
coming right through there.
There we go.
Now, for the shadow we'll
use a little blue and white,
little touch of brown with it.
Let's put a little shadow right here.
Don't want a great deal
in the shadows this time,
just a little bit.
Maybe a little touch over in here.
Few little things happening
all along the way.
Little bit too straight so I'm
gonna break that up a little
so it doesn't look too round.
Don't want it to look
phony, want it to look real.
Okay now I'm gonna
really diffuse this one.
I want it to just about disappear.
Even gonna work a little bit in there,
and we'll lift upward.
Always follow the angles that
you've built in your mountain.
Always work with those angles.
Okay now let's build
another one, little closer.
This time I'm gonna put
a little Alizarin in blue
to give it a little
bit more of a purplish,
little touch of brown to dull it.
All right.
And let's take this one and
run right up through here.
Now this being so dark
should push everything back.
Maybe a little bump there.
Want this just to be a nice
slow lowling a little hill.
And just get in there and
do it, thing like that.
Don't worry about it, let it happen.
There.
And we'll pull this down a little bit.
One reason we do so many
mountains in this series
is to teach you to use the knife
that you can make mountains,
you've made friends with the knife
then you can do just about
anything you wanna do with it.
Okay, maybe we'll take a
little blue and white here.
Maybe there's a few little
patches of snow laying on this
just here and there.
Just let those work down here and there.
There.
And maybe there's a little snow land
right in here somewhere.
Just sort of bring that together.
Okay and we'll take a little
bit of the blue and brown
and put some sap green with it.
There we go, very dark,
it should look black.
And now we'll load the brush up.
And let's just do some
little things like this.
I want some little indication of trees
way back in the distance back here.
And maybe a few of them have
just a little bit more detail
so we can just add a
little bit here and there.
We're only looking for
basic shapes as far back.
You would not see a great deal of detail.
And here and there nice little trees.
Add a little more shape.
Okay.
A lot of paint on the
brush, very, very thick.
Just like so.
Okay, now then we can take
and just scratch a few
little trunks here and there.
And all we're doing here is
using the point of the knife
and cutting through the
paint so the canvas shows.
And it gives the illusion of little trunks
way back in the distance.
And you don't have to worry
about cutting through the canvas
with this knife.
The canvas is very, very strong
and we recommend that
you use stretch canvas
rather than canvas boards.
The canvas boards have
cardboard in the center
and they have a tendency
to absorb your magic white
very rapidly and leave
you with a dry canvas.
And we depend on this being wet
through the whole picture.
Okay, now let's take
little gray,
a little yellow and red
all mixed together here
and let's start putting some
land coming down through here.
And all we're gonna do is just push.
Like so.
All the little grassy
things happening here.
And maybe here and there we can see little
parts of the dirt showing through,
little areas where there's
some ground showing.
So we just lay that in.
And then you can just
go back and push it down
into the picture, put things
that are projecting over it.
Little more magic here,
have to have a thin paint to
make it stick on all these.
And as these come out of the shadow,
let them get a little brighter.
These trees with shadow all back in there.
So you want this to get a
little brighter as it comes out.
There we go.
And let's take and pull just
a little bit of this down
into the water.
There we go.
And then we'll just, just
hypnotize it a little bit,
just make it come together.
Here I'm adding just a little bit of dark.
We have two light areas so we'll
put a touch of dark in here
just to separate these,
very, very little paint.
Okay, now let's take
a little Vandyke brown
and we'll just go right along here and
build me some little shore.
Here all we're doing
is touching the canvas.
Okay, and we can put a
few little sticks in here
while we have some color on the knife.
You know what, when people
see all these little
sticks and stuff, they think
you've spent days and days
with your one haired brush sitting here
doing all these little rascals,
and when you get them believing that
then you up the price of it.
For a long time I've painted
this way in the secrecy
of my home and charged unbelievable prices
which a lot of painters are doing now.
But if people see it takes you 30 minutes
then they don't wanna pay you
an unbelievable price for it.
They wanna pay you 30 minutes labor, so
you have to make a decision
whether you wanna be a
traditional artist or an
artist that eats regular.
And we'll lay some little
ripples along the water here,
just here and there.
Okay, now
maybe we'll take some of this dark color
and let's put a little tree
right here, what the heck.
Like so.
And we'll take and pull
some of that paint down,
make this little reflection.
Put a little tree trunk in.
And we'll lay a little
highlight right along here
just so it stands out.
And then we need some leaves on it
so I'm gonna drop a few
little leaves here and there.
There we go.
Very light touch,
don't want to destroy.
And we'll use just a little
bit of the Vandyke here.
Okay,
now let's put something in the foreground.
We will have all kind of
nice little bushes and stuff
just growing around here.
And let's put something right here.
There we go.
And we'll highlight these real quick.
Look at that, all those
little leaves and bushes
and you can do it.
You can do it,
just practice a little,
load a lot of paint to the brush.
Remember thin paints
stick to a thick paint.
Maybe just a little greenery on this.
A little something right there.
Okay, a few little sticks.
Now let's get brave.
Let's have a huge limb coming out here
like there's a three over here somewhere
and all you can see is
a big limb coming out.
I know this is scary to
take in and put something like this
right out through all
the work you went through
but give it a try one time.
And maybe we have one
coming down through here.
And then we can have some
little limbs coming off these,
all kinds of little things happening here.
Wherever you want them just drop them in.
And there's a little something
just protruding right up here.
Okay, now
you could put just a little
bit of highlight on here
just to break it up.
Shows a little sunlight is hitting.
Yeah.
Now let's lay some leaves on top of them
and we first need some dark,
let me get some dark color here.
A little bit of sap, a
little bit of blue and brown.
There we go.
And we'd lay a little
color on the brush here
and now we're just gonna start tapping
where we want some nice
little leaves to be.
Just let them fall in there.
There.
Just sort of helps make a nice
composition of your picture
and push everything back.
Think you'll like this once you try it.
And as I say first time is sort of the
son of a gun distance
through all these right up
in the middle of your picture.
It's gonna scare you a little bit.
But jump in there and do it.
Remember you're the master.
This canvas is afraid of you.
You're the master.
Okay, now we can take
a lighter color green,
a little more magic in it.
And we'll load this brush full
and think where your light is coming from.
The top of these are
gonna be a little brighter
than the bottom so we'll just
lay a little bit of color
right along the top here.
This is where you need
a good brush though.
Be very careful about the brush you use.
Avoid nylon brushes, they cut paint.
These are natural bristle brushes.
Put the color right in here.
I always remember back when
I was a traditional painter
how long I would agonize trying
to do something like this
with the little one haired brush
and working for days and days and days
to get an effect that you
can now get in minutes.
Okay.
There we go,
and we have almighty limbs projecting
right out in our picture
and makes it look like
there's a tree over here.
Okay, maybe,
maybe right in here.
Let's do this.
Let's have an old tree that's falling over
coming right up through here.
If you got all your nerve
up and done this one,
shoot, we might as well
just keep going with it.
No use letting you stop now.
And maybe he had a little
friend that fell over with him.
There we go.
Now don't laugh, trees need friends too.
Everybody needs friends.
Okay.
Take a little white and little brown here.
Now you'll put just a
least little touch of
sort of an orangey color in it.
And we're gonna just
work that right down here
and make him look old and tired,
just barely touching.
Just pull that right along
like so.
Let it go.
Okay, now we'll take
and put a few little bushes in front
so he has a place for his foot to sit.
And we'll take the liner brush,
a little bit of thin oil like so.
There we go.
And we'll put a few little
limbs hanging on here
that are just about going,
just here and there.
Let them go wherever which
way, whatever makes them happy.
And maybe this one is just hanging down.
He's tired,
poor old thing.
There.
This old tree is just about going,
it's gonna fall over here in the pond.
Maybe a little limb or two left up here,
something like so.
Okay, I think we'll sign that one
and call it finished
and there we go.
And I'd like to thank you very, very much
for watching us today.
I hope you've enjoyed this painting
and that you've painted along with us
and until next time, happy painting.
Thank you very, very much.
(lively music)
(calm music)